<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three sermons preached by that learned and reuerend diuine, Doctor Eedes, sometimes dean of Worcester, for their fitnesse vnto the present time, now published by Robert Horn ...</title>
            <author>Eedes, Richard, 1555-1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 237 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100344</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">39961074</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 39961074</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150376</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73905)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150376)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 643:18 or 1943:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three sermons preached by that learned and reuerend diuine, Doctor Eedes, sometimes dean of Worcester, for their fitnesse vnto the present time, now published by Robert Horn ...</title>
                  <author>Eedes, Richard, 1555-1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.M. for Philemon Stephens and Christopher Meredith, and are to be sold at the Golden Lyon in Pauls Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-O⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: item at reel 1943:6 stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in: Folger Shakespeare Library and Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>The Christians admission and foundation in Gods household -- The Christians guide to a wise conuersation -- The short prosperitie of the wicked and the happy estate of the iust.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150376:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THREE SERMONS PREACHED BY THAT LEARNED and reuerend Diuine Doctor EEDES ſometimes Deane of WORCESTER.</p>
            <p>For their fitneſſe vnto the preſent time, now publiſhed, by ROBERT HORN Miniſter of Gods WORD.</p>
            <p>The ſeuerall titles and Texts follow on the next page.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLES. 12.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Preacher ſought to finde out acceptable words, and that which was written, was vpright, euen words of truth.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Philemon Stephens</hi> and <hi>Christopher Meredith,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Golden Lyon in <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard. 1627.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150376:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <pb facs="tcp:150376:3"/>
            <head>The Chriſtians Admiſſion and foundation in Gods houſhold.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>The Text. EPHES. 2.19, 20, 21, 22.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yee are no more ſtrangers and forreiners, but fellow Citizens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And are built vpon the foundation of the Apostles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe being the chiefe corner ſtone, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>The Chriſtians Guide to a wiſe Conuerſation.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EPHES. 5.15, 16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Take heede that yee walke circumſpectly; not as fooles, but as wiſe:</p>
               <p>Redeeming the time: for the dayes are euill.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="quotation">
            <head>The ſhort proſperitie of the wicked, and the Happy eſtate of the IVST</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 37.35, 36, 37.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I haue ſeene the wicked in great power: and ſpreading him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe like a greene Bay-tree.</p>
               <p>Yet hee paſſed away, and loe hee was not: yea, I ſought him, but he could not be found.</p>
               <p>Marke the perfect man, and behold the vpright: for the end of that man is peace.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150376:3"/>
            <head>THE PVBLISHER to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD Reader: the ſubſtance of theſe Sermons was long ſince preached by a reuerend and learned Deane, Doctor <hi>Eedes</hi> Deane of <hi>Worceſter;</hi> which being giuen me in ſundry broken and caſt papers after his death, I peruſed at my times of leaſure; and perceiuing they might be of vſe to many by Printing, I was very vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to engroſe them for priuate vſe from publique benefit. And that made mee thus to ſet them together as I could, with ſome ſupply where any thing was wanting, and where the reading was troubleſome, with ſome ſmall alteration. Thou haſt them (therefore) not altogether as they were
<pb facs="tcp:150376:4"/>preached, but as I could copie them from the Authors firſt lines. They concerne the times we liue in as directly and particularly as if they had bin ſet vnto them by the Preacher. If any thing, here ſet downe, may (any whit) <hi>further thy walking in the way of grace,</hi> I thinke my labour this way well paid for. God bleſſe thy reading in this, and other good Bookes, ſpecially in the Booke of God, for which I pray, who am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> ROBERT HORN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150376:4"/>
            <head>THE CHRISTIANS ADMISSION into the houſhold of GOD, and his founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſame.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>EPHES. 2.19, 20, 21, 22.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Yee are no more ſtrangers and forreiners, but fellow Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God:</p>
                     <p>And are built vpon the foundation of the Apostles and Prophets, Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe being the chiefe corner ſtone,</p>
                     <p>In whom all the building fitly framed together, groweth vnto an holy Temple in the Lord:</p>
                     <p>In whom you alſo are builded together for an habitation of God through the ſpirit.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>EE are no more ſtrangers and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reiners, but Citizens, &amp;c.</hi> Great was the goodneſſe of God in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, great in continuing the world for mans ſake: his power in the one, was more then the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> of the world could expreſſe: his loue in the other, is more then the <hi>beſt</hi> of Chriſtians can conceiue: but neither was the creation of the world more then the <hi>electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:150376:5"/>of his Church; nor the continuing of the one, which is great, beyond the preſeruation of the other, which is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. It was much that he created the world <hi>of nothing,</hi> more that <hi>he redeemed</hi> it of nothing: the one <hi>he</hi> did for <hi>vs,</hi> when we were <hi>his</hi> owne, and that without <hi>coſt:</hi> the other, when we <hi>were his enemies,</hi> but not without the <hi>death of his onely ſonne.</hi> Therefore, how much the greater a benefit it was that God ſhould <hi>ſaue vs,</hi> then that <hi>he</hi> ſhould make <hi>vs,</hi> that we ſhould be <hi>borne anew,</hi> then that we ſhould be <hi>borne;</hi> ſo much the better it were for vs not to be <hi>borne,</hi> then not to be <hi>choſen;</hi> and not to <hi>be,</hi> then not to be of <hi>his Church.</hi> Wherein, howſoeuer <hi>Iacob</hi> had a <hi>priuiledge,</hi> and <hi>Iudah</hi> the <hi>prerogatiue;</hi> ſo that they were <hi>choſen</hi> as the <hi>Lillie</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>flowers</hi> of the <hi>field,</hi> as the <hi>ſheepe</hi> before all the <hi>beaſts</hi> of the <hi>earth,</hi> as the <hi>Vine</hi> before all the <hi>trees</hi> of the <hi>Foreſt,</hi> as the <hi>Doue</hi> before all the <hi>birds</hi> of the <hi>aire,</hi> and as his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiare <hi>people</hi> before all the <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>world:</hi> yet was the benefit to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> no leſſe, and the mercy of <hi>God,</hi> to them, a great deale more, that they which <hi>were no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> ſhould bee called a holy people, and which were wild by nature, ſhould by grace, become naturall and legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate branches in the true Oliue, which is the Church of God.</p>
               <p>For which cauſe the Apoſtle, in this place, commendeth to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and, in them, to vs, not onely the eſtate of their calling in Chriſt, but the ground and end thereof in him. In the ſpeaking whereof, that I goe no farther then the words lead me; three things may well and chiefely be obſerued: as firſt, the calling of the Gentiles: ſecondly, their foundation, being called: and thirdly, their building vp. In their calling wee are to conſider from whence, and to what they were called: in their foundation, by whom, and vpon whom they were laid: and in their building vp, how and to what end they were built. They were called from being ſtrangers and forreiners, to be citizens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God. They were laid by the Prophets, and Apoſtles, vpon Chriſt: and they did grow; for the manner, as coupled together, and for the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150376:5"/>end, to bee a holy Temple in the Lord, and the habitation of God by the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>For the firſt: there is no one thing that doeth more mooue a man, to conſider what hee is, then to remember what hee was. So great a light to our iudgements, doeth this light of comparing our ſelues, with our ſelues, bring, and ſo deepe an impreſſion in our hearts, doeth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of that which is paſt being ſet to the preſent, make. For, as there is no miſery greater, then to haue beene happy: ſo is it not the leaſt part of happineſſe to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that we haue beene miſerable. <hi>Adam,</hi> the better hee was in Paradiſe, the worſe hee was out: contrarily, the Gentiles, the further they were from the Couenant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, the greater was their benefit in it. And therefore, as the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> was bidden to remember from whence ſhee was fallen, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.5. that, remembring her great fall, ſhe might ſorrow, and bee more aſhamed, then if ſhe had neuer beene mounted ſo high, in that loue, which the Apoſtle (there) calleth her firſt loue, <hi>verſe</hi> 4. ſo (here) the <hi>Epheſians</hi> are bidden to remember, to what they were raiſed, as from being Gentiles in the fleſh, and ſtrangers in Iſrael, to bee worſhippers in ſpirit, and of the Iſrael of God, that they might thinke more highly of that excellent eſtate, to which they were called, and in him that called them, endeuour to walke more worthy of it. For although health bee welcome to all men, yet to them it is euer moſt welcome, that haue beene moſt ſicke, and though peace be euer ſeaſonable, yet neuer more then after Warre: ſo the grace of God, though it cannot come amiſſe to any; yet where ſinne hath abounded, there it aboundeth much more. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.20.</p>
               <p>And (therefore) not without good cauſe, the Apoſtle, in this place, deſcribing the vocation of the Gentiles, doeth (as alſo in the beginning of the Chapter) put them firſt in minde of that eſtate from which they were called, not to looke backe, as <hi>Lots</hi> wife to Sodom: <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. and ſome Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites to the fleſh-pots of Egypt; but that, by looking into the miſerie of their firſt ſoule condition, they might
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150376:6"/>be brought the ſooner to a loathing of it; and in the baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their old man, might more perfitly ſee and admire the excellent worthineſſe, of their new eſtate in Chriſt. Further, if it pleaſed God, when hee had brought his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of Egypt, &amp; was about to bring them into Canaan, to make that their deliuery out of Egypt ſo great a benefit, as that at the giuing of the Law, hee tooke it for a peece of his ſtile, ſaying; <hi>I the Lord that brought thee out of the Land of Aegypt:</hi> and if afterward, hauing brought them out of Babylon, he would bee remembred by the name of that God, that deliuered them from the land of the North, that is, from the Babylonian yoake, as being a worke of ſo great ſaluation. <hi>Ier.</hi> 16.15. How can it be, but that he would haue vs, who are called to a better inheritance, and from greater dangers, to bee ſo much the more mindfull of our old eſtate, by how much wee are deliuered from a blacker darkeneſſe then that of Egypt, and a more terrible priſon, then that of Babylon? For beſides the naturall infection of our firſt parents, whereby (with all mankinde) our ſoules and bodies were made the veſſels of corruption, and our perſons the bond-ſlaues of ſinne; and beſides that, by them, the image of God was defaced in vs, and we depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of all good thereby, it was added, in the ſecret, but iuſt iudgement of God, to this miſery of our loſt eſtate, that our <hi>father</hi> ſhould bee an <hi>Amorite, and our mother an Hittite:</hi> that, <hi>in our natiuitie, when wee were borne, our nauell ſhould not be cut:</hi> that, <hi>no eye ſhould pitie vs,</hi> and that <hi>we ſhould be caſt out in the open field, to the contempt of our perſon, in the day that we were borne. Ezech.</hi> 16.3, 4, 5. Alſo that wee ſhould bee as the <hi>Mountaines of Gilboa,</hi> vpon which muſt <hi>neither come deaw, nor raine;</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.21. that is, neither <hi>deaw</hi> of grace, nor <hi>raine</hi> of righteouſneſſe. For, (almoſt) for foure thouſand yeeres, none of the fatneſſe of Heauen fell vpon the ſoile of the Gentiles; a little ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling there was vpon <hi>Melchiſedech, Iethro, Iob,</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Niniue, and ſome others, but the fruitfull raine fell vpon the fields of Iſrael, and God watered his own garden onely, not voutchſafing any of his influences to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150376:6"/>fields of the Heathen. And they (generally) ſate in darkeneſſe, ſaue that here and there God opened the eyes, now of one, and then of another, who ſaw the light, though more darkely, then the children of the light did. The table was for Iſraelites, and not for Canaanites; yet ſome crummes fell from the table of the children, at one time, to a Canaanite a woman of ſingular faith, at another time to a woman, conuerted at <hi>Iacobs</hi> well, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles to ſundry others, both men and women, ſtrangers from the knowledge, and loue of the true God; neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, there were not many ſuch, till the wall of partition was broken downe, and men might as eaſily haue num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred them, as a man may a poore mans ſheepe. All the reſt of the Heathen were in palpable darkeneſſe, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>giuen vp to ſtrange luſts, and alienes from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which though they did leaſt feele, that had moſt cauſe, (becauſe as euery man is furtheſt from the knowledge of that happineſſe which is in Chriſt, the further hee is from the acknowledging of his owne great miſery without him,) yet there was no man giuen vp to ſo reprobate a minde, but that by the Diuine light of his darke nature, he might perceiue and ſee, that hee wanted figge leaues to couer his nakedneſſe, knowledge to direct him in his blind way, ability to ſtrengthen him in his weake apprehenſions, and that in himſelfe (as of himſelfe) it were an endleſſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſeeke for, and finde true happineſſe. And thoſe wants of nature, as they made them by nature fearefull, ſo did their feare ingender in them a kinde of reuerence, to worſhip whatſoeuer they thought was able to helpe them, as not onely the Sunne and Moone (which they made their Gods) but whatſoeuer was more vnworthy the name of God.</p>
               <p>Wee read of <hi>Columbus,</hi> a trauailer, that when in the Weſt Indyes he could not obtaine victuals for his army, of a certaine people that worſhipped the Moone, he vſed this ſtratageme. Fore-ſeeing by Aſtronomie that an eclipſe would ſhortly be, he threatned them, that vnleſſe they did
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150376:7"/>releeue his army by ſuch a day and houre, hee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue their god out of Heauen. Which though they made light of when they heard it, yet, becauſe euen light things, in ſo great a matter were not to be neglected, they waited both for the day and houre, that he had ſpoken of, and finding the face of the Moone then to bee darkened, thought that he had power (as hee ſaid) to remooue their God: and therefore, beſides that they made almoſt a god of him, they yealded not their victuals onely to his army, but themſelues to his gouernement.</p>
               <p>That which <hi>Columbus</hi> found in the god of thoſe Indians, may be thought of the other gods of the Heathen; what affiance ſoeuer they put in them, there is a time when they will bee eclipſed. To this opinion of falſe gods that was ioyned (ordinarily) great wickedneſſe of life, and ſo, as there was nothing ſo vile and wicked, that at one time or other, by ſome one or other of that blind world of Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, was not made lawfull. But to bury them, ſpecially the prophaner ſort of them, in their owne mire, and not to ſpeake more of them among Chriſtians; let vs examine whether the light of reaſon, which the more ciuill people among them did liue in, bee not meere darkeneſſe. For which of them did euer goe ſo farre with the ſharpneſſe of their wit, and reach ſo high, or wade ſo deepe with the ripeneſſe of their iudgement, as to come (I doe not ſay) to the knowledge of the true, and great God, whom (as it is written of <hi>Simonides</hi>) the more they ſought, the leſſe they found: but that euen in thoſe things which they moſt ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, might not iuſtly ſay, that the greateſt part of that they knew, was the leaſt of that they knew not? And as for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and vertue, whereof they opened the ſchoole, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, moſt of them who ſpake as though they hated vice, did liue as though they hated vertue;) it was the iudgement of thoſe (whoſe iudgement was moſt receiued) that the nature of good, and of that which we call honeſt, was not ſo much in deed, as in opinion, and cuſtome. Yet, could they not deny that to be true which <hi>Tully,</hi> in one of his bookes <hi>de natura Deor.</hi> Of the nature of Heathen
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150376:7"/>gods, ſpeaketh of, that many did <hi>ſummâ improbitate vti, non ſine ſummâratione;</hi> that is, commit notorious crimes, but not without great helpe of reaſon. Neither could they but erre in other matters, who erred ſo much in that, which was chiefe, to wit, the end of mans life, as that there were ſcarce two found of one opinion.</p>
               <p>But wee, vpon whom it hath pleaſed God, in the riches of his mercy, to ſhed the beames of his louing and bright countenance, and to lighten the darkeneſſe of our reaſon, with the day-ſtarre of his grace, haue learned out of the ſchoole of Chriſt, that the naturall man, (whoſe members are weapons of vnrighteouſneſſe, and fooliſh heart is full of darkeneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21.) doeth not perceiue the things of the ſpirit of God: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. And ſeeking, wee haue found, that his life is vanitie, his vnderſtanding blindneſſe, his iudgement opinion, his reaſon fooliſhneſſe, and his being in the World, but a kind of being in a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, wherein hee is eſtranged from the Citie of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God. For euer ſince hee was, not onely, caſt out of the garden of God, but kept out by the Cherubim, <hi>Gene.</hi> 3.24. hee hath beene a ſtranger to Heauen, hauing had no other acceſſe or entrance thereunto, then it hath pleaſed him, that caſt him out, to giue him by effectuall vocation.</p>
               <p>Now what it is, in this ſenſe, to bee a ſtranger, or bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed man, to be denied the priuiledges, and libertie of our naturall ſoile, and to goe exile, into flat Atheiſme, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the true God, it may bee ſomewhat diſcerned by the bitter, and heauy dayes that goe ouer their heads, who are but put out of their earthly countrey by Tyrants, and but for ſome ſhort time. The naturall affection, that euery man feeles toward his owne countrey, and proper home, may ſufficiently teach vs what it is to bee ſtrangers, from our countrey of Heauen, and not for a ſhort time, or life, but for euer. In other baniſhments, wee may finde ſome remedy, one place to vs, may be as good as another, and we are (all) <hi>Socrates</hi> his countrey men, that is, (as he was wont to ſay) Citizens of the World, and therefore baniſhed but out of one part of our countrey, into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150376:8"/>but hee that is thruſt out of this Citie, is thruſt out of all, and though he dwell in the faireſt Cities of the World, yet doeth he but liue the life of one that wanders in a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, and hath no Citie to dwell in.</p>
               <p>Againe, whereas in other baniſhments, we are denied but a temporall freedome, and ſuffer onely the loſſe of goods and liuings, in this our baniſhment from heauen, we are <hi>put</hi> from an euerlaſting <hi>freedome,</hi> and looſe, not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, but <hi>true riches;</hi> nor ſome <hi>temporall,</hi> but an <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall inheritance,</hi> nor liuing onely, but <hi>life</hi> alſo; and not this <hi>ſhort life,</hi> but the <hi>life that endureth euer,</hi> the <hi>life</hi> of ſaluation, and the bleſſed <hi>life</hi> of the <hi>Saints in glory.</hi> And where in other caſes, our baniſhment may bee vniuſt, and our exile for righteouſneſſe, and ſo, wee (the baniſhed) may haue, for the ſupply of our <hi>naturall ſoile,</hi> the pleaſant <hi>paradiſe</hi> of our good conſcience to <hi>walke in:</hi> in this caſe, to be <hi>caſt out of Heauen,</hi> is worthy to be <hi>caſt out;</hi> and, in the puniſhment of it ſelfe, what good conſcience can <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue vs,</hi> when it is iuſt, and deſerued? And now, as the ſtate of them, who are <hi>ſtrangers</hi> from the <hi>citie</hi> of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is miſerable enough, ſeeing they are denied the libertie that is ſo much worth; ſo is their miſery doubled by this, that they haue made themſelues worthy of it, being <hi>depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the glory of God, becauſe they haue ſinned, Rom.</hi> 3.23. partly by not <hi>vnderſtanding,</hi> which was the <hi>darkeneſſe of their minde,</hi> &amp; partly (but principally) by not <hi>ſeeking after God,</hi> which was the frowardneſſe of their will, and becauſe they would haue it ſo. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.11. For, <hi>they gaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ouer to worke all vncleaneneſſe, euen with greedineſſe. Epheſ.</hi> 4.19.</p>
               <p>But, what this is we ſhall better vnderſtand, if we exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thoſe titles, with the which the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, doth deſcribe &amp; <hi>ſtile</hi> thoſe Chriſtians, that were <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles:</hi> where, <hi>hee</hi> calleth them (firſt) <hi>Gentiles in the fleſh, Epheſ.</hi> 2.11. which name, though it were a common name to the Nations of the <hi>Earth,</hi> yet was it (now) and was holden a name of as great reproach to them of <hi>Gods citie,</hi> as the name of <hi>Barbarian</hi> to a <hi>Grecian,</hi> and the name of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150376:8"/>
                  <hi>Turke</hi> to a <hi>Christian.</hi> The reaſon was, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were great <hi>Idolaters;</hi> and the <hi>things which they ſacrificed,</hi> they did <hi>ſacrifice to Deuils, and not to God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.20. Alſo, for that <hi>world of wickedneſſe which</hi> they were <hi>giuen vnto,</hi> it was ſuch, as <hi>might not bee named,</hi> that is, which they could not ſpeake of for ſhame. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. And when our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> would put them to the <hi>worſt,</hi> that would not <hi>heare the Church,</hi> the worſt name <hi>he gaue</hi> them, as the worſt, that could be giuen them, was the name of a <hi>Heathen: Mat.</hi> 18.17.</p>
               <p>So the <hi>Apostle,</hi> in this Epiſtle, exhorting theſe <hi>Epheſians to watch ouer</hi> their liues, and <hi>themſelues</hi> with ſome care and diligence, forbids them to <hi>walke as other Gentiles,</hi> that is as the worſt ſort of men. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.17. No leſſe opprobrious was the name that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> gaue them in the ſecond place, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 2.11. by calling them the <hi>vncircumciſion;</hi> it being the marke, by which they were diſtinguiſhed and knowne, from Gods <hi>peculiar people.</hi> And therefore it is ſaid, that no <hi>ſtranger that is vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in heart, or vncircumciſed in</hi> fleſh ſhall <hi>enter into the Sanctuary of God;</hi> accounting all to be <hi>ſtrangers from God,</hi> and <hi>Gods peculiar inheritance,</hi> that are ſuch. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 44.9. For this cauſe, doeth <hi>Dauid</hi> call <hi>Golijah</hi> the vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed <hi>Philiſtim:</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.26. and <hi>Saul</hi> deſired his Armour-bearer to kill him, leaſt hee ſhould fall into the hands of the vncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtims:</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.4. and <hi>Steuen</hi> drawing a Metaphore from hence, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.51. cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the deſperate Iewes, men of vncircumciſed hearts and eares. Thirdly, he calles them (when they were Heathen) men without <hi>Chriſt; Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. that is, without the hope and grace of the bleſſed Seed in Chriſt: and not ſo onely, but alienes from the common Wealth of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> that is, from the externall profeſſion, and outward fellowſhip of the <hi>Church;</hi> and thereby, ſtrangers from the Couenant of Promiſe, becauſe they knew not his iudgements. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 147.20.</p>
               <p>And hereof enſueth, that which is reckened in the laſt place, that they were not (onely) without hope; becauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150376:9"/>without the Law, and Word, in which were the Promiſes, by which Hope is perfited; but without God in the World, becauſe without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by whom, and by whom (onely we know him.) Thus by their names, we ſee their deedes, as we ſee a face in a glaſſe. Their wiſedome, was but the wiſedome of the fleſh, and they did ſinne in the beſt things, that they beſt did. For, they had not faith, and without it, it is impoſſible to pleaſe God: <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6. the Scripture ſaith ſo, though the Church of Rome ſay other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, becauſe they would eſtabliſh, if not the freedome of Mans will, yet, at the leaſt, the pureneſſe of their impure naturals, thereby. And therefore wee ſay with Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> that <hi>virtutes Gentium quâdam indole animi ita delectant, vt eos, in quibus fuerint, vellemus praecipuè ab inferni cruciatibus liberari, niſi aliter ſenſus humanus, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Creatoris iuſtitia ſe haberet:</hi> the vertues of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles for a certaine good intent they ſeeme to beare, doe ſo delight vs, that wee could wiſh them free from Hell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but that there is one reaſon of mans thinking, and another of the Diuine iuſtice. For, if the regenerate and beleeuers themſelues, while they are at home in the body, are abſent from the Lord, 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5.6. how can they bee neere him, that are not yet called, and whoſe eſtate, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their ſauage life, is compared to a deſert, and the men in it, to Dragons and Oſtriches in the wilderneſſe? <hi>Iob</hi> 30.29.</p>
               <p>And who are called, in the Scripture, not workers but ſeruants of vnrighteouſneſſe? And not ſicke, but dead in ſinnes, and treſpaſſes? And not people of God, but children of wrath? And giuen vp, not to the darkeneſſe, but blindneſſe of their vnderſtandings? To walke in all, not wantonneſſe onely, but vncleaneneſſe; not through infirmitie of nature, but with greedineſſe of will and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection? Which being ſo, and a greate deale worſe then either the tongue of man can expreſſe, or his heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, my words, nay my thoughts are ſwallowed vp with the due conſideration of this firſt benefit, being the new-birth of our Chriſtianitie, that wee are no more ſtrangers,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150376:9"/>and no more forrainers; and yet, what is this to that which now followeth, that we ſhould become.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Citizens with the Saints, and of the houſehold of God?</hi> Though theſe two are coupled together, with ſo neceſſary a chaine of coherence, that he who leaues to be a ſtranger, beginnes to be a Citizen, and hee that is no more a forrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, is foorthwith one of the houſhould of God; yet, as God, when hee paſſed by and ſaw his Church, in her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, polluted in her owne blood, thought it not enough to waſh her with water, and to annoint her with oyle, ſpreading ouer her his skirts of loue to couer her filthines; but cloathed her with Silkes, and decked her with Iewels, and other beautifull ornaments, that ſhee might grow into a Kingdome; <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.8, 9.12, 13. So, though it were much that God ſhould take from vs the euils of our old eſtate, yet he thought it not enough, vnleſſe hee gaue and adorned vs with the riches of our new calling; and though it were an exceeding great benefit, and more then wee could hope for, to bee deliuered from being any longer ſtrangers and forrainers; yet, hee that is rich in giuing, would not here ſtay, as if he had done enough, vnleſſe hee had (alſo) made vs Citizens with his owne houſhold people, and of his owne family, and peculiar charge. Where, if the diſproportion betweene God and man ſeeme ſo great, as that it muſt needes ſeeme a hard matter, for fleſh and blood to conceiue, how God ſhould giue ſo vile a creature as man, ſo worthy an eſtate, as of being a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen with his Angels, and houſhold people, let vs know that, as <hi>Alexander</hi> told a priuate meane perſon, to whom hee gaue a whole Citie, that though it were beyond the proportion of his eſtate, yet he ſhould conſider, not what hee was to take, but what became him to giue: ſo this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, (which is great indeed) is to be meaſured with the yard of the giuer, and not by the baſeneſſe of vs on whom it is beſtowed: and that (here) it was conſidered, not what wee deſerued to receiue, but what ſtood with Gods good pleaſure to giue, without deſert, to vs that haue receiued ſo much: the rather, becauſe he who is rich in mercy, holds
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150376:10"/>himſelfe to be neither rich nor great, except he make vs rich in receits, and himſelfe great, by giuing to vs: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he is ſaid to make vs worthy of that eſtate to which he calleth vs. And yet further (which maketh the benefit great in it ſelfe greater to vs) we are not onely admitted into this Citie, as free-Deniſons, but adopted into the family as Sonnes, and of the houſhold of God. Neither are we ſonnes onely by (ſuch) adoption, but heires, yea, fellow heires with Chriſt. Beſides, in the manner of our adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wee haue no ſmall aduantage: for, whereas men doe rather finde them fit whom they adopt into their houſe, then make them ſo: to bee adopted in Chriſt, is to bee made worthy, in him, of the inheritance to which we are called, and with the gift of the ſonne is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the grace of new-birth. So the Apoſtle; <hi>Whom he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knew, them he predestinated to be made conformable to the image of his Sonne, that he might be the firſt borne among many brethren, Rom.</hi> 8.29. and therefore, God did not onely make vs ſonnes, but make vs fit to be ſonnes in an inheritance that fadeth not, reſerued in heauen for vs.</p>
               <p>Againe, whereas adoption among men, takes effect onely by ſucceſſion, and ſo as the adopted doth not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in the inheritance, till he be dead that adopted him: he that is adopted to this ſpirituall inheritance of Saints, is preſently poſſeſſed of it with him that gaue it. To this may be added that notable ſaying of Saint <hi>Austin, haereditas in quâ Christi cohaeredes ſumus, non minuitur multitudine filiorum, nec ſit anguſtior numeroſitale cohaeredum; ſed tanta eſt multis, quanta paucis, tanta ſingulis, quanta omnibus;</hi> that is, the inheritour of Chriſt is neither diminiſhed by the multitude of ſonnes, nor made narrower by the number of heires; but it is as great to many as to few, and as much to euery one as it is to all: for, ſince the Lord did enlarge the place of his tents, and ſpread out the curtaines of his habitations, the Churches in which he dwelleth with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Eſay</hi> 54.2. ſince he remoued the wall of partition, and opened the doore of faith to the Gentiles, there hath bin no reſpect either of Iew or Gentile, bond or free, male or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150376:10"/>female, but of a new creature: which, as it cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God the Father, ſo neither can it ſtand without the Church the Mother; more then he may haue Chriſt to be his head, that is not a member of his body, the Church. And this carrieth ſuch a neceſſity with it, that as there was no ſafety without the Arke, nor hope without the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: ſo, neither is there any liberty without this Citie, nor inheritance but in this family: to which neceſſity there commeth this dignitie, as it were recompence; that this Citie is the fellowſhip of Saints, and this fellowſhip of Saints the very houſhold of God. And, what greater pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue; ſeeing that, hereby, he who dwelleth aboue the heauens vouchſafeth to haue an habitation vpon his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole, the earth; and by ſuch a conſociation with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to vnite the true members of this earthly houſe to that Ieruſalem, which is aboue, and free, the mother of vs all?</p>
               <p>And, albeit there be in this Citie (many times) enemies as well as friends, and ſtrangers as Citizens; alſo, <hi>veſſels of honour and diſhonour, children of promiſe and children of wrath;</hi> yet of this Citie there are none, nor of this houſe, but they that are <hi>ſealed with the bloud of the Lambe,</hi> and with the word of his teſtimony to newneſſe of life, and to be <hi>holy, and without blame before him in loue, Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. who, becauſe they are the true members and liuely parts of this ſpirituall habitation of God, therefore, and for their ſakes, it is called the <hi>Citie of the Saints,</hi> and <hi>houſhold of faith;</hi> and by <hi>Dauid</hi> the Prophet, <hi>the congregation of the iuſt, Pſal.</hi> 111.1. the benefit whereof, howſoeuer they that little know doe leſſe regard, yet they that haue any feeling of the Spirit muſt needes confeſſe, and ſay with the ſame Prophet; that <hi>they are bleſſed that may dwell in this houſe;</hi> and that (for the time) <hi>one day in thoſe Courts is more worth then a thouſand yeares elſewhere, Pſal.</hi> 84.4.10. yea, here, they will wiſh rather to be doore-keepers, that is meaneſt in office, and leaſt in place, then to be great or higheſt in the <hi>tabernacles of wickedneſſe, ver.</hi> 10. the reaſon is; here, the Lord God is ſunne and ſhield vnto them; their ſunne
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150376:11"/>in the miſts of aduerſitie, and their ſhield of defence in trouble, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. here they may <hi>behold the beautie of the Lord,</hi> is to ſee his goodneſſe in the face of Chriſt: and to be <hi>ſatisfied with his pleaſures,</hi> is to <hi>receiue of his fulneſſe,</hi> that grace or meaſure of grace that cauſeth true ioy, and bringeth entire and ſound comfort with it to the perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpirit of man: both which imply a <hi>change of our vile eſtate,</hi> and (as it were) a new birth in it; by the which not onely the blinde eyes of our vnderſtandings are ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the <hi>old man cast off with his workes;</hi> but our hard hearts are ſoftned to the will of God, and the new man raiſed vp in vs to righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe, in the obedience of faith according to the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>They that thus <hi>behold the beautie of the Lord,</hi> are no longer in darkneſſe; for in <hi>his light, ſhall we ſee light:</hi> and, as it fared with the children of Iſrael, who had light in their quarters, when the reſt of Egypt was couered with palpable darkneſſe: ſo, howſoeuer the Prince of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth caſt a miſt of errour, and ſpread a cloud of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance vpon the children of vnbeliefe; yet the Sunne of righteouſneſſe, in this Citie of his ſpirituall Iſrael, and in the proper horizon of the children of faith, ſhall make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall day-light; ſo ſcattering all clouds, miſts, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtings, that no night ſhall be therein, neither any going downe of the Sunne, <hi>Eſay</hi> 60.20. which Sunne, becauſe he ſhineth in our mindes, and giueth his word to this Citie, as his beames in our hearts; therefore would he haue vs to frame our ſelues to this cleare light of the Goſpel, which is preached to vs, <hi>and to walke as in the day;</hi> furniſhed with the armour of the light in the true knowledge of the ſame Goſpell, with faith and ſound obedience, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt the darkneſſe of our ignorance, and the Prince thereof, ſo as we may be called (no longer) darkneſſe, but light in the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8. And therefore the Church, in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>cloathed with the Sunne,</hi> and to haue <hi>the Moone vnder her feet, Apoc.</hi> 10.1. ſo the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in the Church muſt be cloathed with Chriſt and his workes; and tread downe the world and his vanities, as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150376:11"/>contemptible things. They that doe ſo, that is, put on Chriſt, doe fully, by that faith they haue in him, enioy all the liberties and whole freedome of this Citie: as that there ſhall be no condemnation to them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. that all things, euen their very ſinnes and the diuell, their tempter to ſinne, ſhall <hi>worke to the beſt for them:</hi> that they haue the right of ſonnes, and by ſuch right, a lawfull intereſt to Chriſt and his merits: that the hand-writing or obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Lawes that was againſt them, is done away, and an acquittance ſealed to them in his bloud and death, who tooke vp their bond, and (as a booke vtterly cancelled) faſtned it to his Croſſe, neuer to be of force any more: that they behold a moſt ſeuere Iudge in the face of a Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and by him may challenge their generall pardon, in his death: that they haue <hi>free acceſſe to God the Father by Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and may be ſure to <hi>receiue whatſoeuer they aske in his name:</hi> that, beſides large immunities from all kinde of bondage to ſinne, they are endowed plentifully and richly with the graces of the ſpirit to righteouſneſſe: that, by the Word and Sacraments rightly adminiſtred, they get and retaine that peace of conſcience, that no man (euer) well conceiued, but he that firſt receiued it: and, in a word, that they haue for aſſurance of ſaluation in the God of their ſaluation: theſe are, and are ſure to be the franchiſes of Citizens and ſons, that are in Chriſt, and are followers of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And, who rightly conſidering this in heart, may not cry out with the Apoſtle, <hi>O altitudo? O, the deepeneſſe of the riches</hi> both of the mercy and loue of God to mankinde? <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33. that when we were nothing, he ſhould make vs? and when we were worſe then nothing, hee ſhould doe ſo much, ſo exceeding much, for vs? that, when we lay polluted in our bloud, hee ſhould waſh vs with his owne precious bloud? and when we were ſold vnder ſin, redeeme vs with a price, from the condemnation of ſinne? that he ſhould giue himſelfe, for ſo vile creatures, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake ſo ſhamefull a death for ſo ſhameleſſe offenders? or, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> notes, he ſhould be that which we are, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150376:12"/>we might be that which he is: It is a ſtrange thing that the Poets faine of <hi>Amphion,</hi> that with the ſweetneſſe of his Muſicke, he drew trees and ſtones together to the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Thebes:</hi> the morall is; that by his wiſdome and ſweet elocution, which was as muſicke to their cares, he drew a rude people, that dwelt in woods, to ciuilitie and manners; and to liue in ſocietie, that liued ſauagely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. That which the Poets haue fained of <hi>Amphion</hi> and <hi>Thebes,</hi> is moſt true in Chriſt and his Church: for, with his word, as with the muſicke of heauen, he called the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and of them, as of ſtones, raiſed vp children to <hi>Abraham, Mat</hi> 3.9. and he made them that were <hi>Gentiles,</hi> no longer <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that is, ſtrangers, but ſonnes: and thoſe that were vncircumciſed in the fleſh, circumciſed in the ſpirit: and the old men of ſin, the new borne of God: and thoſe without Chriſt, the very members of Chriſt: and thoſe heires of promiſe, that had no hope: and thoſe that were aliens from Iſrael, partakers with Iſrael of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of life: and ſtrangers, Citizens: and farre of, neere: and without God in the world, Gods children: and no people, a glorious people.</p>
               <p>Yet becauſe, he is not a <hi>Iewe,</hi> that is outwardly one; and becauſe <hi>many that are called, few are choſen;</hi> therefore, we that are Citizens, muſt liue as Citizens; not the worlds Citizens, but Citizens with the Saints. <hi>Ieruſalem is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as a Citie that is compact together, Pſal.</hi> 122.3. this was ſpoken of the earthly, and may well be applied, both to the ſpirituall <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the Church of Grace, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, which is the Church in glory: for, we muſt not thinke that Gods delight was any way, ſet vpon timher and ſtone; or, at any time, vpon faire and well compacted buildings: but this was rather to admoniſh the Citizens, then to praiſe the Citie, teaching them, that if God be pleaſed with ſuch an vniformitie and compactedneſſe in materiall buildings, much more will he reſpect in them (his owne building by grace) ſpirituall order and compacted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde. And ſo, if the Citizens at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> muſt be in order to God; ſhall the Citizens in the Goſpel
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150376:12"/>breake order, and liue in no conformity to him? Are we (then) Citizens of God? we muſt keepe Gods order, and not what rule we liſt in his Citie: we muſt honour his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and word, reuerence his name and Sabbaths, bow to him onely and to no creature with him; keepe his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and obſerue his lawes.</p>
               <p>The Magiſtrates that watch his gates, muſt ſee that no prophaneneſſe be either practiſed or countenanced within them: they muſt ſee that the good be encouraged, and the euill taken away, or reformed: alſo, that all within their authoritie (as it were gates) ſerue the Lord, or be made to ſerue him.</p>
               <p>The Miniſters muſt faithfully execute their charge in the watch of this Citie: they muſt not be blinde guides, nor ſleepie watchmen: and, they muſt <hi>eate the roule, and goe and ſpeake to the houſe of Iſrael, Ezech.</hi> 3.1. they muſt warne the people of their danger, with the trumpet at their mouth, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33.3, 6. and feeding them with good and ſound teaching, lead them to the pure ſtreames and riuer of life.</p>
               <p>The people, the Citizens, muſt be ruled by the good word of God, and by humaine ordinances and lawes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to it: not reſiſting gouernment, and giuing ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to God, by honouring thoſe powers that are of him. Thus if we be Citizens, we muſt liue as they that dwell in Gods Citie, and not in the worlds foreſt. So if we be of the houſhold of God, we muſt liue as his houſhold ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and ſonnes, and not as ſeruants of ſinne, and ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> and ſo ſhame our Maſters houſe, and diſcredit our Maſters ſeruice: or, we muſt liue, that is, holily liue, as his ſeruants and ſonnes. Now, <hi>holineſſe becommeth Gods houſe, Pſal.</hi> 93.5. and they that are of his houſhold muſt be holy.</p>
               <p>Many get in that are not ſo, but they ſhall be turned out, as hee was, that had not on his wedding garment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.11.13. for God cannot endure that any vncleane perſon, that any <hi>Moabite, Cananite, Iſmalite,</hi> or other ſonne of <hi>Belial</hi> ſhould be witneſſe of his praiſe. <hi>The gates of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150376:13"/>the Lord are gates of righteouſneſſe; and the righteous ſhall enter into them, Pſal.</hi> 118.19. His houſe is the houſe of his honour, and they that be of his houſhold, muſt doe him ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice; which dogges and ſwine cannot doe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though ſuch be ſometimes in the houſe, yet they are but ſtrangers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and none of the houſhold: which is true in all that prophane rabble of ſwearers, drunkards, filthy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, and other notorious offenders; and in all hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, of whom the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh thus, <hi>they went out from vs, but they were not of vs,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.19. and generally in all contemners and deſpiſers of God, who, though they liue in his houſe, haue no inch of priuiledge, neither any allowance therein.</p>
               <p>Gods houſhold is the houſhold of faith, and of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men; or it is the Church of Gods Saints, and not a ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of beaſts, or cage of vncleane birds. In a word, Gods houſe it is the houſe of good people, and of goodneſſe, and will ye ſteale, murther, and commit adultery, and ſweare falſely, and burne your incenſe to ſtrange Gods, and come and ſtand before the Lord, in the houſe whereupon his name is called, though ye commit all theſe abominations? <hi>Ier.</hi> 7.9, 10. If ye be of the houſhold of God, ye muſt not conſpire againſt him in his owne houſe, as a houſhold of rebels, and increaſe of ſinfull men; and ye muſt be ruled by him, and doe reuerence to him, that hath the key of the houſe of <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some liue in his houſe, that both diſhonour him and his houſe; and many arme themſelues with the name of the Church, when yet (ſaue for name) the Church hath no greater enemies then they are: therefore, leaſt in ſtead of the Arke of the Church, we fall into a ſhip of Pirats, and in ſtead of the Lords houſe, vpon a den of theeues; we muſt (as followeth) ſee, that our Chriſtian outward calling haue a good and ſure foundation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:150376:13"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>VERS. 20.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Built vpon the foundation of the Apostles and Prophets, and Ieſus Chriſt (himſelfe) the chiefe corner-ſtone.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THat is grounded, by the doctrine of the Prophets and Apoſtles, vpon Chriſt. The <hi>Rhemists,</hi> in their annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vpon the new Teſtament, would wreſt this, which is here ſpoken of the foundation in Chriſt, to the perſons of the Prophets and Apoſtles, his ſeruants. But beſides that it makes flatly againſt the ſupremacy of <hi>Peter,</hi> to haue that giuen to all, that they would appropriate to him; it ſeemes to haue no ſhadow of that, that they would haue it in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to be: for, whether by the foundation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, be meant (as ſome vnderſtand it) that the vocation of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> had the ſame ground, which the Prophets and Apoſtles had; or (which ſeemeth to be neerer to the Apoſtles minde) that the doctrine of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Prophets, was the foundation of their calling in Chriſt, in neither can it any way fauour their abſurd opinion: or, if there had bin any reſpect of perſons, in this recitall of names; the Apoſtle might as well haue mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Patriarks, to whom the promiſe was made, and the worthy Kings, by whom it was continued, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets by whom it was (but) ſpoken. And (here) firſt he nameth them that were laſt, <hi>to wit,</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; not that they preached any other doctrine then was agreeable to that of the prophets, which were before them; but becauſe they witneſſed that to be done, which (before) was but promiſed to be done; and were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſent to manifeſt that clearely (as it were in the open ſunne) to the world, which by the Prophets) ſo long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, was but ſhadowed: for, albeit the fathers in the old Teſtament, had (at all times) the Prophets (as it were the leſſer ſtarres of heauen) to giue them light; yet was it, in a manner, night with them all, till the ſunne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (Chriſt Ieſu) did ariſe vnto them. Whoſe light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150376:14"/>it was in great meaſure beſtowed vpon the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as alſo becauſe (after his aſcenſion) the holy Ghoſt in viſible maner, came downe vpon them, therefore was the doctrine, which they taught, a neceſſary meane, by which to lay the foundation of the Church vpon Chriſt. This, though the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth labour to auoide, by prouing that there was a Church, before the word was written with inke or engrauen in ſtone, and ſo making it to be more probable that the Church ſhould giue authoritie to the Word, then take any from it: yet becauſe we know that, howſoeuer there was light in the world before the Sunne was placed in his tabernacle in heauen, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.3.16. yet when the Sunne, the chiefe of the two great lights was made, there was no light that was not deriued from it: we are perſwaded that though the heauen of the Church had her light of knowledge, within, before the light of letters came; yet as ſoone as the word was written, which was written when that Law, imprinted at the firſt in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and <hi>Eues</hi> heart, began to weare; all the light the Church had was to be borrowed from the Word; firſt of the old Teſtament, and after of the old and new. And this we may learne of the Apoſtles themſelues, whoſe Church was, (it ſelfe) grounded vpon the doctrine of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, which is here added, as another part of the Churches foundation in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But becauſe the doctrine was not theirs, but his that ſent them, and who when the fulneſſe of time was come, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. came himſelfe, and brought his euerlaſting Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell with him; therefore Chriſt (as followeth) is mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſpoken of by an excellency; as Ieſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; and <hi>Chriſt the chiefe corner ſtone:</hi> for, though the Gentiles, in their vocation to the Citie and houſhold of God, were built vpon the foundation, that is, doctrine of the Apoſtles and Prophets; yet were they not built vpon them, but vpon Chriſt, who, as he is the ground of all faith, ſo is he the matter and end of all Scripture: and therefore vpon him, the Gentiles and all Churches were, and are (properly) laid by their doctrine.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150376:14"/>
               <p> And whoſoeuer buildeth (I doe not ſay) vpon any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but him, but vpon any other with him, hath the leſſe hold of this foundation, and the leſſe aſſurance of his owne building. This ſtone, this chiefe ſtone, laid in Sion, was and is contemptible in the eyes of the world, and therefore refuſed by worldly builders, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.22. yet was it made the head of the corner, and (here) the chiefe corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone: not by compariſon with others; as our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries would haue it, that they may make them to be of the foundation that are ſcarce of the building, and heads that are no ſound members of the Church; but becauſe, to him, that is (onely) high, all things are aſcribed in the higheſt degree.</p>
               <p>And he is called the corner-ſtone, becauſe both ſorts of people, Iewes and Gentiles are reconciled, and (equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) founded in him: for, he is the Sonne, whom we muſt kiſſe when God is angry, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.12. It is his face, in whom we muſt, and onely can behold the glory of God: to him was giuen a name aboue all names, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9. neither is there any other name vnder heauen, by which we muſt be ſaued, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. <hi>Tertullian</hi> cals him the ſeale to both Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments; and Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> the knot, in the which all the Articles of our Faith are bound vp, or which holds them altogether: and (therefore) are the righteous ſaid to bee as Mount Sion, which cannot bee remooued, but remaine for euer, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 125.1. Becauſe they are grounded vpon that ſtone, in Sion, in which, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer truſteth, ſhall not be aſhamed, <hi>Eſai</hi> 28.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6. which ſtone, is not onely ſo elect and precious, that wee cannot haue a better, but ſo neceſſary and ſo ſingular that we may haue no other. For other foundation no man may lay, then that which is already laid, Ieſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Corin.</hi> 3.11. in him is the ſumme of our ſaluation, and all the parts. Hee is the authour and finiſher of our faith, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.2. the beginning and the end, the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> thereof, and of whatſoeuer is betweene. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.8. And (to be ſhort) hee alone is all in all vnto vs, wiſedome, and righteouſneſſe, and ſanctification, and redemption: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150376:15"/>1.30. and in him doe the Gentiles truſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.12. But were the Gentiles, and are wee, that ſometimes were as theſe Gentiles, laid by one continual and conſtant doctrine of the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles, vpon Chriſt? Then is there but one rule, both to them and vs, of faith vnto ſaluation, by the doctrine of the Scriptures. For did not (all) eate of the ſame ſpirituall meate? And did not (all) drinke of the ſame ſpirituall drinke? and were not (all) baptized vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the cloud, and in the Sea? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2.3, 4. That is, was not one Law (as it were <hi>Moſes</hi>) and one Goſpel, as it were ſpirituall meate, and ſpirituall drinke in Chriſt, to Iew and Gentile? To theſe Gentiles, and to vs that were Gentiles, and are Chriſtians? So, the Goſpel is ſaid to bee the power of God vnto ſaluation to euery beleeuer, to the Iew firſt, and alſo to the Grecian. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. Not one to them, and another to vs, but one to both.</p>
               <p>The people before Chriſt, and wee now in Chriſt, were of one houſhold, and vnder one gouernour: now the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of one Kingdome, and (much more) priuate perſons of one houſe haue but one law. For the great God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, is not like that great King of the Macedons, of whom it is written, that as many nations as hee had vnder him, ſo many kindes of ſeruice hee receiued of them: but ſo ielous rather he is of his glory, and true ſeruice, that as he admits no God but himſelfe, ſo he vouchſafeth no ſeruice but his owne; and acknowledges no ſeruice of his owne, but what is done by his owne Word, and tendred in his owne Sonne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abrahams</hi> creede, and ours are one; and the booke which <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> had in their heart, as it was, hidden in the Wall. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 22.8. Wee (their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie) who walke in the ſteppes of their faith, haue in our hands; ſaue that they had but an epitome of Chriſt, and wee the volume at large. God ſpake by his Prophets in the old Teſtament, by his ſonne in the New. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1; 2. Is not the tongue of God alway the ſame, and one to all? Or did hee ſpeake contrarily to our fathers and to vs? In diuers manners I grant, for he liſped (as it were) by <hi>Moſes</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150376:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>to them, in ſundry tipes, figures, and ſhadowes of things to come: <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.10. But to vs hee hath ſpoken plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Chriſt in the Goſpel. So that wee haue the ſame Word that they had, but more legible, and in a fairer let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and they haue the ſame Law that we haue, but more vailed with ceremonies, and darker to them then it is to vs. The Church and people of Rome, who ſay with thoſe Iewes, which purſued Chriſt to death, wee haue a Law: <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.7. Haue another rule, not drawne vpon the ground, nor according to the rule of faith, neither yet built vpon the foundation that is (here) ſpoken of, but of Popes and Councels.</p>
               <p>The great things of Gods Law they count as a ſtrange, thing or thing they much reſpect not: <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.12. only, their owne dreames pleaſe them. But there is enough (leaſt written) for the guiding of euery true beleeuer to Chriſt, and to life in him: <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.31. and they that will not heare <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, how ſhall other things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwad them? <hi>Luke</hi> 16.31. Here alſo we haue no building, but vpon the Apoſtles and Prophets, Miniſters; and Chriſt the Maſter, vpon their Doctrine, and his perſon: and what warrant (then) for additions to theſe by ſuch as they were, of whom God complaineth by <hi>Ezechiel;</hi> that they ſet their threſhold by his threſholds, and their poſts by his poſts. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 43.8. I ſpeake of our aduerſaries, who adding to that which is written, ſo many vnwritten fabulous vanities, to which they giue the countenance of Scripture, doe ſet the threſhold of tradition, by the thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold of the Word written, making the Lords ſiluer droſſe, and mingling his Wine, with worſe then water. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 1.22.</p>
               <p>But wee that haue a moſt ſure Word of the Prophets, let vs take heede vnto it, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. and be wiſe in that; not aboue that with Heretickes, nor againſt that with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, that is able, and therefore ſufficient enough of it ſelfe, to make vs wiſe to ſaluation. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. Let vs not with the Papiſts, whom we heare condemned, make it onely a partiall rule of our liues, but (impartially) ſet our
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150376:16"/>wayes to it, with reſpect to all Gods Commandements. Neither let vs preſume to giue our ſelues a diſpenſation for any thing forbidden by it, though neuer ſo ſmall; which is but to erect a court of faculties in our owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes againſt it. For ſome will commit a ſinne, and then ſtretch the Word, to make it a little ſinne, if it bee great: and if it be little, to make it nothing. But good Chriſtians muſt be builded, as well in their conuerſation as faith, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Apoſtles, Prophets, and Chriſt, that is, vpon the whole Word of God, that they may bee abſolute, being made perfect vnto all good workes: 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17. that is, made perfect indeed, and furniſhed thorowly to the power of godlineſſe.</p>
               <p>And therefore, they are iuſtly reprooued, who ſeeke to any thing in their corporall and ſpirituall diſtreſſe, rather then to the Scriptures. In the worſhip of God, ſome more eſteeme their owne opinion and the tradition of their El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, then the rules of the Word. If they bee ſicke, they will goe (firſt) to carnall meanes, and (laſtly) to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. In their apparell, they are rather led by the faſhion, in their recreation by the company, in eating and drinking by their appetite, then the Scriptures. And (generally) in their liues, it is eſteemed a courſe too ſtrict, and of too much niceneſſe to ſtand to the direction of the Scriptures. Gods intent in writing and giuing his Word, was the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our hearts in the truth, and the grounding of our affections by the nature thereof: if therefore wee care not to build our faith vpon it by the Miniſterie, nor to direct our courſe by it in our ordinary way, that it may bee ſaid, though in a better ſenſe, this was done that the Scripture might be fulfilled: <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.36. we fruſtrate Gods purpoſe of inditing holy Scripture, and make our ſelues guiltie of a prodigious ſinne, or a ſinne, as bad as the ſinne of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.23.</p>
               <p>Beſides, in our obedience this way, our owne good is ſought; but wee ouer throw it, and our ſelues by odious diſobedience. Therefore the Lord by <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſpeaketh thus; Statutes and ordinances haue I giuen them, which (if
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150376:16"/>a man doe he ſhall liue in them, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 20.11. Loe, the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them is our life, or our gaine; as the not doing of them muſt needes be, and iuſtly, our deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, not to build vpon the Word, is to build vpon ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance; and ſo to build Popery in vs: which in ſtead of building in Conſcience, is to build in Hell: for, there is no conſcience, that is, good conſcience, without it; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good conſcience what are we, but vnconſcionable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? So much for our building vpon the foundation: but, what manner building muſt this be? for the manner, it muſt be a coupling together: and for the end, it muſt be a holy Temple in the Lord: as it followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>VERS. 21.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>In whom all the building coupled together, groweth vnto an holy Temple in the Lord.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE common knot that coupleth vs to God, and one to another, is the ſpirit: and in the ſpirit, this buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding muſt be coupled, as with the foundation by Faith, ſo in it ſelfe by loue: for it commonly falleth out, that that which is diuided in it ſelfe, is eaſily from it ſelfe diuided alſo. And therefore as we haue one God and Father of all, which is aboue all, and through all, and in vs all: <hi>one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme, Epheſ.</hi> 4.5. ſo muſt we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide to be knit together in one minde, and in one iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. and to be (as the primitiue beleeuers were) <hi>of one heart, and of one ſoule, Acts</hi> 4.32. <hi>endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to keepe</hi> (as much as we may) <hi>the vnitie of the Spirit in the bond of peace, Epheſ.</hi> 4.3.</p>
               <p>They dwell neere together that inhabit in one Citie; but Chriſtians (who are holy Citizens, are Citizens with the Saints) ſhould dwell neerer in heart then men doe in their houſes. The communion of Saints is as an vndiuided Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; and Cities in vnitie are goodly Cities: ſo is it a <hi>goodly thing for brethren to dwell together in vnitie, Pſal.</hi> 133.1.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150376:17"/>Againe, Chriſts Coat had no ſeame; and ſhall his body be diuided? was Ieruſalem compact in it ſelfe? and ſhall Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalems Citizens iarre? muſt her buildings touch toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.3. and ſhall not Chriſtian brethren touch neerer, who are linked in faith, and ioyned in Chriſt? muſt our houſes be vniforme? and ſhall wee, that liue in ſuch houſes, liue in no agreement? One ſaith well, the Church leaueth to be, when ſhe leaueth to be one. And, therefore, they doe not a little deceiue themſelues, who thinke they can grow in the root, and be torne from the branches: or, hold the foundation, and be rent in the roofe; for, the branches muſt be vnited that will grow in the root; and the roofe muſt be ſound and well coupled, that will, any while, keepe the foundation.</p>
               <p>This would be conſidered of all, both houſe and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; but ſpecially the builders, or labourers in this buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſhould conſider that it much concerneth them to be at peace among themſelues, and with the Church: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould they ſtudy, not onely, to be quiet among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but to ſowe among thoſe that heare them, the ſeeds of peace.</p>
               <p>And to this they may take ſome light from the very Prince of darkeneſſe; who knowing that his Kingdome can no longer continue then he makes it hold together, doth therefore, he and his, conſpire to diuide vs, but can neuer be perſwaded to diuide themſelues: all their labour is to make a rend in our Church, and to ſtop euery little chinke in their owne; alſo, to keepe their owne foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to ſhake ours. How much more ſhould the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Gods Church, both build themſelues, and it, with louing exhortations to peace; <hi>that peace may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their wals, and proſperitie</hi> (the conſequent of godly peace) <hi>within their palaces? Pſal.</hi> 122.7.</p>
               <p>And for the ſpirituall houſe, which is builded by them, how ſhould it hold agreement with the truth, and with it ſelfe; not carried into faction and parts, according to theſe diuided tongues, <hi>I am of Paul, and I of Apollos and Cephas, and I am Chriſts,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. ſeeing euen the children of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150376:17"/>hell and houſhold of <hi>Belial,</hi> doe agree ſo well (ill I might ſay) both againſt vs, and with errour and lying vanities, againſt God, and his righteouſneſſe?</p>
               <p>And yet, that we may not take the dry bones of peace for that peace which is coupled with holineſſe: the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row being gone; it is to be conſidered, that euery peace is not to be followed: for, <hi>what peace, where Iezabel and her fornications are?</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.22. what peace with the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabel</hi> of <hi>Italie?</hi> and what peace with the <hi>Romiſh</hi> witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts? better open warre then ſuch peace: but I ſpake of peace among our ſelues: wherein (yet) we muſt take heede of hauing peace with the vnfruitfull workes of darkneſſe; and, ſo, generall perſwaſions to peace muſt be linked, which made the Apoſtle to ſay, <hi>if it be poſsible, and, as much as in you is, haue peace with all men:</hi> now, what we may doe poſſibly, that we may doe lawfully; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we may ſeeke peace and not finde it, at a churles hands: if, then, mans incorrigibleneſſe breake the peace, and ſome mans frowardneſſe will haue no peace, we are in no fault, if we liue not familiarly with ſuch: but we muſt be in charity with them, and pitie them in their euils, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their amendment, and ready, vpon it, to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled; elſe we (our ſelues) are not children of peace. And in this ſenſe, we muſt <hi>haue peace with all men:</hi> and yet not ſit vpon one, or the ſame ſtoole with the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: for, if we ſee a thiefe, we may not runne with him; we muſt, here, diuide our ſelues from him in his ſinne, but not in our charitie: and vile perſons we muſt hate, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.4. that is, as ſinners, not as men. To be ſhort (therefore) if we will haue peace with men, I meane ſuch peace and in ſuch manner, as may make it lawfull and good; we muſt, firſt, ſee it be not againſt God, and ſo haue no peace, to wit, of familiarity, with Papiſts, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.21. <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. chap. whole. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it be not againſt the Common-wealth: for, what peace with Traitors? thirdly, that it be not againſt our brethren, whom we muſt not hurt, but <hi>loue as our ſelues.</hi> Fourthly, that it be not againſt our ſelues, our ſoules, or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150376:18"/>bodies by euill
<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 5.9. Epheſ. 5.11.</note> fellowſhip: for, to touch the pitch of the wicked, is to be defiled with the
<note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 5.6.</note> company: and peace with the wicked, is called by <hi>Hilarie,</hi> a ſlauery, but no true peace.</p>
               <p>All theſe kindes of peace are carnall and impious, or peace more cruell then any warre, which I leaue to thoſe who <hi>cry with one voyce, let him be crucified, Mat.</hi> 27.22. the peace required here, is the peace of charitie, the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly peace of Chriſtians, and this we owe to all, euen to good and bad; to the good, for that they haue; and to the bad, for that they may haue: ſo much the rather, becauſe that the <hi>vnitie</hi> required in this building, is not that wee ſhould be coupled onely, that is, knit, or glewed, or arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially made faſt one to another; but, as followeth:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grow,</hi> as it were into one, or ſo together, that we may be as vnwilling to be diuided from our brethren, as wee would to haue our owne limbs torne from vs: and for this cauſe, and in this ſenſe, are the parts of this building called by Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> not dead ſtones that muſt be faſtned with morter, but liuely, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. which receiues from the corner ſtone, as from their root, ſap and life ſufficient, though not in one meaſure, yet as is fitteſt for euery ones calling, and beſt for the whole building. And therefore it is not enough to be in the foundation, and vnited to the building, vnleſſe wee daily <hi>grow</hi> (as it further followeth) <hi>vnto an holy Temple in the Lord:</hi> which is alſo meant by the ſtone in <hi>Daniel,</hi> which being cut out of the Mountaine without hands, grew, and became great, and filled the earth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35. for, by ſuch increaſe, we come to be the Temple, or habitation of God: by it God dwels in vs, not as he is in his eternall godhead, euery where; but as he is ſpecially in the faithfull by his Spirit; and yet wee are not many, but one Temple: and the ſame ſpirit which is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in euery one, is but wholly one in all: ſo wee haue the meaning of: the reſt of the Text.</p>
               <p>And now ſeeing we are called from ſo baſe an eſtate; as we would riſe from baſeneſſe in the worldly birth, to more and more greatneſſe, and would alſo depart further and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150376:18"/>further from an obſcure parentage to a better ſtocke and family: ſo in the heauenly new-birth, our deſire (whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be greater) ſhould be no leſſe to grow and increaſe more and more in ſpirituall and true greatneſſe; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and further to bee remoued from the parentage of ſinne, to the noble ſtocke of Chriſt, which is the diuine ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the Sonne of God. This growing muſt bee in the Lord, or in the ſundry ſtatures of his feare, from glory to
<note n="b" place="margin">Apoc. 22.11.</note> glory. For the eſtate of a Chriſtian in regeneration, is not a retrograde or ſtanding ſtill, but a going forward therein, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.16. And as children grow by the milke that they receiue: ſo, and vpon this condition we receiue the milke of the word, but it is, that we may grow thereby. 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 2.2. Or if wee haue taſted how bountifull the Lord is; this taſting of him, how can it but ſet vs on a longing, till we be filled with him? <hi>verſe</hi> 3. That is, filled with the knowledge of him, when the Word dwelleth richly in vs, and not in a beggarly manner? <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.16. And filled with the obedience and loue of the truth, when wee walke no longer in the fleſh, but in the ſpirit or good way of life: and lanch foorth, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.22. or ſaile forward, (as a Ship gone out of the Hauen) from the ſhore of the new birth, to the Hauen of our peace in death. Many are at a ſtand in knowledge, and rather goe back-ward then forward in the way of grace. Such grow but vntowardly, and prooue dwarfes, and not men of any ſtature in Chriſt. But in <hi>viâ virtutis, non progredi eſt regredi;</hi> in the way of true vertue, not to goe on, is to goe backe: and, as it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a member of a growing body, that groweth not, as the body doeth: ſo neither can it bee any liuely member of a true Church, that proſpereth not, as that Church doth with the increaſes of God. All <hi>non proficients</hi> (therefore) in the degrees and ſchoole of regeneration, are bad Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and not members growing into Chriſt, but members <hi>pro forma,</hi> that is, for faſhion onely; and ſo, are as farre from the end, as they fall ſhort of the meanes of being as it followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An holy Temple in the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> For, how can that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150376:19"/>bee a fit Temple, or habitation for God by his Spirit to dwell in, which groweth not into a building? What man can conueniently, and will contentedly dwell in a houſe that is but begun to be built, and before it haue any, either roofe or couer? And will the high God dwell in any houſe in his Ieruſalem below, whoſe neither wall is builded, nor roofe couered? but to proceede: the words that follow haue two points in them of ſpeciall conſideration: as the qualitie of this Temple, it muſt be holy: and the reaſon thereof; it is the <hi>habitation of God by his Spirit.</hi> It is called a Temple, by alluſion to the Temple that was at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> which was a type of the ſpirituall Ieruſalem and Church of Chriſt: and this is either of all the ſtones toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is the Church; framed with the corner-ſtone, which is Chriſt: or of the ſtones conſidered ſeparately by themſelues, euery one of which makes a ſingular temple, as all together makes an vniuerſall in Chriſt. So many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, therefore, ſo many liuely ſtones toward the building of the generall Temple: and yet euery true Chriſtian is a Temple to God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.19. And this Temple, both the whole, and euery ſtone in it, muſt be holy, that is, endewed with holineſſe, and purged from the luſt of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, which was the luſt of thoſe which knew not God, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.4, 5. which worke of reformation, though it ſhall be hindred by many, as the ſecond Temple at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem had many aduerſaries, <hi>Neh.</hi> 4.1, 2, 7, 8, <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.19, 20. yet ſhall it proceede to the perfection of the body of Chriſt, as that other building went forward, and was finiſhed, notwithſtanding all that either malice or craft could doe againſt it.</p>
               <p>Onely, let vs not hinder it our ſelues, by liuing in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, and by neglecting to purge our ſelues, that wee may be a peculiar people to God, zealous of good workes. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. And, what we beleeue let vs practiſe; wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue a holy Catholique Church, let vs therefore practiſe holineſſe, that our practiſe be not againſt our faith. Let vs labour to be holy, as hee is holy that hath called vs. 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.15, 16. And ſeeing hee hath waſhed vs, who hath giuen
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150376:19"/>himſelfe for vs, let vs not plunge our ſelues againe in the mire, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25, 26. to wit, in the mire of our firſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>VERS. 22.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>In whom you all are builded together for an habitation of God through the Spirit.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>FOr, who will prepare for a great man (his friend) in a foule houſe, or lodge him in a ſtable? And is any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon greater, or friend better to vs then God? Or, is any houſe, or roome of the houſe, fowler then an vnpurged conſcience? And what ſtable is more loathſome, then the loathſome ſtable, or rather ſtie of a wicked heart? But, how doeth God dwell in vs? <hi>Reſp.</hi> Miniſterially by his Word and Sacraments, and (principally) by his Spirit. For his Word (therefore) ſeeing hee dwelleth in vs by it; wee muſt reſolue to giue to it, as to himſelfe, our beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement: lodging it in the beſt roome of the houſe, the heart, and not in the out-houſe of the eare. And for the Sacraments; chiefely that of the Supper, the chamber muſt be trimmed, wherein Chriſt will eate that Sacrament with his Diſciples. <hi>Marke</hi> 14.15, 16. And, for that which is chiefe, and expreſſed in my Text, the Spirit, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is the Spirit of God, and very God; wee muſt take heed how wee ſinne againſt it, that is, the good motions of it in our hearts, wilfully, and diſpitefully: for that is a ſickeneſſe to death, for which there is no Phiſicke by repentance.</p>
               <p>This is a ſinne of men enlightned with the trueth. The Gentiles, without God, cannot commit it, neither the Iewes, that are without Chriſt. A ſinne, wherein a man falles away, generally, and malitiouſly from God, yea, for euer and vtterly from him, in all the effects of a reprobate heart, and heart that cannot repent. This is that great ſinne, which Satan hath ſo blacked, that it can neuer bee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150376:20"/>made white: a ſinne that ſhall not bee forgiuen to a man, either in this World, or in the World to come; that is, neuer. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.32.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But is not the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, a ſinne againſt the Father, and Sonne as well as him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This ſinne, if we conſider the perſon of the holy Ghoſt, it is no more againſt it, then it is againſt the perſons of the Father and the Sonne: but becauſe the holy Ghoſt immediately, both conuinceth conſcience, and enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it; therefore when we ſinne againſt knowledge, and the light of our hearts, we are ſaid properly, and directly to ſinne, not againſt the Father, or Sonne, but holy Ghoſt. But a Chriſtian may ſinne againſt the Spirit, though in a farre leſſer degree of ſinne againſt him, then by this, which is ſo bitterly offenſiue againſt all his graces in our hearts.</p>
               <p>To know how; wee muſt firſt know how, and in what reſpect, the holy Ghoſt may be ſaid to dwell in a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, or God by him. And this is not in regard of ſubſtance (for the whole ſubſtance of the holy Ghoſt, which cannot bee diuided, cannot bee ſhut vp within the body or ſoule of man) but in reſpect of ſome particular worke or ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Now a Chriſtian may ſinne againſt this worke of the Spirit in him; either when grace is offered, and not accepted of; or accepted of, and not well vſed. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, grace was offered to the old World by <hi>Noah,</hi> and hee warned them (for a hundred and twenty yeeres) by preparing the Arke: but they had neither eares to heare it, nor hands to receiue it, and ſo the Arke, that is, the time of repentance, offered by it, condemned them. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7. <hi>Sodom</hi> was exhorted to repentance by iuſt <hi>Lot,</hi> and a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant land: yet ſhee reiected the Spirit that ſpake by theſe vnto her. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. The gheſts that were bidden to the ſupper, were bidden by the Spirit to it; but they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to come. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.18, 19, 20. <hi>Steuen</hi> ſpake by the Spirit to the Iewes, but they ſtopped their eares, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.57. neither vouchſafing to heare him, nor the Spirit, by which he ſpake.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:150376:20"/>
               <p> Many times, the Miniſters of the Goſpel knocke at our hearts by their exhortations, and warnings to repentance, yea, many biddings wee haue, by ſickeneſſe, and other wayes, and wee doe as much. But this is to refuſe grace, when the Spirit offereth it, which cannot but grieue the Spirit, by the which wee are ſealed to the day of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.30.</p>
               <p>And this is one kinde of ſinne againſt the Spirit: an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other is, when wee make the Spirit weary of vs, hauing receiued it, or grieue it by our wicked behauiour, not vſing our Gheſt well. Which made the Apoſtle in the foorth Chapter of this Epiſtle, and the thirtieth verſe (as wee heard) to exhort theſe <hi>Epheſians,</hi> not to grieue, or make ſad the Spirit in them. Where hee compareth the holy Ghoſt to a gheſt, and our bodies and ſoules to Innes.</p>
               <p>Now, as men will vſe their gheſts well, that they may come againe: ſo would the Apoſtle haue all Chriſtians, in theſe Chriſtian <hi>Epheſians,</hi> ſo to entertaine a good motion, as a good gheſt, when it is offered, that it may come againe, and bring more company with it, to enrich this, ſhall I ſay Inne? Nay Temple of the Spirit, the heart, with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of ſpirituall wealth, and bleſſings in heauenly things in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But the children of God (themſelues) doe not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes keepe one tenure in receiuing the Spirit, when by it, grace is offered to them, for the auoiding of ſome euill, or the doing ſome good. For ſometimes, they are leſſe apt to pray, leſſe ſit to heare, and leſſe prepared to the Sacrament, then at ſome other times they bee. Yea, they may haue leſſe feare of ſinne, care of well doing, zeale in prayer, and comfort in the Word at one time then another.</p>
               <p>This indeede, is a tempting of the Spirit, which though it make him not deſirous to be gone, yet ſomewhat cooles his loue toward vs, as in <hi>Dauid</hi> and others. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we muſt ſtriue with prayer, againſt all manner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay in theſe ſpirituall riches, and omit no oportunitie to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150376:21"/>doe well, as hee that meanes to bee rich in his trade, will omit no meanes of gaining by it. And (here) let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what a ſhame it is for the children of God, though they cannot looſe the Spirit, to looſe, for ſome ſeaſon, any graces (which they once had) of the ſanctifying Spirit. For was it not a ſhame for <hi>Lot,</hi> who was ſo chaſt in <hi>Sodom,</hi> to commit ſuch inceſt, out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> in a Caue in the Mountaine? <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.33.35. And did it not greatly blot <hi>Dauids</hi> Chronicle, that in the dayes of peace (which hee did not in the time of warre) hee ſhould fill his eyes with adultery, and ſtaine his hands with blood? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2, 3, 4, 5.15.</p>
               <p>How weake was <hi>Sampſon</hi> that was ſo ſtrong, and how ridiculous, that was ſo feared, when the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from him? <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.20.25. So <hi>Peter,</hi> looſing by the deniall of his Maſter, much of that courage hee had, when hee cut of <hi>Malchus</hi> right eare; <hi>Iohn</hi> 18.10. how was he poſed, and ouercome of two ſilly maydes? <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.69.71. And ſurely, if it bee a matter of diſcredit, being rich, to become poore in worldly ſubſtance, what greater ſhame is it, being rich in grace, to decay in the Heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treaſure?</p>
               <p>This ſhould make vs to purge our ſelues (daily) from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. not to be careleſſe, as if in proſperitie we could not be moued, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.6, 7. for, a man may take a dangerous ſurfet after a full feaſt of grace: and to be humbled, when wee haue done our beſt; confeſſing that <hi>we are vnprofitable, Luk.</hi> 17.10. the beſt haue their infirmities: and in euery Chriſtian wombe, as in <hi>Rebeccahs,</hi> there is an <hi>Eſau</hi> of fleſh, and <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> of ſpirit <hi>strugling together, Gen.</hi> 25.22. we are ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but in part, and corruption goeth not out but with our laſt enemy.</p>
               <p>In a word, in all the regenerate, there is a mixture of ſleeping and waking, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2. of ſinne and grace: it concernes vs (therefore) that put on our harneſſe, not to boaſt, as he that putteth it off, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.11. and ſo to take heede that we giue the ſpirit no occaſion, by fainting,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150376:21"/>or becomming ſecure in that warre, which is betweene the fleſh and ſpirit in euery Chriſtian ſoule, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. It is ſure that the elect can neuer quite looſe the ſpirit, that is, the ſauing graces of the ſpirit that dwelleth in them: and yet it is as ſure that the ſame may, by ſinning againſt it (ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry wayes) looſe the feeling, the comfort, the ioy and peace of it, for a ſeaſon; which made <hi>Dauid</hi> to pray vnto God, that he would not <hi>take his ſpirit,</hi> that is, the ioy of his ſpirit <hi>from him,</hi> as appeareth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.11, 12. They that take him to ſpeake otherwaies, ſay, that he ſpake but as a diſtempered ſick-man, who ſpeakes, he knowes not well what himſelfe; and what maruell that a guiltie priſoner at the bar (the water ſtanding in his eyes) ſhould miſſe in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his owne pardon.</p>
               <p>But I take it, that <hi>Dauid</hi> was come to himſelfe, when hee penned that exemplary Pſalme of his ſinne for the Churches inſtruction; and that therefore hee knew what he ſaid, not diſtruſting any totall loſſe of the ſpirit of adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but onely deſiring that his feeling might come againe vnto him, and that he might haue (as he once had) both a free and ioyfull ſpirit in worſhipping toward God. Yet, let his example be a warning to vs who haue receiued a farre leſſer portion of ſanctifying grace then <hi>Dauid</hi> had: for, where ſuch a Cedar fell, <hi>let him that ſtandeth, take heede leaſt he fall,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12. if ſo excellent a man, ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exalted, as vpon his ſtrong hill, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.7. was ſo quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon the loe ground in his adultery and murder, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by his penitentiall Pſalme, wee had neede to take heede that we <hi>grieue not the ſpirit,</hi> who ſtand vpon ſo loe a banke already.</p>
               <p>How this may bee, and how this our moſt worthy Gheſt may bee grieued, after wee haue receiued him into houſe, and ſo our light eclipſed, though not quenched as in the darkneſſe it ſelfe; wee may ſee it, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what darkely, in certaine earthly ſimilitudes: for, as if, when ſome noble Gheſt ſhould offer to come vnto vs, we ſhould receiue him but in ſome out or backe houſe, not in our beſt lodgings, wee ſhould conſtraine him with indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150376:22"/>to leaue vs.</p>
               <p>So, for this Lordly Gheſt (the Spirit) who commeth to vs in his Word gloriouſly, as in his Charet: if we turne both it and him contemptuouſly into ſome forſaken cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as it were backe-romes of the heart, what hope is there hee ſhould tarry with vs, and his Word, any while, abide among vs? How much leſſe, if we receiue his Word into our hearts, as into ſome priſon-houſe, holding the trueth in vnrighteouſneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. or, behead it as <hi>Iohn</hi> was in priſon? <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.10.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if we ſhall not receiue a great man (our friend) chearefully, or with good well-come, wee ſhall giue him good cauſe, with contempt, to paſſe by vs, another time: ſo, if we ſhall not receiue gladly and willingly the Spirit of comfort, how can wee but driue away the Comforter? If wee doe not flow vnto him, as the Sea, after ſuch an ebbe and low-water of knowledge and true goodneſſe; how can wee retaine that God, who will not tarry, any while, but where he findes a cheerefull giuer?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, though a man receiue his great friend into his beſt roomes, yet if he doe not dreſſe vp thoſe roomes, and make them ſweete, remouing all noiſome ſauours, he ſhall greatly offend that perſon, his friendly ſtranger: ſo, though wee ſhould receiue the Spirit into our hearts in ſome graces, yet if wee prepare not for his comming, nor make ready our hearts for his abode among vs, remouing our filthy and vnſauory ſinnes that offend ſo much; how can wee but giue iuſt occaſion to that ſame Spirit to forſake vs? For what greater deſpit can bee offered to the Spirit of Grace, and of Glory, then to ſee ſinne (his moſt deadly enemie) in his owne habitation? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.32.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, though a man receiue ſome great man (his friend) into a houſe ſwept and garniſhed, that is, well prepared for him, yet if afterwards, hee bring his enemie (the greateſt hee hath) to out-face him, and to vexe him in the ſame place, how can hee but bee mooued againſt, and offended with ſuch an hoſt? So, though we entertaine the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150376:22"/>Spirit, for a time, in ſome good motions, and in a heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in many things, as <hi>Herods</hi> was, yet if after ſome time, wee returne (being thus waſhed) to our wallowing againe in the mire, and begin to licke vp the vomit that wee caſt; how can wee thinke to reteine the Spirit, and this forme of ſinning together? For, as if one ſhould ſet vp a rebell in that Kings owne dominions: ſo are they who bringing ſinne into the heart, Gods owne Throne, or (further) into any of their outward ſenſes, his owne dominions, doe vexe him (as it were) at home in his owne poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, though one receiue a noble man, into a faire and well furniſhed houſe, and poſſeſſe him quietly of it, yet if hee prouide not conueniently for his perſon, and traine, how can hee pleaſe him? So, who can pleaſe the Spirit, though hee make neuer ſo godly a ſhew of being zealous in the Law, if he abridge him of the diet and ordinary that belongeth to his good keeping in him? If hee care not to nouriſh his good motions at Sermons, and in the point of hearing, ſcantle him by attending vpon the Word, but at certeine times onely, and ſo become (as Maſter <hi>Latimer</hi> merily ſaid) but a Straw-berry-hearer? And, may not the Spirit ſay to ſuch, as Chriſt to thoſe on his left-hand, at the laſt day; <hi>I was hungry, and yee fed me not; thirstie, and ye gaue me no drinke? Mat.</hi> 25.42.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, though this great man ſhould bee receiued in all conditions and manner, anſwerable to his great place and companies, yet if after a day or two, (as being weary of our Gheſt before he bee willing to leaue vs) wee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw things neceſſary from him, wee cannot but much offend him: ſo howſoeuer wee begin in the Spirit, yet if (waxing weary of well doing with thoſe fooliſh <hi>Galati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> that ranne well)
<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 3.3.</note> we end in the ſame, in the fleſh, wee muſt needes grieue the holy Ghoſt, and ſhall heare, the laſt ſtate of theſe men is worſe then their firſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.26. then ſhall wee bee ſeuen fold more the children of the Deuill.</p>
               <p>And thus wee haue heard how many wayes, the Spirit
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150376:23"/>(after it is receiued) may bee made ſad by vs, and cauſed with griefe to leaue vs. Let vs bewar how wee ſo offend, leſt we turne the habitation of God, into an habitation, or hold of vncleane ſpirits.</p>
               <p>And (now) to conclude with that which is full of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular comfort; ſeeing wee are the habitation of God by his Spirit we may learne that God is not in vs, as a ſtranger in another mans houſe, but as at home, in his owne; and therefore will not looſe vs, as no man will looſe his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance that is able to keepe it: and, who ſo able, as hee that is Almighty? Neither (being the habitation of God) can wee lacke any thing that is good; that is, that is good for vs. For, what want can there bee in the Kings houſe? And as all good things are brought to the court: ſo, what ſo euer is excellently good, is to bee had here. Here is loue, ioy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſſe, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, faith, meekneſſe, temperance, againſt which there is no Law. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23.</p>
               <p>Here is no Winter, nor fall of the Leafe, but a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Spring-time: and hee that would haue what hee can wiſh (if hee will wiſh lawfully and well) let him come hither. Let him build in grace, and ſet his houſe vpon Wiſedomes pillars, <hi>Prouerbs</hi> 9.1. and no enemie ſhall hurt him. For it is the <hi>Bethel</hi> of God, or houſe vpon the Rocke: <hi>Matthew</hi> 7.24. And hee that is in it will keepe it, when they that come againſt it, ſhall fall downe before it: for, who dares interrupt Gods poſſeſſion? Or, if hee dare, ſhall not periſh?</p>
               <p>Thus the ſecuritie is great, and the walkes are ſtrong, where God is the inhabitant: and, hee that is a wall of defence about his people, will bee a wall of fire againſt his peoples enemies. <hi>Zecharie</hi> 2.5. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 4.5. Hee that builds <hi>Sion,</hi> will throw downe <hi>Babel:</hi> and hee that ſaues <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> will ouerturne <hi>Paleſtina.</hi> The reaſon is, his Tabernacle is in <hi>Salem,</hi> and his dwelling at <hi>Sion. Pſal.</hi> 76.2. But <hi>Babel</hi> and <hi>Paleſtina</hi> were Countries, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee neuer vouchſafed either to dwell, or bee, as in his Church.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:150376:23"/>
               <p> So I conclude; make God your inhabitant, and yee are ſure, but if hee dwell not in you by his Spirit, yee ſhall neuer dwell in ſafetie.</p>
               <p>And now, hee that dwelleth in vs, and in his elect by promiſe, keepe vs and his whole <hi>Iſrael:</hi> yea, bleſſe vs, and ſaue his Iſrael, the Church which hee hath purchaſed with his owne blood; that, being the habitation of God by his Spirit, it may bee a temple of holineſſe dedicated to his glory, in the grace of Chriſt, and loue of God the Father, to both which, with the holy Spirit of both, be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and giuen all praiſe and glory, now and euer: <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:150376:24"/>
            <head>THE CHRISTIANS GVIDE TO A wiſe Conuerſation.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>EPHES. 5. VER. 15, 16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Take heed that yee walke circumſpectly; not as fooles, but as wiſe:</p>
                     <p>Redeeming the time: for the dayes are euill.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake heed that yee walke circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly, &amp;c.</hi> It is written of
<note n="a" place="margin">Cardinall Pole</note> Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Pole,</hi> that being demaunded which was the beſt way to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Epiſtle of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans;</hi> anſwered, to begin with the ſtudy of the former part, and practiſe of the latter; becauſe the firſt is a demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtration of the grounds, the ſecond an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to the fruits of Faith. That which he ſpake true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of that one Epiſtle, may be obſerued in all the reſt, and generally in all his writing: for, he planteth by doctrine, and watereth by exhortation in euery Epiſtle, laying the foundation by teaching, and building vpon it by exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a holy life; that the true Chriſtian rooted in faith, and ſtrengthned through hope, may by the ſanctification
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150376:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the ſpirit, grow to a perfect man in Chriſt. Herein the proportion he vſeth is not alwayes alike, nor the ſame, as ſtanding (ſometimes) more vpon doctrine then exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely in that large Epiſtle of his to the <hi>Romans:</hi> ſometimes more vpon exhortation then doctrine, as in this to the <hi>Epheſians;</hi> yet doth he apply both, and vſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as one becommeth more needefull then another to profit with. And ſurely, if euer there were a time wherein there was more taught then followed, more knowne then practiſed, and therefore more neede of exhortation then doctrine, it is ours, and it is now: for euen now, and at this time, we are (a great number of vs) better Schollers then men; and vnder the full ſailes of our ſcience, what doe we but make ſhip-wracke of all good conſcience? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue not thought it amiſſe to intreat of that part of the Apoſtles exhortation, wherein hee generally aduiſeth the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and in them vs, that ſeeing they were called from being ſtrangers and forreiners, to be Citizens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God; and ſeeing they were made of enemies, ſonnes, and tranſlated out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe into ſo great light, they would (therefore) as Citizens and ſonnes, or as ſonnes and children of light, take heede, not onely (though carefully) to the doctrine which they had receiued, but circumſpectly to their wayes, walking not onely directly therein in regard of themſelues, but wiſely in reſpect of others, and not as fooles in the vanitie of their opinions, but as wiſe, vnderſtanding what the will of the Lord is: not neglecting the grace then offered, but redeeming the ſeaſon, or buying it backe againe, like good chapmen of time.</p>
               <p>Now, in theſe words, the Apoſtle requireth (firſt) dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, <hi>take heede:</hi> then the ordering of our wayes by dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, <hi>how yee walke;</hi> after, all auoiding of offence in walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>that yee walke circumſpectly,</hi> and circumſpectly with diſcretion; <hi>not as fooles, but as wiſe:</hi> and laſtly, that wee take all occaſion to doe good, not looſing but redeeming the opportunitie: the reaſon is, <hi>the dayes are euill,</hi> or we liue in a bad age, and with men of bad conditions; ſo euill
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150376:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>and nought, that they haue euen tainted time it ſelfe, and the very dayes in which wee liue. To take heede, and not to our walking, is no diligence; to walke, and not circumſpectly, no diſcreet diligence; to be circumſpect, and not wiſe, is great follie; to be diſcreet and wiſe in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, and not for time, is vanitie, and no godly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion: but ſo to take heede that we walke; ſo to walke that we be circumſpect that we be wiſe; ſo to be wiſe that we redeeme the time, or bin out for well doing, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious commoditie that others deſpiſe (who therefore are no good husbands of time but ſpendthrifts of it) is the way (indeede) to make the dayes that are euill to others, good to vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take heede)</hi> is as much as watch ouer your Chriſtian ſtate, that you receiue not the grace of God in vaine: of this duetie, as there are many cauſes to moue vs to it, ſo there are many occaſions to withdraw vs: for whether we looke into the world that was made to ſerue vs, or into our ſelues who were made to ſerue the Lord; whether we caſt our eyes vpon things without vs, or call to minde the things that are within vs; what are they (take them at their beſt) but cauſes to moue vs to <hi>walke worthy of our vocation?</hi> but take them in their corruption, and what are they but occaſions of euill? what, but ſnares in the world, and the chaines of the Prince of darkeneſſe to hold vs in wickedneſſe?</p>
               <p>And both theſe, as they are of no ſmall force, the one to bring vs to our duties, if well conſidered, the other to lead vs away from them, to all vanitie of minde &amp; error of life, if not well watched and taken heede vnto, ſo doe they exact at our hands no ſmall labour and diligence, duely and well to obſerue both one and other; for albeit godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be of it ſelfe, ſo great riches, that it neede nothing but it ſelfe to commend it to vs: and ſinne be of it ſelfe, ſo great (not gaine but) loſſe and loathſomeneſſe, that it hath enough in it ſelfe to make it vile vnto vs: yet that there may be nothing wanting to ſtirre vp our diligence, by all meanes in this matter, many things are ſpoken of the one
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150376:25"/>to make vs to ſeeke it with more care, and as much is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the indignitie of the other, to make vs auoid it with more contempt: for the firſt conſideration, if wee would enter into the ſoule of it, acknowledging the great care that God hath of vs, how can it but moue vs to double di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and heede in the matter? ſpecially, being thereby waged, and with ſome hire, to ſeeke that which is ſo worth the ſeeking? for to ſpeake nothing of our creation, which was of nothing, nor how he made all things ſubiect to vs, that we (for whom he made all things) might be ſubiect to him alone: when we were worſe then nothing he redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs, and when we had leſſe then nothing, hee endued vs with the graces of his ſpirit, that being dead to ſinne, <hi>we might liue vnto righteouſneſſe, and being deliuered from the hands of our enemies, we might ſerue him without feare, all the dayes of our life, in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, Luk.</hi> 1.74, 75.</p>
               <p>Now that hee deliuered vs from ſo great a bondage as we were ſubiect vnto, not onely generally by the fall of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> but more particular by being caſt out of the common wealth of Iſrael, was ſuch a benefit as deſerueth whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeruice we are any way able to performe vnto him: but that he ſhould redeeme vs with ſo great a price, as the death of his firſt and onely ſonne, and call vs alſo to ſo high an eſtate, to be Citizens with the Saints, and <hi>heires with him of an inheritance immortall, vndefiled, that fadeth not, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in heauen for vs:</hi> this is a bleſſing that is many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees greater then the ſeruice of our whole life can attaine vnto: but beyond all this, that hee ſhould endue vs with thoſe gifts, and bleſſed graces that make vs to walke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of this vocation, and able, as it would ſeeme, to pay him with his owne lent loue, by making vs ſo rich in him; what heart created can conceiue what this is? and if it cannot be conceiued by vs, how doth it concerne vs to take heede (ſeeing theſe benefits of God are ſo much more then we can deſerue or conceiue) not to receiue ſo great grace in vaine; nor to thinke, where we can deſerue nothing, we can ſerue more or better then wee ought; or to play the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150376:26"/>vnthrifts with ſo rich a treaſure committed to our keeping and vſe? He that hath committed to vs our life, and his money, to be recalled at his pleaſure, and hath diuided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs his bleſſings, and his talents to occupie till hee come, will one day, moſt certainely, require againe his coine of life that he lent vs, and reckon with vs particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the ſeuerall peeces of his ſtocke of grace; both, which we haue ill imployed, and which we haue not imployed to their beſt end, which is his glory: then, neither the hiding of our talent in the ground by an vnprofitable life, ſhall be able to deliuer vs from our account to damnation: nor the ſmalneſſe of his gift, and of our receit, as it were the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle talent, excuſe vs, if we haue bin vnfruitfull in the leaſt matters: nor others ill vſing of greater graces be a cloake for vs; but the ſecrets of all hearts, as it were the bookes of the Lords accounts, ſhall be laid open, euery leafe of them, and hidden thing in them: and a iuſt, I doe not ſay equalitie, but proportion of increaſe ſhall be exacted at our hands according to the meaſure of grace which wee haue receiued: for as it is in the fift of the ſecond to the <hi>Corinthians ver.</hi> 10. <hi>We muſt all appeare before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of God, that euery man may receiue the things which are done in his body, according to that hee hath done, whither it be good or euill:</hi> and therefore they doe not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle deceiue themſelues, who hauing a greater meaſure of grace dealt vnto them, and more of the Lords money in their hands then others, doe abuſe all that bountiſulneſſe of the Lord, and <hi>turne his grace into wantonneſſe;</hi> and yet thinke they ſhall as eaſily paſſe their accounts, as they who haue receiued ſmaller ſummes both of time and ſpirituall riches to anſwer for; as if to receiue much, were rather a priuiledge to greater ſecuritie, then the charge of a greater burthen.</p>
               <p>But it fareth not with the heires of heauen as it doth with the Lords of the earth, who becauſe they are borne to greater rents and poſſeſſions then others are, thinke they may liue more idlely then others, and (as they vſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) more wickedly: but the more that euery one receiues
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150376:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>here, the more will be required of him; and the better his calling is, the more ſeemely muſt his walking be in it: for wee are all of vs <hi>vnprofitable ſeruants;</hi> euen the beſt of vs, when we haue done our beſt, are ſo: and if wee were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny degrees better then we are, we were many more degrees worſe then we ſhould be. And, in this reſpect, we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>ſtewards of God,</hi> not owners of his gifts; and therefore not to abuſe them to our pleaſures, but to anſwer for not vſing them in his ſernice.</p>
               <p>But as we are to take heede to our Chriſtian life that it be godly and righteous, in reſpect of the cauſes that ſhould moue vs ſo to doe ſo in regard of the many occaſions that ſtand in our light and way to withdraw vs from a good courſe, we ſhould take this paines for the ordering of our Chriſtian life, much more: for, how many are they, and how many wayes offered? I would we were as willing to preuent them, as wee are ſure they doe daily, nay euery houre, and moment of our life, circumuent vs: for, who can open his eyes, and not ſee? his eares, and not heare occaſions of euill in all places? who can thinke, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe? walke, and not walke in death? or, (which is leſſe) but ſteppe out of doores, and not ſteppe into a great pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of ſinne? Not onely by the corruption of our vile na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by which we are carried to all euill, but alſo by the ſubtile inticement of our old enemie, who hath ſpred his nets of deceit ouer all the world, and baited his hookes with euery part of our fleſh, and hath ſo many lures of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture for our eyes, charmes for our eares, vaine thoughts for our hearts, and by-wayes for our feet, we are ſo engirt and beſet daily on euery hand and ſide of vs, that wee are eaſily caught, and no ſooner aſſailed, then taken: neither is he ſure that thinkes hee commeth into this field of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults beſt appointed for them: the world, what is it but a Sea, which ſwelleth with pride, fometh with luſt, boileth with deſires, and hath many contrarie tydes and tempeſts to turne vs from the port to which wee ſaile? Our life, what is it but a life of battels, and a perpetuall warfare, in the which we are to ſtrine againſt the world and the Prince
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150376:27"/>thereof, yea againſt our owne fleſh, and the luſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and not to haue one minute of truce with them; but in a calme to looke for a tempeſt, and to be moſt diſtruſtfull, when the enemy ſeemeth moſt quiet and ſtill? for, beſides thoſe many weapons which Sathan hath to aſſault vs, the many occaſions that he hath to withdraw vs; his skill in vſing his weapons, his policie in applying and taking his occaſions; he is well acquainted with the humours, not of euery age onely, but of euery eſtate alſo: and therefore can fit euery one with and in that to which hee is moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined. He tempteth young men with beautie, middle age with glory, and old age with money: he ſtirreth vp con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in ſuperiours, enuie in inferiours, and malice in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals: If any be ſtrong in faith, hee will teach him to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume; and if any be weake, he will driue him to deſpaire. He cloatheth his foule practiſes with tolerable names; making luſt but a tricke of youth, ambition a ſpur to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, deſire of money honeſt prouiſion, and whatſoeuer is of it ſelfe euill, and for it ſelfe hatefull, a thing meerely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different: yea, where he cannot hinder the courſe of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, he will ſo aduance it in the followers, that hee will make them proud of that they doe. And to be ſhort, when he perceiueth that hee cannot worke ſo groſely in the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light, as to perſwade them that darkneſſe is light, and light darkneſſe; hee fetches about vnder hand to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them, that though they may not doe as the wicked doe, yet it is no harme to keepe them company; and though they be aſhamed of many things in the light, yet in the darke they neede not, ſeeing no man ſees them.</p>
               <p>Further, to this his skill and policie, hee addes no leſſe diligence: and for this, hee is ſaid to be a Dragon that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſleepeth, and Lyon that neuer lyes ſtill, <hi>ſeeking whom he may deuoure;</hi> hee ſowes tares in the night, and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth their growing in the day; he gaines the time that we looſe, and where we are careleſſe, he workes; what wee ſcatter he gathers, and what opportunities wee giue, hee takes. And what hee doth in perſon by himſelfe, the ſame
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150376:27"/>he doeth by his Miniſters, making them more watchfull to build vp the Synagogue of Antichriſt, then they are to build Gods houſe; and more zealous for a temple of idoles, then they are zealous for the Temple of God. <hi>None doeth faint or fall among them; none ſlumber nor ſleepe; neither is the girdle of their loines looſed; nor the latchet of their ſhooes broken, Eſa.</hi> 5.27.</p>
               <p>Wherefore it is, that though our caſe be neuer ſo good, and our enemies caſe deſperate, yet hee will bee in hope to ouercome vs, if by no other meanes, yet with his impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities. And to this, as to all other his attempts againſt vs, he is much incouraged and ſet on by our owne corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which giues him no ſmall hope, while wee cary that about vs, which is as ready to open the gate, as hee to enter.</p>
               <p>For, as <hi>Bernard</hi> noteth very well: <hi>Quot quot degimus in regione vmbrae mortis, &amp;c.</hi> As many of vs as liue in this ſhadow of death, in this infirmitie of body, as it were ſeat of temptations, we haue our inconueniences; we are eaſie to bee ſeduced, faint to doe good, weake to reſiſt euill. Whereby it commeth to paſſe, that when we would iudge betweene good and euill, wee are deceiued, when wee would doe good, wee cannot, and when wee would reſiſt euill, we yeeld vnto it.</p>
               <p>This the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> calleth the Law in our members, rebelling againſt the Law of our minde, and leading vs captiue to the Law of ſinne. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23. A Law of ſuch force and ſpite againſt vs, while wee dwell in this earthly houſe, that wee need no other enemie to maintaine battell with vs, and to keepe vs this way doing. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſeeing we haue ſo many cauſes to ſeeke a thing which for it ſelfe, is ſo worthy; ſeeing alſo our auncient enemie beſets vs with ſo many occaſions, and ſo much skill and diligence, going ſo farre beyond vs in his aduantages, to our ſpoile and vtter deſtruction: how ſhould theſe things moue vs to be well appointed, at all aſſaies, to take heede to our Chriſtian ſtate, and particularly (as followeth) to our walking.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:150376:28"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>That yee walke, &amp;c.</hi> Albeit, wee are to take no ſmall heed to our Chriſtian ſtate, that it ſtand vpon matter of ſound doctrine, ſo that not onely we beleeue nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Word, but beleeue whatſoeuer is conteined in it: yet are we ſo to looke to it, that we faſhion our walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, and ſo to beleeue, that we liue there-after. And therefore, where we are willed to take heed of falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that come in Sheepes cloathing, and to trie the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, becauſe ſome that ſeeme of God, may prooue Sathani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call: we are taught to know falſe Prophets by their fruits, and lying Spirits by their Doctrine: and the Apoſtle who exhorteth <hi>Timothie</hi> to looke to his Doctrine, exhorteth the ſame <hi>Timothie</hi> alſo to looke to himſelfe. For true it is, that as our eyes deſire light to the end they may ſee, and yet withall deſire it, that by ſeeing they may receiue and giue direction to the body: ſo the eye of the ſoule, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, deſires the Doctrine, as it were light of the will of God, that it may know; and yet ſo ſhould deſire to know, that good affections may follow, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſo gotten, may direct our life. Alſo, as it is ſaid of Chriſt that hee knew no euill, when it is meant hee did none: ſo may hee truely be ſaid, to know the will of God that doeth it.</p>
               <p>For in vaine doe we keepe his Commandements in our heads, if wee keepe them not in our liues. And here, the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> that hee might ſtirre vs vp to the deeper ſtudy, and meditation of the Law, pronounceth them happy, not that are learned, but that are vndefiled in the way, not that know the Law, but that walke in it. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, hee calles the Law a Lanterne, not vnto our eyes, but vnto our ſeete: and a light, not to our mindes, but to our pathes. Which hee doeth, that wee might vnderſtand that fruitleſſe knowledge, and an idle profeſſion of the Law without fulfilling it, is a damnable, both knowledge and profeſſion.</p>
               <p>And if any ſhall thinke that obedience to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, was ſo required vnder the Law, as that it was abrogated with it, (which is the opinion of many
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:150376:28"/>
                  <hi>Atheiſts</hi> at this day, that by it they may cloake their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of life, and of ſome Profeſſours, that yeeld too much to their luſts:) let them know that Chriſt came not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Law, but to fulfill it; <hi>Math.</hi> 5.17. and that hee was ſo farre from taking any edge of rigour from it, that he whetteth it to a ſeuerer expoſition, adding more quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to it, then the Phariſes would confeſſe to bee in it in reſtraining the naturall Man. For, where the Law forbad to commit murder, he expounded the Law rightly, to forbid anger: and where it forbad to commit adultery, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded it, to forbid all looking vpon a woman to luſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her: <hi>Math.</hi> 5.27, 28. Where it forbad forſwearing, he expounded it, to forbid ſwearing at all, to wit, vainely, and in common talke: <hi>Math.</hi> 5.33.34. and where it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to loue our neighbour, hee expounded as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement to loue our enemies. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.43, 44.</p>
               <p>So hee laid more weight vpon the Law, rather then tooke off any; for, hee himſelfe was to fulfill it. How much the more iniury doe our aduerſaries (the Papiſts) to vs, and to our Doctrine, while they goe about to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the ruder multitude, that our Doctrine of faith, takes away good workes, and brings in a greater liberty, or rather licenſe of life, then is to bee found among the Turks, and Infidels. For where we ſay that faith alone doth iuſtifie; we doe not require that faith ſhould be alone, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it iuſtifies alone, but confeſſe with the Apoſtle, that faith without workes is dead. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.17. And ſo grant him any thing rather then faith, that can ſpeake as though hee hated vice, and yet liue, as though he hated vertue, It is the ſaying of our Sauiour Chriſt; <hi>not euery one, that ſaith vnto me Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdome of Heauen, but he that doeth the will of my Father which is in Heauen. Math.</hi> 7.21.</p>
               <p>For, the fig-tree in the Goſpel made a faire floriſh by leaues; but, hauing nothing but leaues of ſeeming, withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; <hi>Math.</hi> 21.19. after Chriſt had ſaid, <hi>neuer fruit grow on thee any more.</hi> The fooliſh Virgines had Lampes of a glorious profeſſion, as well as the Wiſe; but lacking the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150376:29"/>Oile of faith and a good conſcience therein; were ſhut out. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.1.3.10.11. The Phariſe had the Law of God in his mouth, and in the skirts of his garments, no man oftner, or more; and yet when hee went into the Temple to pray, the ſilly Publican, was preferred before him: for, he went to his houſe more iuſtified, rather then he. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.14. By all which wee learne, that it is not enough to come neere to God with our lips, except our hearts come neere him, and our hands touch him. <hi>Math.</hi> 15.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.20. To be hearers of the Law, and not doers, is to deceiue our ſelues: <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.22. For, ſo wee ſhall make our eares to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe vs, and our owne mouthes to ſpeake againſt vs. And they, who (like Monſters) haue longer tongues then hands, that is, can ſay more then they will doe, are not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly compared to leaues without fruit, lampes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out oile, clouds without water, hauing a ſhew of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, but denying the power thereof. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. To theſe (as <hi>Gregory</hi> noteth in his moralles) it commeth to paſſe in the iuſt iudgement of God, that by the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their liues they looſe the opinion of their faith. For, though we are to confeſſe with the mouth, as wee doe beleeue with the heart; <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. Yet (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith in his booke <hi>de Duplici Martyrio) effica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius eſt vitae quàm linguae teſtimonium:</hi> more ſpeaking is the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of our life, then the witneſſe of our tongue. And, in the ſame booke further; <hi>habent &amp; opera ſuam linguam, habent ſuam facundiam (etiam) tacente linguâ.</hi> Our workes can ſpeake, and that eloquently for vs, though we hold our peace. In the end hee concludes, that as our good workes profeſſe God, ſo our euill doe ſay for vs, that wee thinke there is no God. It cannot be denied, but that the Word of God is like vnto fire; and therefore as able to worke in vs, not onely the knowledge of Gods will, but obedience to the ſame, as fire giues vnto water, not onely heate but motion, making it not onely hote, but to boile ouer. Yet as fire it ſelfe, though neuer ſo hote, doeth not burne the hand that lightly toucheth it, paſſing quickely through the flame: ſo neither doeth the Word worke
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150376:29"/>where it is little regarded, or paſſeth preſently through vs. And here their negligence commeth to bee reprooued, who, though they acknowledge the Doctrine of Chriſt, and can be content (in their manner) to giue their names to the trueth, doe not much trouble themſelues in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it foorth by their deedes, how ſo euer (other wayes) they will be wary enough to doe nothing directly againſt it. But, though they thinke it good to ſleepe in a whole and warme skinne, and to paſſe through this life, as a Ship through the Sea, that leaueth no ſigne of her being there: yet they ſhall finde, how ſo euer they can reaſonably cleare themſelues of doing no euill; that they ſhall anſwere for not doing of good, and further, for not doing as much good as they might.</p>
               <p>And therefore, let them that liue in no particular voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion flater themſelues as much as they liſt, becauſe in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing, they doe no euill (though indeede, it be euill to doe nothing, and idleneſſe bee (as <hi>Bernard</hi> proueth) as well the mother of vice, as the ſtep-mother of vertue) they ſhall heare, one day, that ſentence of condemnation read againſt them; <hi>I was hungry, and ye gaue me no meate; I thirſted, and yee gaue me no drinke; I was naked, and yee cloathed me not. Math.</hi> 25.42.43.</p>
               <p>It is not ſaid, that when Chriſt, in his poore members, was hungry, yee tooke away his bread, but it is ſaid, yee did not feede him: nor that yee tooke away his drinke, when hee was thirſty, but that yee gaue him no drinke: neither that yee vncloathed him, but that yee cloathed him not when hee was naked. So Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> but as wee muſt walke, ſo wee muſt ſo walke, that wee bee circumſpect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Walke circumſpectly, &amp;c.</hi> Becauſe there is but one way right, and the ſame narrow, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.14. where there are many by-wayes, and broad withall, it is neceſſary, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that in our walking, we bee circumſpect, looking about vs, and to our feete, where we ſet them: and that as well in reſpect of our ſelues, that we doe not erre, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of others, that we doe not offend. For our ſelues we
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150376:30"/>ſhall not doe amiſſe, if, as the Sailor hath alway the North pole, and the Archer his marke in his eye; ſo we euer haue in the eye of our minde, the end at which we ſhould aime in our whole courſe; euen that which is the North pole of our Chriſtian Nauigation, and white or leuell of our beſt and holieſt endeuours here. And therefore if wee did well conſider to what end we were created, and ſince the image of God was defaced in vs, to what end wee were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed; it would moue vs to take that courſe that could beſt bring vs to that end, and to thinke all that labour loſt, that is beſtowed to the contrary, or impertinently thereunto.</p>
               <p>The rather (alſo) ſhould wee ſo doe, becauſe it is not in our power or choiſe to propoſe to our ſelues, in our Chriſtian walke, what end and manner wee liſt; but haue the ſame pitched and ſet vnto vs by the will of God, whoſe will in his Word, is our ſanctification, and that euery one of vs ſhould know how to poſſeſſe his veſſell in holineſſe and honour. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.3, 4. Now this holineſſe of life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the chiefe end, or white at which the regenerate ſhould aime and bend vnto, in their Chriſtian conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doeth ſet a price vpon it, and all other things elſe, which (though lawfull and needfull in our mortall life) we ſhould much leſſe eſteeme then it, and it (being chiefe) much more then them all. For this cauſe it behoueth vs to bee very circumſpect, that (ſeeing temporall bleſſings are neceſſarily, and may lawfully, in a ſort, be deſired) we bee not caried away with the tide of our affections, to ſet our hearts vpon them, or to eſteeme them, either for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or for any other end, and with any other minde, then for the exerciſe of godlineſſe.</p>
               <p>For as the Moone is darkened and Eclipſed, when the Earth doeth come betweene her and the Sunne: ſo the mindes of the godly ſuffer, and are in a certaine Eclipſe of Pietie, when earthly cogitations, come betweene them and the Sunne of Righteouſneſſe, Chriſt Ieſus. Therefore well was it noted by <hi>Gregory</hi> in his Morals, that <hi>ſolus in illicitis non cadit qui ſe aliquando, &amp; a licitis cante re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringit;</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:150376:30"/>that is, that hee onely doeth not offend in things vnlawfull, that now and then reſtraines himſelfe from things lawfull.</p>
               <p>And now, if wee muſt bee ſo circumſpect in things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and lawfull, as not to deſire them, either more or other wayes then we ſhould; how much more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, ought we to be in thoſe things, that (of themſelues) are vnlawfull and wicked? There is no fellowſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene light and darkeneſſe, betweene the workes of the Spirit, and the deedes of the fleſh. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. If we will liue in the Spirit, wee muſt walke in the Spirit: <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.25. And if we bee Chriſts, wee muſt crucifie the fleſh with the affections and the luſts. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24.</p>
               <p>One ſaith well; if wee would bee of the minde before we ſinne, of the which wee commonly are, when we haue ſinned, and did marke our pleaſures (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> doeth aduiſe) not as they come, but as they goe away; wee would not commit ſuch groſe ſinnes, and ſo with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as wee doe; nor drinke iniquitie as the moſt doe, who drinke it, as the beaſt doeth water. Neither are wee to be wary or circumſpect onely in the greater euils, but in ſmaller offences (alſo) wee muſt ſtop their courſe when they are a beginning, and roote them vp when they are young. For little ſparkes may proue great fires, and ſmall ſprings riſe to great ponds.</p>
               <p>The leaſt infirmities wee haue, doe bring (as Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> noteth) though not death, yet ſickeneſſe to the ſoule, and though they doe not quench, yet they make ſad the Spirit of God. And (therefore) as they that loue their bodily death, doe not onely preuent death, but the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes that make way to it: ſo they that care for the health of their ſoules, will bee as diligent to preuent the diſeaſe, as they would the death of it, when they ſee it comming. For, if it bee true in the life of the body, it is much more true in the life of the ſoule, that <hi>vita, non eſt viuere ſed va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere;</hi> that is, it is not life to liue, but to bee in health, and many liue by breathing, that are dead in ſinne. If (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) we did as conſtantly beleeue that, which wee cannot
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150376:31"/>denie to be moſt true, which is that our aduerſary win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noweth vs as wheat, and that we ſhall giue an account of euery, not onely wicked, but idle, not onely deede, but word, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36. we would (as Saint <hi>Ierom</hi> counſelleth vs) <hi>minima pro maximis cauere,</hi> be as circumſpect in ſmall things as in great, ſpecially ſince the leaſt ſinne committed is made greater then wee can anſwer by the greatneſſe of him againſt whom it is done.</p>
               <p>This ſhould make vs carefull to preuent, not ſinne one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but the occaſions thereof, that we be not ouer-taken ere we be aware, and take the diſeaſe before we ſuſpect it. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus vereri qui ſcit, ſcit tuto vadere;</hi> the minde that knoweth how to feare, knoweth how to walke ſafely, and without feare: and it is care to be prouided againſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that make vs ſecure. As (therefore) it is written of the <hi>Africans,</hi> becauſe their Countrey is troubled much with Snakes, that they tread lightly in euery place, and, if they chance to feele any cold thing, doe more then halfe ſuſpect it is a Snake; and as they that ride with a charge in the night, doe (becauſe of the darkeneſſe, and their feare furthered by it) take euery buſh for a thiefe: euen ſo wee, who by reaſon of a greater charge, goe in greater danger, and are threatned with the bitings of ſharper teeth then Snakes haue any, ſhould much more ſuſpect vpon euery occaſion; thinking euery place we tread on, to be a net to ſnare vs, and euery thing we doe, to be a bait to catch vs; in euery graſſe we ſhould feare a ſnake, and in euery buſh a thiefe of our ſaluation: as well againſt ſmall as great ſinnes we ſhould come well appointed with the <hi>armour of light,</hi> hauing about our loines <hi>the girdle of truth,</hi> in our hands the <hi>ſhield of faith, and ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God;</hi> for the couer of our feet, the <hi>preparation of the Goſpell,</hi> and the <hi>helmet of ſaluation</hi> on our head; <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe</hi> for our <hi>breaſt-plate,</hi> and for all parts, <hi>prayer,</hi> which is the button, or knot, that holds all the peeces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether that we looſe nothing. Theſe we haue in the armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Scripture, by the key of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> chapter 6. verſes 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. If wee
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150376:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>take theſe peeces from thence, arme with them vpon all occaſions, and vſe them as we ought, wee ſhall not runne into euill: and when the enemy aſſaileth vs, wee ſhall be ready both to giue him battaile, and to ſend him backe.</p>
               <p>And yet it will not be enough for our circumſpect walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that we ſhe all, not onely ſinne, but occaſions of ſinne our ſelues, except we ſo beare our ſelues in reſpect of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that we giue no occaſion of iuſt offence to them by word or deede. I ſay iuſt offence; becauſe, many times, an offence may be taken when it is not giuen. So the aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the truth are offended at our doctrine which is true, and at the fruits of it, which are good: like as the <hi>Iewes,</hi> when <hi>Stephen</hi> did truely charge them to be <hi>men of vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed hearts and eares,</hi> ſuch as euer reſiſted the holy Ghoſt as their fathers did, were (euen) cut to the heart, and gnaſhed at him with their teeth, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51, 54. But how can we helpe it? the offence is taken by them, not giuen by vs. Now if the malice of the wicked be ſuch that they will take offence at that which is well done; how cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect ſhould we be, and how circumſpectly ſhould we walke, that by our euill deedes we giue them no iuſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion?</p>
               <p>This occaſion, though it may be giuen diuers wayes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther when we teach ſome falſe or vncertaine doctrine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that which we haue receiued; or when in things indifferent we abuſe our Chriſtian libertie, eating with of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and wearing our apparell ſo as may iuſtly giue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: yet is it chiefely ment in this place, as ſpoken of that offence that is giuen by our euill life: for, we ought to haue an honeſt teſtimony euen of them that are without: and our light ſhould ſo ſhine vnto others in our godly conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, that they may ſee our good workes through it; and by it, or beholding it, glorifie our father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. we muſt not be an occaſion that the name of God be blaſphemed through vs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.24. the rather, becauſe they that are without, and alſo becauſe they that are weake within, haue their iudgement led by no other
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150376:32"/>rule, nor eſteeme of the doctrine further, or otherwiſe then they ſee it fruitfull in the followers: therefore doth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle exhort the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> ſince they were called in hope, to adorne the calling with their good liues; and, being <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in the ſpirit of their minde, to caſt off the old man, and to put on the new in holineſſe, Epheſ.</hi> 4.22, 23, 24. ſince they were lightned, hee bids them to lay aſide the workes of darkeneſſe, and in an honeſt conuerſation, to doe the deeds that will not flye the light. So he wrote to the <hi>Romans,</hi> who alſo had bin <hi>called,</hi> by God, <hi>out of darkeneſſe into his marueilous light;</hi> bidding them, ſince <hi>that night was paſt, to walke honeſtly, as in the day, Rom.</hi> 13.12, 13. that is, to doe the workes of the day of the Goſpell, not the vnfruitfull workes of the night of ignorance, and of ſinne. The ſame Apoſtle writing to the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> doeth in great zeale, and with many reaſons charge them to giue none offence, either to the Iewes, or to the Gentiles, or to the Church of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32. but to edifie one another with their good example, as well as doctrine, <hi>ver.</hi> 33. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.12. and in his former Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> fift chapter, and 22. verſe, for this cauſe hee exhorts them to abſtaine, not from euill onely, but from all appearance and ſhew of euill; for, the common ſort takes euery one to be as he ſeemes, and will take a ſmall occaſion to condemne him and his profeſſion that ſeemes not.</p>
               <p>I doe not ſpeake this, as if men ſhould liue to opinion and ſhew, and that euery thing were beſt that ſeemes beſt, or that the common ſort thinkes beſt: but I ſpeake it to the end we ſhould not vtterly neglect the vulgar report, or (which is the diſeaſe of an impudent face and heart) neuer regard what men ſay of vs: for, that which <hi>Tullie</hi> ſpake of friendſhip, is true of reports; <hi>graue eſt amicitia verè ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſari, ſed ſi falſò accuſeris, non est negligendum.</hi> In friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it is a grieuous thing iuſtly to be accuſed, and not to be neglected if we be accuſed falſely: for, albeit a cleare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be a brazen wall; yet, as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> noteth, <hi>duo ſunt neceſſaria conſcientia, &amp; bona fama; conſcientia prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter te ipſum, bona fama propter Proximum:</hi> that is, two
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150376:32"/>things are needefull in a (peaceable Chriſtian life) good conſcience, and a good name; good conſcience for our owne ſakes, good name for our neighbours ſake. And this later is ſaid by <hi>Salomon</hi> to be <hi>aboue great riches, Pro.</hi> 22.1. that is, more then any or all the commodities of this life. In another place, by the ſame wiſe King in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> it is preferred before <hi>the beſt ointments,</hi> and eſteemed with the moſt precious things, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> was carefull not to ſeeme delighted with <hi>Sauls</hi> death; and therefore to ſatisfie others as well as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himſelfe, he greatly mourned for it, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.17, 19. &amp;c. The like ſatisfaction he was carefull to giue about the death of <hi>Abner,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.31. hee would not haue the ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of that trecherous deede to come neere him, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moues it by making great lamentation for him, though he had beene his enemie: though it be not in our power to bridle the tongues and pennes of ill diſpoſed perſons, yet it much concernes vs to beare off their ſtroakes with our innocencie, and to be ſure that we giue them no iuſt occaſion.</p>
               <p>The true light that came into the world, entred with this condition, that men ſhould not onely ſit ſtill in darkeneſſe, but loue darkeneſſe; and not onely ſo much, but more then light, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19. ſo ordinary a thing it is for truth it ſelfe to heare ill, and where there is moſt neede, not to be receiued. Chriſt is tearmed but the Sonne of a Carpenter, though the Sonne, and great power of God: the Apoſtles men of excellent tongues and ſpeech, are ſaid to be <hi>full of new wine, Acts</hi> 2.13. <hi>Paul</hi> moſt ſober, is ſaid to be <hi>mad and beſide himſelfe, Acts</hi> 26.24. <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt, <hi>to haue a Diuell, Mat.</hi> 11.18. the Primatiue Chriſtians to beleeue in a <hi>Galilean</hi> and hangd God: theſe did well, and yet heard ill in the world that was not worthy of them: ſo true it is that the world ſpeakes no language ſo much and perfectly, as reproach and ſlander: and hence it is that of late, the execution of Iuſtice is called perſecution for the Goſpell; puniſhment of Traitors, martyring of Saints; the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Faith, the preaching of looſeneſſe, is not our diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150376:33"/>among our ſelues come to this, that on the one ſide all zeale is made hypocriſie, and all learning iudged vanitie on the other: on either ſide, what is ſo good, but it is made ill? and what ſo ill, that is not made worſe?</p>
               <p>Theſe things (as I haue ſaid) well conſidered, haue we not great cauſe to looke to our wayes, and our ſelues cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly? and ſeeing wee are to regard our brethren in our example, as well as to cleare our ſelues in our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, how warie ſhould wee be both of doing euill our ſelues, and of being any occaſion that euill be done by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? The Heathen Law-giuer appointed a double pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to a publique ill-doing Magiſtrate: the one for doing euill, the other, for giuing an euill example. And ſo Chriſtians, when they doe amiſſe, ſtand doubly charged before the Lord; once for the euill they doe, and againe for the hurt that commeth of it. So <hi>Dauid</hi> bore a double ſinne in his ſinnes of adultery and murther; one before God, that was put away, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.13. another by which <hi>he made the enemies of the Lord to blaſpheme:</hi> and this was viſited with certaine ſharpe chaſtiſements temporall: the <hi>childe that was borne muſt dye,</hi> and the ſword of trouble muſt be walking, <hi>verſe</hi> 14. and <hi>verſe</hi> 10. Therefore though this counſell of a heathen man be good, <hi>Ne te quaeſi veris extra,</hi> that is, let no man ſeeke himſelfe in other mens mouthes: yet that which another ſaith is neceſſary; <hi>viuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum recte cum propter plurima, tunc has (precipue) ob cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas, vt linguas mancipior, contemnas:</hi> we ought to liue wel, as for many other reaſons, ſo for this chiefely, that we may contemne the tongues of railing <hi>Martius.</hi> And it cannot but be neceſſary for euery one that doth tender his credit, though in the firſt place to take heede that hee deſerue no euill, yet in the ſecond to be no leſſe carefull that he be not euill ſpoken of without deſeruing.</p>
               <p>So we ſee that hee had neede to haue as many eyes as <hi>Argus,</hi> or rather to be full of eyes, as an Angell of God, that will be circumſpect enough in an age ſo full of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and in dayes ſo euill: to which let me adde this one reaſon more, and that is, the ſmall incouragements
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150376:33"/>that this froward world affords to thoſe that follow after things of beſt report; the diſgraces that it caſts vpon grace in the <hi>children of light;</hi> &amp; the no accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that it makes either of godlines or of godly perſons, able to make them to turne out of their good way, if they walk not circumſpectly. And here the admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Chriſt gaue, would be reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred, it is a good antidote againſt carnall weaknes: <hi>bleſſed is he that ſhall not be offended in me, Mat.</hi> 11.6. &amp; we ſhall haue need of it for our more comfortable <hi>paſſing through this vale of Baca.</hi> It is a hard condition that we are put vnto; hard (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) to <hi>fleſh and bloud to beare the croſſe</hi> with patience, when our good conuerſation in the world is not onely left without honour, but <hi>filled with reproach:</hi> for, will it not much trouble a man in his way (who yet walketh weakely) when he ſhall heare with his eares, that that which is moſt precious and aboue all worldly treaſure, ſhall beare no price, or be reckoned nothing in the ballance, that is, in the opinion of the greateſt, and greateſt part of worldly men? Beſides, what incouragement is there for good things and good men, when no rewards (here) are aſcribed to them? when no nobilitie is giuen to the new birth? no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the ſeruice of God? no beautie to the beautie of the daughter of <hi>Sion, whoſe glory is all within?</hi> no ioy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall to a good conſcience? no glory to the croſſe? no wiſedome to the knowledge of Chriſt? and no riches to true godlineſſe, which (yet) is of ſo great gaine, that the Merchant of this Pearle was content to ſell all, himſelfe and all, to buie it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.44. If a man <hi>walke not circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly,</hi> how can he out be offended at theſe things? how can he but either refuſe the narrow way of grace, or (being entred into it) goe backe with diſcouragement? It is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary therefore, and more then conuenient, that wee ſo <hi>walke,</hi> and further (as it followeth) that <hi>we walke;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Not as fooles, but as wiſe.)</hi> By wiſedome, the Apoſtle (here) meaneth Chriſtian wiſedome, and godly warineſſe: not ſuch wiſedome as hath no folly in it: for, who is ſo wiſe, but is in ſome things fooliſh, and at ſome times dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth fooliſhly? Hence this ſaying; <hi>ſtultor, plena ſunt omnia;</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:150376:34"/>that is, all things and places are full of fooles and folly; or the wiſeſt are fooles in ſome things: and no man ſo wiſe, that doth not ſometimes trip, and in ſome things halt downe right in his wiſedome. Neuertheleſſe good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians may and ought to carrie themſelues wiſely and with good diſcretion in all companies, and at all times. And in the Apoſtles dialect, he is counted wiſe, not that hath no folly in him in reſpect of heauenly knowledge and matters, but that hath the leaſt folly in him, in regard of them. But fooles are they that vnderſtand not, nor will know, <hi>what the will of the Lord is, Epheſ.</hi> 5.17. And of all fooles, there is no foole to him, and yet no folly ſo much followed as his, <hi>who ſaith in his heart there is no God, Pſal.</hi> 14.1. For ſuch an one, if he might be ſeene in his owne likeneſſe, and not masked and diſguiſed in ſo many profeſſions, (as it were) ſhapes, in the which he puts himſelfe, wee ſhould finde ſinne a peereleſſe foole; yea him a foole, that ſo var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with colours goes for wiſe. And this couert-folly doth chiefely reigne in the worldly Politique, who hauing learned of his Maſter <hi>Machiauel,</hi> that Religion was deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed but to fray fooles (though States-men, that muſt not be eſteemed fooles, muſt (neceſſarily) ſeeme religious) is yet very circumſpect to be reputed wiſe and religious, thereby to abuſe the ſimplicity of them that are religious indeede.</p>
               <p>Of this kinde I would there did not abound in our own State too many, who vnder the name of Religion, are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to cut the throat of Religion; and therefore condemne Churches and Colledges, as cages of vncleane Birds, that they may make them the neſts of Cormorants. Hence it is, that hauing ſhorne the wooll of our Eccleſiaſticall prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the moſt of our beſt reuenewes, in many places, are by Gods heauy hand vpon our ſinnes, made but thred-bare penſions; but the ſtubble that they haue conceiued will bring forth chaffe for the vnquenchable burning, and that which <hi>they ſeemed to haue, ſhall be taken from them, Luke</hi> 8.18.</p>
               <p>Others there are, who (alſo) would ſeeme wiſe, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150376:34"/>are fooles: and theſe are (rather) negatiuely, then poſitiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, religious: fooles, that can reaſon againſt all Religions, but for none: who (therefore) make Religion the Butt for their tongues to ſhoot at.</p>
               <p>And there are another ſort of fooles, who thinke they walke as warily as is required, if they can ſo walke that mans Law can take no aduantage of them, though they breake Gods Law daily; ſwearing horribly, ſpending time wickedly, and miſpending Gods Sabbaths. It may be ſaid of ſuch as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid of the like in his time: <hi>Quàm angusta eſt innocentia ad legem bonum eſſe?</hi> that is, how nearely goe they to worke with their honeſty, that will be no better then the Law compels them? ſpecially that Law that entreth not into the heart, but ſtaieth without, as it were, in the vtter court of words and deedes? In this caſe euery man ſhould be a Law to himſelfe, remembring that the prauitie (euen of thoughts) hath a Iudge, the Iudge of thoughts; and good men will doe that which is good, rather of conſcience becauſe they know it to be good, then of conſtraint becauſe it is commanded: For thus they free themſelues from that folly by which many thinke they walke circumſpectly, when they walke cloſely; and are wary, when (indeede) they be craftie: but this damned policie of the Papiſts, <hi>Si non caste, tamen caute:</hi> if you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not liue chaſtely, at leaſt liue charily; let vs leaue to the <hi>Mowles</hi> and to the <hi>Bats, Eſay</hi> 2.20. to Papiſts, and to Papiſticall perſons: for ſinne is ſinne, though it be ſhut vp; I doe not ſay in the ſecreteſt corner of our chambers, but in the very cloſet of our hearts: and thoſe cloakes that we ſeeke to couer it with, are but the figge-leaues of <hi>Adam,</hi> or rather nets, in the which fooles think they dance vnſene: but who can conceale fire, which will manifeſt it ſelfe by it owne light? ſo, who can hide ſinne, that will not be hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, though it be neuer ſo cloſely pent vp in our thoughts? yet the fowle of the heauen will carry the voyce, and that which hath wings will declare the matter, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.20. wee haue ſeene the happy experience of it in our dayes; where nothing was, or could be practiſed againſt <hi>Iacob</hi> by
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150376:35"/>any <hi>Eſau,</hi> but it was knowne to
<note n="b" place="margin">Q. Elizabeth.</note> 
                  <hi>Rebecca,</hi> our mother in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.42. and the <hi>Rauens of the Valley haue picked out the eyes of many of her haters, Pro.</hi> 30.17.</p>
               <p>But ſay, that the light of our ſecret ſinnes did not breake out before men: yet, what hope is there to hide them, when hee alwayes beholdeth them, who can enter when the doores are ſhut, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.26. and thoſe eyes I meane of conſcience, ſee them, that are more, in this caſe, then a thouſand witneſſes? It may be ſaid of theſe circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect fooles, <hi>vix quenquam inenies qui aperto oſtio poſſit viuere, ianitores conſcientia, non ſuperbia oppoſuit.</hi> Seneca <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 96. That is, yee ſhall ſcarce finde one of them that dares liue with his doore open, which proceedeth rather from the guiltineſſe of his conſcience, then for any pride to keepe a porter.</p>
               <p>To this folly, let mee adde another not much vnlike; and this is the folly of thoſe that are ſtrict in ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and in greater looſe girded: and theſe, if they were meaſured by the ſame thread that they meaſure others, would bee found little better then Phariſaicall fooles, that ſtraine at a Gnat, and ſwallow a Camell, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.24. they tithe Mint, and Cummin, but leaue the weightier matters of the Law. <hi>verſe</hi> 23. Daintie they are in a cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, but not daintie to commit ſin; and (as wee vſe to ſay) they ſtumble at a ſtraw, and leape ouer blockes. But of all fooles, they are fooles of record, who thinke they are circumſpect enough, if they can cloake their owne faultes by finding fault with others. And this folly runnes like a ſpreading Canker; it hath ouer-taken the moſt part of men, who ſeeke themſelues, rather euery where, then in themſelues; and who (like that woman, of whom <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> maketh mention) ſit blind at home with their eyes in a basket, but put them on when they goe abroad. But there are none, that looke leſſe into themſelues, then they that looke ſo much into others.</p>
               <p>For, whereas the honeſt minde, the better it is it ſelfe, the leſſe it ſuſpecteth others to be euill, and either looketh not at all vpon others, or looketh on them as on a glaſſe,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150376:35"/>in the which her owne infirmities are reflected vpon her ſelfe, and therefore is as farre from iudging ill of others, as ſhe is from thinking her ſelfe to bee good: the minde that is fouled with ſinne, and thereby enforced to loathe her owne filthy home, is glad to flie out, and to wander among others; and there, either by diſcouering their ſinnes to couer her owne, or by reprouing them, to gaine to her ſelfe an opinion, and ſeeming not to be as ſhe is.</p>
               <p>To conclude all theſe follies in one, and many other not ſpoken of, which to ſingle out by one and by one, were an endleſſe labour; they walke as fooles that walke after their owne ſancie, and not as they haue direction from God in his word; and therefore, in the next place, it is requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red that wiſedome bee the Guide to our circumſpect walking.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But as wiſe.)</hi> Here, leaſt any man might be deceiued in the word, or miſtake what true wiſedome is, in the 17. <hi>verſe,</hi> that followeth, it is ſaid to be that, <hi>which vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what the will of the Lord is:</hi> excluding all wiſedome of the fleſh, and iudging none wiſe, but who are made wiſe by the word to ſaluation. Where (yet) the Apoſtle doth not ſo oppoſe betweene that wiſedome which is of God, and that excellent facultie of vnderſtanding, which is a gift of the ſpirit of God common to good and bad, to the ſpirituall, and in the naturall man, as if none were able to conceiue the things of God but men vnlearned, and men not trained vp in humaine knowledges: for, howſoeuer morall wiſedome is meere fooliſhneſſe with God, when in the ſurges of her owne conceit, ſhe is lifted vp aboue that which is meete; yet when ſhee holdeth her owne proper courſe and channell, in ſobriety, ſhe proueth an inſtrument of much ſeruice to Gods glory, and Church: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (as one ſpeaketh of many) <hi>ſi vtiſcias ancilla eſt, ſi neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, Domina:</hi> that is, if thou canſt tell how to vſe her, ſhe is thy ſeruant, but if thou canſt not, ſhe will be thy miſtreſſe: ſo may it be ſaid of wiſedome acquired with induſtry; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſanctified thou maiſt command her; not directed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, ſhe will not ſerue but command thee. To be wiſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150376:36"/>then, is ſo to be by the word of God: more generally, to be wiſe, is to walke in a contrary way to fooles. How they walke we haue heard: and ſo wee haue heard how wee ought to walke: that is, as <hi>Antipodes</hi> to them, and (as was ſaid) in contrary wayes.</p>
               <p>It is ſole <hi>wiſedome to feare God,</hi> and one maine point of it is, <hi>to walke in his Commandements, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.10. <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Iob</hi> further, <hi>the feare of the Lord it wiſedome, and to depart from euill is vnderſtanding, Iob</hi> 28.28. It was once ſaid by one, that it was <hi>res ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſa eſſe Christianum:</hi> a matter of wit to be a Chriſtian: now it may be ſaid (all things well conſidered) that it is a point of great wiſdome to be a good Chriſtian: for though the rules of Chriſtian life be ſo conſtantly true, as that they all draw the varietie of our wayes, and the differences of our callings <hi>to that one thing which is neceſſarie, Luk.</hi> 10.42. as to their proper center, yet are there in the world courſes of our naturall life, ſo many caſes, and ſome of conſcience, which require a right iudgement, in regard of circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and manner of doing: that he had neede of more then a minde to doe well, that will walke as hee ought in things honeſt towards them that are without, and in things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different towards them that are weake within: for we muſt not thinke that it is perfect wiſedome onely to vnderſtand the will of God, but perfect and true wiſedome is, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it to the life, in all the actions of our life. To doe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otherwiſe, or contrary, is not <hi>to walke wiſely, but as fooles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore hath the Scripture concluded all vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe vnder the name of folly; whether it be of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the minde, or peruerſeneſſe in the affections and will: ſo <hi>Miriams</hi> ſinne of grudging againſt her brother and Lord <hi>Moſes,</hi> is called a fooliſh ſinne, <hi>Num.</hi> 12.11. ſo the Iſraelites a froward people, are ſaid to be a fooliſh people, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.6. and <hi>Samuel</hi> told <hi>Saul,</hi> when hee had done wickedly, that he did fooliſhly, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Dauid</hi> confeſſeth as much againſt himſelfe, after he had numbred the people, ſaying: <hi>I haue done very fooliſhly,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.10.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150376:36"/>the Princes of <hi>Zoan</hi> are called fooles, <hi>Eſay</hi> 19.11. ſo are the wicked people in <hi>Ieremie,</hi> 4.22. and the Phariſes that were hypocrites, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.16, 17. and the rich man that was couetous, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.20. and the two Diſciples that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued not, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.25. The <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo are called fooles that <hi>knowing God, glorified him not as God, Rom.</hi> 1.21, 22. and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the Apoſtate <hi>Galathians, fooliſh Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Gal.</hi> 3.1.</p>
               <p>And thus it is plaine that all vnrighteouſneſſe is folly, and that all workers of iniquitie are fooles. If therefore we will be truely wiſe, we muſt be wiſe to doe good, and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to that which is euill. <hi>The heart of a wiſe man is at his right hand: but the heart of a foole is at his left,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Eccleſ.</hi> 10.2. It is properly vnderſtood of the good and bad ſucceſſe that followeth the actions of the wiſe, and fooliſh: and yet it may not vnproperly be referred to their different courſes of life; as that the heart of the wiſe is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer inclining to good, and the heart of fooles euer decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as by a left hand from it. And this ſeemeth to be the reaſon why the Phyloſopher, as hee accounted wiſedome the Queene and life of all morall vertues; ſo he did ſhut vp all vices in that one of folly. Where he thought not enough to doe <hi>bona,</hi> the things that were good, except wee did them <hi>bene,</hi> that is, wiſely and well in euery circumſtance: for if we erre but in one circumſtance we doe ill; and wee cannot doe perfectly well, vnleſſe well in all: therefore in the not perfection of our wayes, whoſe very perfection (as <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith) is to acknowledge how farre wee are from perfection. Our firſt point of wiſedome is, not onely to commit no folly, but to haue an eye to the good wee doe, and to that which we would doe wiſely, that it be good both in ſubſtance, and in manner of doing, and throughly and in euery part good; yea, well and good; well, as from vs, and good to our neighbour.</p>
               <p>Further, we may be ſaid <hi>to walke wiſely,</hi> when wee not onely ſeeme, but are Religious; and walke, both as the Law requires, and as good conſcience directs; not think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it enough to walke cloſely, vnleſſe we walk innocently.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150376:37"/>And our <hi>walking is with wiſedome,</hi> if wee haue the greateſt care of the greateſt matters: if we turne our eyes from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to our ſelues; for the iuſt man is the firſt accuſer of himſelfe; and if we follow what is commanded, not what we fancy in Religion: for folly hath this miſerie, to be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with it ſelfe: and it is hard to finde a man ſo fooliſh, that thinkes not himſelfe wiſe: ſo incurable is the ſickneſſe of thoſe that are wiſe in their owne opinion.</p>
               <p>But what wiſedome is in vs, <hi>reiecting the word of the Lord? Ier.</hi> 8.9. and how can wee be ſaid to <hi>walke wiſely,</hi> who walke not after true wiſedome, but after <hi>Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell?</hi> In Chriſtian vertues wee doe our dueties to halues, and therein profeſſe our ſelues wiſe: is this <hi>to walke wiſely?</hi> Wee draw examples into rules, and preſume that euery thing is lawfully done, that is done commonly. Many thinke it to be a ſafe and good plea to ſay, that either they were not the firſt that did ſo, or that they doe no more then others; Is there any wiſedome in this? but ſuch ſhall one day finde, that as they haue ſinned with the multitude, they ſhall be puniſhed with the multitude, and beare them company in their deſtruction, as they bore them company in their ſinne: they finned by example, but they ſhall be puniſhed in their owne perſons, when it will be but cold comfort to them to goe to hell with company. And then what wiſedome will it be to ſeeke a defence either in the example, or cuſtome of euill?</p>
               <p>Here, I would we that ſhould teach others, could teach our ſelues: wiſedome ſhould be in our mouthes, and the vertue of it in our wayes: but doe wee not follow the droue to the ſhambles, that ſhould lead the ſheepe of the ſlaughter to Chriſt? Wee that ſhould turne others from the world, doe we not cleaue to the world our ſelues? and haue we not our conuerſation in couetouſneſſe, that ſay to another, <hi>thou ſhalt not couet?</hi> Wee ſhould conquer the world, and hath not the world made a conqueſt of vs? Wee are not vnder that tyrannie that did Cloiſter the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell from theſe outward things, and from all libertie in them: but are wee ſo circumſpectly wiſe, as
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150376:37"/>to vſe this our libertie without ſcandall? Doe we gouerne our families to the example of others? Doe wee vſe the World as if wee vſed it not? Or rather doe we not vſe it, as if we had skill to vſe nothing elſe? Or, as if it were our charge, and not the flocke of Chriſt committed to vs? Many haue a minde to enter the courſe of godlineſſe, who ſtill ſtand at the gate, or goe backe, taking a longer day. For, they deferre the reſolution, thinking they can neuer beginne to late, where true Chriſtians thinke, they can neuer beginne too ſoone. One ſpeaking of folly, ſpeaketh well of ſuch: <hi>Inter caeter a mala hoc quoque habet ſtultitia, ſemper incipit viuere;</hi> among many other euils that folly hath, this is one, ſhee is euer beginning to liue. Doe ſuch walke wiſely? To theſe wee may adde another kinde of fooles, that walke no better. And they are ſuch as make (indeed) more haſte to beginne, but with as ill ſpeede: for they dwell vpon their beginnings, and are neuer led for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to perfection. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1. Hauing gotten the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of forward men, they ſpend vpon the ſtocke of that poore credit of theirs, till all be gone. And theſe, in ſteede of walking wiſely, walke as fooliſhly as any: for, beſides that they leaue to bee good, they deſire to bee no better; and they left (but) the World with <hi>Demas,</hi> to returne more violently to it; before they held it in one hand, now they embrace it with both. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But is euery <hi>walking wiſely</hi> walking well? <hi>Anſ.</hi> Euery <hi>walking wiſely</hi> according to the word; wherein, and wherein onely is true wiſedome, is ſafe walking and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wel: not elſe, for wiſdome in her corruption is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of hereſie for opinion, and of diſobedience for action: yet humbled vnder the ſpirit, and directed by the word, ſhe becomes both a bulwarke for truth, and a guide for well doing. So the Apoſtle vnderſtandeth wiſedome, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.8. ſaying, <hi>that God was abundant toward vs in all wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge.</hi> And here he maketh theſe two, to wit, <hi>ſapience,</hi> whereby we vnderſtand heauenly things; and <hi>prudence,</hi> whereby we rightly apply whatſoeuer wee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand of God in heauenly things, to the dueties of our
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150376:38"/>Chriſtian life, theſe (I ſay) he maketh two maine props of faith: by which it is plaine that policie and true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are not ſuch ſtrangers as ſome would make them. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede craft and true religion can neuer meet, but wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and godlineſſe may: and Chriſtian policie in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians is ſometimes, and for ſome purpoſes neceſſary: therefore our Sauiour Chriſt, when he ſent his Diſciples, as Sheepe among Wolues, bidding them to <hi>be wiſe as Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents:</hi> not wiſe Serpents, that is, craftily wiſe; but yet <hi>wiſe as Serpents,</hi> that is, politiquely ſo. He requires (I grant) ſimplicitie of them: but it is the ſimplicitie, not of Aſſes, but of Doues, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.16. that is, innocent: ſimplicitie, not ſillie ſimplicitie. And this wiſedome <hi>Paul</hi> vſed in the councell, when hee caſt a bone betweene the <hi>Sadduces</hi> and the <hi>Phariſes, Acts</hi> 23.6, 7. ſaying, <hi>I am a Phariſe, the ſonne of a Phariſe, of the hope of the reſurrection of the dead am I accuſed:</hi> and ſo ſet them together.</p>
               <p>This, no way iuſtifieth that myſterie of iniquitie that worketh in thoſe faithleſſe and craftie <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> whom the father of errours ſendeth ouer vnto vs; men of as many ſoules, as <hi>Proteus</hi> had faces: <hi>Quo teneam vultus mutan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Protea nodo?</hi> ſaith the Poet: that is, how ſhall we lay a net for ſuch changelings? or catch, as in a knot, ſuch ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery Eeles, and flies of <hi>Rome,</hi> that breake through all Lawes, and haue halfe in their lips, and halfe in their heart and conſcience?</p>
               <p>Theſe are not godly but wickedly wiſe, nor without guile wiſe, but wiſe to doe euill. But wherein (chiefely) conſiſteth ſpirituall wiſedome, and circumſpect walking? in, and by <hi>redeeming the time:</hi> for it followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>VERS. 16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Redeeming the time: for the dayes are euill.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THey that redeeme the ſeaſon, making euery time the time of repentance, are ſpiritually wiſe, and doe <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150376:38"/>walke.</hi> Not they that apply themſelues to all times, nor they that vainly ſpend the good houres of time: for ſuch poure out their time, as water that is ſpilt, which cannot be gathered vp againe; and doe not redeeme time, but looſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> To <hi>redeeme the time</hi> (therefore) is, not to neglec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> grace that it offereth: for though the time be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> too late, when a man doth repent, and God be <hi>of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuffering and great patience;</hi> yet haue wee no patent of that acceptable time of grace: and he that biddeth vs, <hi>while we haue the light, to beleeue in the light, Iohn</hi> 12.36. giues vs to vnderſtand that the hauing of the light is no inheritance.</p>
               <p>Gods peculiar people (the Iewes) had the light of the world firſt offered to them in Chriſts Preaching and Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, but when they <hi>loued darkeneſſe more then light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their deedes were euill, Iohn</hi> 3.19. their light was put out in deepe darkeneſſe, in which they wander from the Lord of life, to this day: the day of ſaluation, or accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble day, that was offered them, they regarded not; then came this long
<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 9.4.</note> night of their baniſhment from the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Gods people: and <hi>God hath giuen them the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of ſlumber, eyes that they ſhould not ſee, and eares that they ſhould not heare, Rom.</hi> 11.6. the darkneſſe that was vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Gentiles is caſt vpon them; and they are a people <hi>that know not whether they go, Iohn</hi> 12.35. This came vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, becauſe they would not <hi>know</hi> (by way of redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) <hi>in their day, thoſe things which belonged vnto their peace;</hi> and <hi>now they are hid from their eyes, Luke</hi> 19.42. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46.</p>
               <p>The <hi>ſeauen Churches of Aſia were ſeauen golden Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlestickes,</hi> and had goodly lights burning vpon them: but when by careleſſe negligence, they fell away from better to worſe, who ſhould haue proceeded from good to better; not redeeming time, but making large penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths of it for pernicious errours and carnall looſeneſſe, by which they fall away more and more, <hi>Eſay</hi> 1.5. their Candleſticks were remoued, and their glorious light put out, and they made a prey to the darkeneſſe of <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:150376:39"/>It is an high point of wiſedome (therefore) to keepe euen reckoning with our time, and not to runne behinde hand with good houres; for occaſion is bald behinde, and they that are wiſe will take hold of her fore-locke: though the Lord be alwayes to be ſought, yet then ſpecially, <hi>while he may be found, Eſay</hi> 55.6. and though alwayes to be <hi>called vpon,</hi> yet chiefely and moſt, <hi>when he is neare, ibid.</hi> There was nothing more importantly obiected to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> then that <hi>ſhe remembred not her latter end, Lam.</hi> 1.9. and God, by <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> reproueth his peoples negligence in taking hold of times and ſeaſons for their turning to him, making the ſimple creatures of the aire, in their kinde, to giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt them: for <hi>they know their appointed times, and keepe the time of their comming,</hi> ſaith the Lord, (hee ſpeaketh of the Storke, the Turtle, Crane, and Swallow that obſerue this order) <hi>but my people know not</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>the iudgement of their God, Ier.</hi> 8.7. Though hee that came at the eleauenth houre, had his pennie, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.9. yet truſt not to that: for, thou maiſt be in hell long before thou ſee that houre, and that is ſet down to keepe vs from deſpaire, not to harten vs to preſumption.</p>
               <p>As (therefore) wiſe Merchants take the preſent fitteſt time for the buying of their commodities: ſo wiſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the beſt Merchants of time, ſhould take the preſent ſeaſon for the making of it theirs, by well-doing: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing neglected (already) many good houres, and yet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more offered (though they cannot call backe one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of time paſt) they ſhould double their paines and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence about the gainefull employment of thoſe that are before them, thereby to make (as it were) ſome amends or ſatisfaction for their loſſes before, doing as much good now, as they might haue done, both now and then. To moue vs to this; let vs conſider (firſt) how nimble and fleete time is, and how ſoone it paſſeth away: the time paſt is gone, the time to come is not yet: onely the preſent may be called time, and what is it? or of what continuance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ſooner come, then it is gone againe? Then what fooles are they that ſo much trouble themſelues with the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150376:39"/>getting away of time that paſſeth ſo quickly, nothing more? But ſuch thoughts wiſe men are eaſed of, and fooles may ſpare; time will go faſt enough without driuing; and therefore let our greateſt care bee to <hi>gather vp the frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and very crummes of time that nothing be loſt,</hi> Iohn 6.12.</p>
               <p>Secondly, let vs conſider how precious time is, and therefore how worthy to be redeemed. Good husbands know this, who will looſe no time for their wealth and markets: And Philoſophers, who knew not any life here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, how were they ſet for the redeeming of time in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of no worth? How loath were they to vnbend their vaine ſtudies for their very meales and naturall reſt? And ſhall we thinke the time long, and the husbandrie ill ſpent that is beſtowed vpon wares of better nature then worldly riches, that is, that is laid out vpon heauenly wealth, and the true treaſure? Shall the heathen ſo occupie time for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine markets; and ſhall we ſeeing the markets we deale in, are of our certaine redemption, tary at home in our idleneſſe, and looſe ſo precious houres?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, let vs conſider how little of our time is in our owne power: onely the time preſent is ours, and how ſmall a thing that is wee haue heard; the time paſt is gone from vs, and for hereafter, who hath power of that, that may bee? For, our life is a vapour, and in a moment wee may be taken away.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, let vs conſider how ſhort our time is; and learne of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the man of God, by ſo poore an Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticke of our dayes, to number them wiſely, not by the Church-booke, but by the true feare of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.12. Euery day windes vp ſome part of the thread of our life, which is of no great length in the longeſt liuer. The far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we paſſe from the firſt day of our birth, the neerer we draw to the laſt houre of our life: and ſo wee goe but to death, and not a foote from it,; therefore ſaith the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul, while you haue time doe good to all. Gal.</hi> 6.10. As if hee had ſaid, you haue no ſuch great abundance of it, that you can ſpare any.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:150376:40"/>
               <p> Fifthly, let vs conſider, that <hi>our aduerſarie the Diuell as a roaring Lion walketh about ſeeking whom he may deuoure,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. that is, the Diuell will looſe no time to deſtroy vs, and therefore let vs redeeme all houres of time to ſaue our ſelues and others. I ſpeake to ſuch as haue the charge of others in the miniſtrie, or (more generally) in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. This Apoſtle of ours did ſo: for writing to <hi>Timothie</hi> he ſaith: <hi>Theſe things write I vnto thee truſting to come ſhortly,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.14. He was vnwilling to looſe any time, which he might husband profitably for Gods glorie and the Churches ſeruice; elſe he might haue ſaid, becauſe I meane to come ſhortly I will not write now. But that that may bee done to day, muſt not be put off till the morrow or the next day: and the Apoſtle would looſe no time, that the diuell might not bee any gainer by him. Which ſhould ſtirre vp negligent Miniſters, who giue Satan time too much, to ſpoile the Lords inheritance. But looke what we looſe, the Diuell gets; if we ſcatter time, he will gather it; and where we are idle he works.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, let vs conſider that time muſt be reckoned for, though (here) wee make no conſcience to looſe whole dayes, and weekes, and moneths, yet we ſhall one day pay to God the ſhot of time, in the ſtrict account of our houres, when our poore ſoules ſhall bee committed to torments, and bodie and ſoule ſhall bee caſt into hell. This ſhould make vs enter into a trembling conſideration with our ſelues about our great arrerage of time; as to thinke how much is vpon the booke for exceſſiue ſleepe, for immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate gaming, for our carnall fellowſhip, for much idle talke, vaine thoughts, and inordinate worldlineſſe: and finding ſo much loſt and ſpent already, do as wiſe husbands in ſuch a caſe ſhould do; that is, grieue for that which is paſt, and bee better husbands hereafter of all our houres, redeeming the time behind, and beginning prouidently to ſaue, before all be gone.</p>
               <p>Seuenthly, let vs conſider and call to minde the example of Chriſt, whoſe doings, as our light wee ſhould follow, and to whoſe perſon, as our beſt precedent, wee ſhould
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150376:40"/>conforme. hee ſaith, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.4. <hi>I muſt worke the workes of him that ſent mee, while it is day:</hi> he ſaith, hee muſt, and it is ſure he did; for hee ſpent the day in teaching, and the night in prayer. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.37.</p>
               <p>Let vs (eightly) conſider, that as God hath appointed that good ſhould be done; ſo he hath ſet the opertunities and ſeaſons wherein to doe it; and therefore hath made euery thing beautifull in the time thereof. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.11. Now, if wee neglect this time with Ieruſalem, what can we looke for, but that the line of Ieruſalem ſhould be ſpred ouer vs for ſuch our negligence, and more then brutiſh contempt of good houres? <hi>Luke</hi> 19.42, 43, 44.</p>
               <p>And now, to caſt vp the reckoning of all that hath beene ſpoken, let vs put theſe together; the nothing of our flight time: the price it carieth with the children of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: how little of it is in our owne power; how ſhort and flitting it is; how much Sathan (to teach, or ſhame vs) ſetteth by it for his owne ends; that houres, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes muſt be accounted for: that Chriſt (for our imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) loſt no houre of time for his Fathers ſeruice, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and that good is to bee done, in that time and ſeaſon, that God (moſt wiſe) hath appointed to it; and hauing made this account, let vs denie (if wee can) that time is to be redeemed.</p>
               <p>O (then) let vs not ſuffer any good occaſion of doing good to ſlip away from vs, but let vs lay ſure hold of it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting one another, while it is called to day. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.13. Euery moment of our life, is the opportunitie giuen for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life, it is that acceptable time, and day of ſaluation, ſpoken of, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. that time of life, wherein God viſiteth vs with his Word and Goſpel, ſpeaking to vs by his Word, and knocking at our hearts by his mercies, and iudgements: Oh, let vs not ſuffer the bleſſing of theſe golden times to bee loſt, or in vaine to bee beſtowed vpon vs.</p>
               <p>Some good things reach not vnto, nor may bee done at all times, as the hearing and reading of the Word, the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of good bookes, conference, ſolemne, and ſet prayer,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150376:41"/>admonition, reproofe, almes: For, theſe muſt haue, and enioy their owne oportunities; but euery time, is a time of turning to God, all times are fit times for the exerciſe of our faith, for repentance of ſinnes, for amendment of life, and for reconciliation with God: Oh (therefore) let theſe ſeaſons and oportunities of times in Gods mercy, bee euer deere vnto vs, let vs deferre no meanes or time, that the Lord ſhall offer (fitly) to vs for theſe dueties, but redeeme them with our preſent induſtrie, and labour of loue, not receiuing ſo much grace in vaine.</p>
               <p>Let vs conſider our miſpent time, and by greater dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in well doing, fetch as much of it (as we can) backe againe by running the way of Gods Commaundements. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.32. Let <hi>Saul</hi> runne to the harpe of his pleaſures, and they that are drunken with the delights of life, as with that wine wherein is exceſſe, let them make themſelues muſicke with mery fellowſhip, to driue away dumpes: but let vs, to whom God hath giuen a better minde, and another ſpirit, take heede how we forfeite the oportunitie of repentance, for ſuch vaine matters: and let vs remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that time well paſt, is the beſt paſtime in the World. Hee that other wayes, paſſes his time, turnes his paſtime into ſinne.</p>
               <p>And becauſe as was ſaid, our time goes away faſt enough, faſter then a Poſt, and as ſoone as a thought, what neede wee (ſo much and ordinarily) in vaine ſports to ſeeke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies againſt it? The yeeres we haue ſeene are gone, the few that are behind, will not tarry long after; and one end ſhall bee vnto all. This end is death, the common end of the liuing, and the happy end of the righteous. Let it bee our care (therefore) to redeeme time, not to caſt it away, and our ſoules with it, vpon the pleaſures of ſinne, as they, who doe more ſeruice to their bellies in one day, then they doe, in a whole yeere of dayes, to God.</p>
               <p>Wary &amp; wel-thriuing husbands, hauing had ſome great loſſe, will watch all Markets, and oportunities to recouer it. Now what greater loſſe, can come to a (truely) and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriuing Chriſtian, then his great loſſe of the time of the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150376:41"/>Goſpel, which is the time of repentance: and ſhould not this force him to follow earneſtly, and continually, all the Markets and oportunities of Religion that he can heare of, thereby to make vp his former great loſſe, at ſuch Chriſtian aſſemblies?</p>
               <p>The way-faring man, hauing ſlept too long in bed, or ſate too late at dinner, will make amends for it by making more haſte (afterwards) in his way: ſo we that trauell to our owne Countrey of heauen; hauing before, either ſlept out our good time in an idle life, or ſate it out in pleaſures, ſhould be (by ſo much the more) carefull hereafter, to quit the way faſter, by giuing all diligence <hi>to make our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and election ſure,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. for it is ſufficient for vs that we haue ſpent the time paſt of our life after the luſt of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> walking in wantonneſſe, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 4.3. Now it is high time, that wee beſtow that well and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in Gods ſeruice, that is to come; redeeming with our bodies, goods, and life (if neede were) that which is paſt, We heard how our Sauiour Chriſt beſtowed all his houres, to the glory of his Father and good of mankinde: at great feaſts hee would looſe no time; and at one feaſt, how many things taught he concerning the feaſts of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and bread of heauen? <hi>Luk</hi> 14.15, 16. &amp;c. At <hi>Iacobs</hi> Well, when he talked with the woman that was a harlot; how did hee forget his owne neede of the water of the Well, to ſatisfie her neceſſitie with the <hi>waters of the Well of life? Iohn</hi> 4.7, 10, 11, 12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how after did he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect his owne meat, to doe that <hi>(which was his meat and drinke) the will of his Father? Iohn</hi> 4.34. What occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did hee omit to doe good? by occaſions of the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, how did he prouide and ſpeake for his fathers ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall harueſt? <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.37.38. And by occaſion of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, how did hee warne his Diſciples of the leauen of corrupt doctrine and corrupt men? <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.11. And what is this but to teach vs to redeeme time by his example that loſt none?</p>
               <p>And if filthy perſons can take all occaſions of filthy talke and doings; ſhall wee (that are Saints by calling)
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150376:42"/>looſe any occaſion of ſpeaking well, and doing good, to the edification of our ſelues and others? ſo much the rather (as it followeth in the laſt place) <hi>becauſe</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The dayes are euill.)</hi> No day conſidered in it ſelfe, is euill; and all dayes, conſidered in their Creator, and firſt creation, are good, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31. Here then we muſt confeſſe a trope, and that the dayes are not properly, but by a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, <hi>euill;</hi> that is euill, for the euils in them: or, becauſe they are infected with the pitch and canker of the world, that lieth wholly in wickedneſſe, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.19. So the daies here are ſaid to be euill, becauſe the men in them were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. And this is reaſon enough to perſwade the children of God to be good husbands of their houres, and to take heede into what places and companies they come, leaſt they take the infection, as a man may comming into a plaguy-houſe: for no plaguie aire can ſo ſoone infect the body, as the aire of euill company may the ſoule, This is plaine by the examples of <hi>Lot,</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and of <hi>Dauid</hi> among the <hi>Philiſtims. Lot</hi> learned to drinke liberally in <hi>Sodome,</hi> and did ſo out of <hi>Sodome, Gen.</hi> 19.33.35. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in the Court of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> courted it with diſſembling, and ſwearing <hi>by the life of Pharaoh, Gen</hi> 42.15. and <hi>Dauid,</hi> who ſuffered much, and learned great obedience by the things which he ſuffered; being but a while among the vncircumciſed <hi>Philistims,</hi> learned to lye and to diſſemble, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.10.11.</p>
               <p>Seeing (therefore) the dayes are ſo euill, that is, the men in them; how circumſpectly ſhould good men walke, and wiſely paſſe their time, leaſt they be circumuented? ſeeing ſo many thornes are about them, how wary ſhould they be both what they touch, and how they goe? The world will ſay, becauſe <hi>the dayes are euill,</hi> let vs be euill for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: but the ſpirit ſaith not ſo; but <hi>redeeme the ſeaſon, becauſe the dayes are euill:</hi> that is, though others be naught, and ſtarke naught, yet be you good and very good: good your ſelues, and meanes to make others good: and ſome ſay, <hi>the dayes are euill,</hi> therefore as the dayes are, ſo be yee: but the ſpirit ſaith, <hi>the dayes are euill,</hi> therefore take heede
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150376:42"/>ye be not as they are; that is, naught as they be. But were the dayes euill when the Apoſtle wrote? then what ſhould let vs to call them euill now? or were they (then) in the poſitiue, <hi>euill?</hi> they are (now) in the ſuparlatiue, worſt: for that that was full then, runnes ouer now; iniquitie I meane, that hath gotten the vpper hand, and workes with both hands.</p>
               <p>At the reformation of the Goſpell, by the zeale of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> one diuell was caſt out, but ſeauen haue returned ſince, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.26. we haue ſeene the growth of ſpirituall <hi>Eſau</hi> among vs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.27. the euill men and deceiuers waxe worſe and worſe, <hi>deceiuing and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13. but we grow not as <hi>Iacob,</hi> from good to better: we are turned from Poperie, but are we turned to the liuing God? and not turned rather from him to Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme: that is, from the falſe God, to no God? the furnace of ſtrange luſts, as that of <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi> in <hi>Babylon,</hi> is it not come from one heating, to be heated ſeauen times more in our dayes, then in any age before vs, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.19. that is, is not luſt (the furnace) ſeuen times more luſtfull? Pride ſeauen times more proud? Wantonneſſe, ſeauen times more wanton? Adulterie, ſeauen times more adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer? Drunkenneſſe, ſeauen times more drunkard? and euery ſinne, is it not ſeauen times more ſinfull? and doe we grow as <hi>Iacob?</hi> or rather doe we not grow as <hi>Eſau,</hi> from euill to worſe? <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.27. What treaſons in Court? What poiſonings at Court? What vnwonted prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Court and Countrey?</p>
               <p>In our Sauiours dayes men ſold and bought in the Church; in our times, Churches themſelues are bought and ſold, <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.24. In the Apoſtolike and firſt times of the Goſpell, the Heathen onely perſecuted Chriſtians: in our age of it, <hi>Manaſſeh Ephraim, Ephraim Manaſſeh,</hi> and both againſt <hi>Iudah, Eſay</hi> 9.21. Ieſuites and Prieſts one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another; and both againſt the Goſpell: nay (which is a warre more vnnaturall) <hi>Iudah</hi> againſt it ſelfe: and the diuiſions of <hi>Rubin</hi> haue bred great thoughts of heart, <hi>Iud.</hi> 5.15. I cannot containe, to remember what miſchiefes this
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150376:43"/>bitter warre of brethren hath already, and is like further to bring forth: and what Chriſtian heart can abſtaine from ſighes and lamentations, to ſee ſo many graue, wiſe, and learned Chriſtians to moleſt one another? The Shepheards to be at variance? the poore Sheepe (for whom the Lord Ieſus ſhed his moſt precious bloud) to be ſo turned out to Wolues &amp; ſpoile? the common people to be ſo diſtracted? errours and Atheiſme ſo to abound, and get head? the cauſe and glory of the Goſpell ſo to be weakned; and men alſo diſcouraged by them, by whom they ſhould be lured and begotten to the truth; that it may truely be ſaid in our dayes, which was ſpoken long ſince; <hi>Quae modo mater erat, formam capit illa Nouercae; &amp; quos lacte aliut, conficit illa flagris:</hi> that is, She that was a mother becomes ſtepmother, and whom once ſhe ſuckled with milke, ſhee torments with ſtripes?</p>
               <p>Our contention is hotter and hotter, our enemies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe that trouble vs; they that hate vs laugh, but the Church weeps that ſhould be comforted by vs; and though ſhe bleede in a veine of ignorance through our common diſtraction; yet no man ſaith to his brethren at variance; <hi>Why ſtriue yee? why doe ye wrong one to another? Acts</hi> 7.26. O! that it were conſidered what great loſſe the Church (daily) ſuffereth by this plague of diſſention? O! that we had betimes, or would yet in time remember, <hi>How good a thing it is for brethren to dwell together in vnitie?</hi> If wee did, or had done ſo, the ſtorme that waxeth thicker and thicker had bin ſcattered, and we ſhould haue ſeene a faire calme of peace in the Churches of <hi>England,</hi> at this day: but our breach is as the Sea, and theſe euill dayes know nothing of the wayes of peace.</p>
               <p>But to goe on: in the Apoſtles dayes, and neare them; what running to the Goſpell? now, what running from it? then, what plaineneſſe in teachers? now, what equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation? then, what obedience to heathen <hi>Caeſar?</hi> now, what practiſing againſt Chriſtian <hi>Caeſars?</hi> then, what ſtrengthning of the Goſpell? now, what vnder-mining it by the builders themſelues? It were infinite to ſpeake euen
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150376:43"/>of generall euils, that are infinite; and therefore I will come to an iſſue with you, and draw to an end.</p>
               <p>Seeing <hi>the dayes are</hi> (thus) <hi>euill;</hi> the greater wiſedome is required of vs, and muſt be vſed by vs, for our auoiding of the infection of that corrupt fellowſhip and miſgouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that (like venome) ſheds it ſelfe vpon all that come neere it. So farre off we muſt be, <hi>becauſe the dayes are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill;</hi> from being euill as they are, that wee muſt take the more paines, and heede to be good. And here, we ſhould rather goe alone in the narrow way, then <hi>follow a multitude to doe euill, Exod.</hi> 23.2. If it be of the faſhion to be euill; we muſt be like vnto Chriſt, and reſemble good Chriſtians, who doe not <hi>faſhion themſelus like vnto this world, Rom.</hi> 12.2. but are in their Maſters faſhion, and conforme to him. But ſome will doe as the world doth, and goe whither the moſt lead them; and whither is that? euen <hi>to the houſe where the dead are, Pro.</hi> 9.18. and what to doe? to be mad with the company, to be baited with their allurements, and to eate of ſuch things as pleaſe them: but no example ſhould preuaile ſo farre (though of thouſands that ſo doe) as to draw vs into wayes of wickedneſſe with follies chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: and if we would not be damned with ſuch mates, we muſt not follow their damnable wayes, their pipes of ſmoake, and pots of exceſſe.</p>
               <p>Againe, ſome feare not the contagious aire of any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie: why, what is their confidence? No company (ſay they) can doe vs hurt. Can it not? and why can it not hurt them? Is it becauſe they are (already) ſo bad, that no company can make them worſe? or haue they forgotten, what company was able to doe againſt <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe (a farre holier man then themſelues) in <hi>Caiaphas</hi> hall? <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.70, 72, 74. Likewiſe, how it preuailed againſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Lot,</hi> vertuous <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> Gods owne King? If theſe were intangled, ſhall they goe free? if theſe carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them a ſmatch of the company, that yet they lik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not; ſhall they that runne deſperately vpon the ſharpe of this worldly fellowſhip, and take pleaſure in it, keepe their ſtate ſtill? It cannot be: and therefore (to make my
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150376:44"/>end here) I beſeech you remember your great danger, and forget not your holy calling in theſe euill dayes; ſo euill, that you may not bee moued from your hope: for this cauſe, take vnto you <hi>the whole armour of God, that yee may be able to reſiſt in the euill day:</hi> and, <hi>hauing finiſhed all things ſtand faſt. Eph.</hi> 6.13. <hi>The God of power giue you to bee ſo minded:</hi> and to this, God the Father, with his holy Sonne Chriſt Ieſus, and the Spirit of both; three perſons in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, one God in vnitie, be rendred all glory, dominion, and honour, now and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:150376:44"/>
            <head>THE SHORT PROSPERITY of the Wicked: <hi>AND THE</hi> HAPPIE ESTATE of the IVST.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 37. Ver. 35, 36, 37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I haue ſeene the wicked in great power: and ſpreading him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe like a greene Bay-tree.</p>
                  <p>Yet he paſſed away, and loe hee was not: yea, I ſought him, but he could not be found.</p>
                  <p>Marke the perfect man, and behold the vpright: for the end of that man is peace.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
               <hi>Haue ſeene the wicked ſtrong, &amp;c.</hi> There are two things obſeruable in this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: the vnſtable proſperity of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 35, 36. and the certaine and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant felicitie of the righteous, <hi>verſ.</hi> 37. Albeit that the wicked man be neuer ſo ſtrong, and in the pride of his heart, ſpread abroad, like a greene Bay-tree, neuer ſo faire; yet hee ſuddenly paſſeth, and is little marked, he vaniſheth ſpeedily, and is as little remembred: whereas the iuſt and vpright man, though his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150376:45"/>life be a kinde of warfare on earth, findes peace at the laſt; and after his red euening a faire day followeth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.2. This is the ſum and ſcope of theſe three verſes. A point (if euer) neceſſary, now moſt needfull for our preſent times and ſtate; and ſuch as can neuer be too much vrged, or enough conſidered, ſpecially ſince it is a thing incident to the beſt, to looke but on the outſide of things, and to meaſure the ſecret iudgements of God with the ſcant yard of his outward bleſſings: whereas indeede his very chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings are bleſſings; and that (which we account bleſſing) but a fatning to the ſlaughter: for, not to ſay any thing of meere fleſh and bloud, <hi>who ſay in their hearts there is no God, Pſal.</hi> 14.1. or at the beſt no Prouidence of God, <hi>Quòd malis benè eſt, &amp; bonis malè:</hi> ſeeing it goeth well with thoſe that are euill, and ill with thoſe that are good, it is a temptation greater then the very children of God can o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome or reſiſt, as long as they are cloathed with this earthly and mortall tabernacle, to ſee the wicked ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and high to riſe aboue the head of the righteous; and to haue, not a large meaſure, but ſuch an ouer-meaſure of theſe commodities and bleſſings that they ſo much want; whoſe godlineſſe (notwithſtanding) <hi>hath the promiſe of the life preſent,</hi> and not onely, <hi>of the life to come,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. for albeit <hi>godlineſſe be great,</hi> of it ſelfe (I doe not ſay) riches, but <hi>gaine,</hi> and haue enough in it ſelfe, to commend it for it ſelfe, to all that are godly-wiſe; yet I know not how it commeth to paſſe, that we praiſe the thing, but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for the reward, and ſtand more vpon the fruit, then the conſcience of a good worke.</p>
            <p>We can be content with the old people and children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to giue an eare to the Commandement of louing the Lord, and of fearing him, and ſwearing by his name, as we finde it of record, in <hi>Deuteronomie chapter</hi> 6 <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. but our chiefe reſpect and ſpeciall eye is to the promiſes there ſpoken of; as the <hi>prolonging of our dayes in the Land,</hi> our increaſe therein, and proſperitie in the bleſſings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; our hauing of Cities which we builded not, houſes full of goods which wee filled not; Wels which wee digged
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150376:45"/>not; Vineyards and Oliue-trees which wee planted not, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.2, 3, 10, 11. We can be content to <hi>ſeeke the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God and his righteouſneſſe, Mat.</hi> 6.33. but not in the firſt place, and with our firſt care, and our zeale will ſoone waxe cold if <hi>all other things be not added to vs.</hi> In a word, we can be content to thinke that <hi>godlineſſe is great riches;</hi> but if the promiſes which it hath of this life, be not preſently performed to it, we thinke <hi>wee haue clenſed our hearts in vaine, and waſhed our hands in innocencie, Pſalme</hi> 73.13.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, the want of theſe outward things in the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though it be a tentation very grieuous, doth not ſo much trouble them, as that they are poured out in ſo great plenty and fulneſſe vpon the wicked: for howſoeuer there are to be found, that haue ſo farre profited in the Schoole of the croſſe, that they can ſuffer many things for Chriſt, and for his name and teſtimony, with great patience and ſound ioy: yet who is hee that is not moued beyond his patience, and afflicted euen aboue the meaſure of his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to ſee the wicked, not onely free from troubles, in the day of his trouble, but a worker of his woe, and of the ſtraits that he is in; and not onely armed with power againſt him, but inſulting with pride ouer him? Nay, what greater indignitie and heauier croſſe can there come to the godly, then to haue the foot of pride to come againſt him, and the hand of wickednes to be vpon him? <hi>Pſ.</hi> 36.11. Who more exerciſed then <hi>Dauid,</hi> and therefore more like to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure troubles then he? yet in this caſe, his <hi>feet were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt gone, his ſteps had well neere ſlipt, Pſal.</hi> 73.2. Who more patient then <hi>Iob,</hi> that mirrour or rather miracle of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? yet in this very caſe, hee was ſo farre from ſilence (one of the trueſt ſignes of patience) that hee queſtioneth why the <hi>wicked ſhould liue, waxe old, and grow in wealth? Iob</hi> 21.7. Who apter to melt into teares, for the daughter of Sion in affliction, then weeping <hi>Ieremie?</hi> yet in this point alſo he groweth to a degree of choller, and reaſoneth with God himſelfe about the matter, asking <hi>why the way of the wicked ſhould proſper,</hi> and they be in <hi>wealth that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliouſly
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150376:46"/>tranſgreſſe? Ier.</hi> 12.1. Becauſe <hi>God is of pure eyes, and cannot behold euill;</hi> therefore, as if he were bound to giue an account of his matters to man, <hi>Habacucke</hi> cals him forth, as if it were before the barre to anſwer him, <hi>Why he lookes vpon the tranſgreſſion, and holds his tongue, when the wicked deuoures the man that is more righteous then hee? Hab.</hi> 1.13.</p>
            <p>So great an eye-ſore is the greatneſſe of the wicked to the conſciences of the godly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which infirmitie in them (to call it as it is) as it groweth from no other cauſe, &amp; as it were root, but that we meaſure them by their preſent eſtates: ſo hath it no other remedy, but to examine them by their ends; in the which we ſhall finde as great cauſe of comfort for the one, as we take of griefe at the other.</p>
            <p>And therefore againſt all ſuch diſcomforts and vnſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, cauſed by a wrie conſideration of Gods ſtraight and iuſt wayes in all that hee doth (who can doe nothing but that which is equall and good) let vs take <hi>Dauids</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and <hi>Dauids</hi> word here, <hi>I haue ſeene:</hi> as if hee had ſaid; but I ſee it not now: or the wicked man was ſtrong, but is not: and was great, but is nothing now &amp; no where, ſaue in ſome ſtrong priſon, or iudged to ſome baſe death: for, therefore hath <hi>Dauid</hi> the King ſet downe thus much for our learning, drawne (as it were) out of the boſome of his owne experience, that we ſhould not be offended too much at the proſperitie of the vngodly, as hee himſelfe once was: becauſe, howſoeuer (for theſe outward matters) he be ſtrong and in power, and (which is the effect of worldly power) ſpread, and vaunt himſelfe like a greene Bay, which can hardly wither: <hi>yet he paſſed away and was gone:</hi> neither could he be found with ſeeking: where yet the <hi>vpright and iuſt man,</hi> though his preſent caſe ſeeme miſerable, his euerlaſting eſtate is not ſo, and <hi>his end is peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this kinde of arguing from the experience of Gods Saints, in the Scriptures, muſt needes be of force (if any) to ſettle &amp; quiet vs in the ſtrongeſt aſſaults of the wickeds proſperitie, which is ſo ſhort and miſerable at laſt: for,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150376:46"/>though the <hi>wiſedome of the world</hi> make experience but the <hi>Master of fooles,</hi> and <hi>reaſon</hi> the <hi>wiſeſt teacher:</hi> yet in the right ſearch of Gods iudgments, it is of force to ſet Reaſon it ſelfe to Schcole, and to conuince the beſt wiſedome in Schooles, of folly: for it is not to be doubted, but that as <hi>whatſoeuer things are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are written for our learning:</hi> ſo the experience of <hi>Dauid</hi> in this place, and of others in other Scriptures, is ſet downe and regiſtred for a direction and rule to our iudgements vpon like occaſions as this was: not that the iudgements of God, in theſe our dayes, are not legible by a weake eye, as written in capitall letters, that all may read: but that they may be leſſe doubted of, hauing the conſent and witneſſe of other times. And if it be true which one ſpeaketh of other ſtories; that, <hi>neſcire quid, antequam natus ſis, gestum fuerit, quid eſt aliud quam ſemper eſſe puerum?</hi> not to know what was done before thou waſt borne, what is it, but ſtill to be a childe? How can they, who are not acquainted with the experiences of Gods children, in the Bibles ſtorie (matters that were done long before their cradle) but be very <hi>babes in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is but a ſmall thing that any one can obſerue and ſee in ſo ſhort a life as we now haue, whereof the one part is gone before we thinke, and (while wee thinke) the other: and (therefore) to enrich our obſeruation, it is neceſſary that we ſhould be acquainted with Gods marueilous workes, done before our time, and written for our learning. It plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God (ſometimes) to ſet ſome vpon Stages, in whoſe perſons he (liuely) acteth his iudgements for the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an age (our memory and age hath ſeene ſome, and ſome (yet) it may behold at this day:) yet doth he it not to the end wee ſhould content our ſelues with our owne experience, but that wee ſhould compare wiſely together what hath bin done in our owne daies, and in the times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs. But now to the matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hee ſaw, &amp;c.</hi> Hee had not onely experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by reading what God had ſtrangely done before his time, but was an eye-witneſſe of many great alterations
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150376:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>which hapned euen in his owne time, as in the ſtorie of his owne life, and in the bookes of <hi>Samuel</hi> and the <hi>Chronicles</hi> may be ſeene: Hee himſelfe ſaw the power and weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe both of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Abſolom;</hi> Hee <hi>ſaw them greene as a Bay-tree,</hi> and liued to ſee them as the greene graſſe, that being cut downe withereth. In the 73. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> hee ſaw that which much offended him, to wit, the wicked farre exalted aboue the godly: for their bodies <hi>he ſaw them lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and strong, and in no perill of death:</hi> free from thoſe troubles in their minde that others feele; the plague not once touching them that conſumeth others. He ſaw how they drunke large bleſſings of a full cup: how their <hi>eyes were ſwolne, and ſtood out with fatneſſe,</hi> which made many weake and ſimple ones to follow them: and how (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that their <hi>deſires were enlarged as hell</hi>) yet <hi>they had more then heart could wiſh:</hi> and as he ſaw their proſperitie, ſo <hi>hee beheld their destruction which came ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly:</hi> who (therefore) might more fitly be compared to <hi>greene graſſe</hi> then to a <hi>greene Bay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iob</hi> ſaw the like, for ſpeaking of the wicked, hee ſaith; <hi>Their ſeede is establiſhed in their ſight, and their generation before their eyes: their houſes are peaceable without feare, and the rod of God is not vpon them: they ſend forth their children as ſheepe, and their ſonnes daunce: their Bull gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and faileth not, their Cowe calueth, and casteth not her calfe, Iob</hi> 21.8, 9, 10, 11. Theſe were great bleſſings, and here was a goodly <hi>Bay-tree:</hi> but how ſoone they vaniſhed, and it was gone, they ſaw: and therefore hee addeth that, <hi>ſuddenly they went downe to the graue, verſe</hi> 13. their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to the earth, and their ſoules to hell.</p>
            <p>And (therefore) though their proſperitie were as great as that of that famous <hi>Polycrates</hi> among the <hi>Grecians,</hi> of whom it is written, that all things went ſo well with him, that when, in deſpight of that which they called <hi>Fortune,</hi> he caſt a Ring of no ſmall account into the Sea, it was brought againe vnto him in the belly of a fiſh, which was preſented to him by a poore fiſher-man: yet the curſe of God is in the meane while digging at their root; and their
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150376:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>houſe, with all that they hold precious, ſhall ſuddenly fall vpon themſelues: and of that houſe it ſhall be ſaid; <hi>the fall thereof was great, Mat.</hi> 7.27. For further proofe in this point we ſhall not neede to goe farre: Let vs but conſider what hath bin done at home lately, and it cannot but be freſh in our memories, how that ſome great in fauour at Court, and greatly feared for their Princes fauour in the Countrie; though they were neſtled among the Eagles, and gat vp into the ſides of the North with that Sonne of the morning; though they ioyned land to land, as if they would liue alone, and builded houſes as if they would liue euer, making no conſcience, by the commodious lying of <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard to their owne faire demaines, to take it from him, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.1. yet came downe ſuddenly, and their neſts with them in one day: one day in the Court of proſperitie, and the next day in the priſon of ſorrow, or hand of death.</p>
            <p>In the worlds opinion very ſtrong, and ſpreading very farre; when in Gods doome they had their <hi>MENE</hi> written vpon the wall, and their <hi>TEKEL</hi> told them in their eare, <hi>Daniel</hi> 5.5, 25. And how ſuddenly came they downe, like <hi>Ionahs</hi> Gourd, which grew in one night, and withered in another, <hi>Ion.</hi> 4.6, 7. when their flatterers thought them eternall? And no maruell, for what was their ſtrength, and in whom were they ſtrong, &amp; in whoſe account? With what armes ſpred they, and from what root? their ſtrength it was not the ſtrength of ſtones, <hi>Iob</hi> 6.12. and they truſted in fleſh; and fooles (onely) thought them happy: their armes were (but) armes of worldly largeneſſe, and their root rottenneſſe; their bagges were ſtuft with ſtolne wares; their houſes built vpon a ruinous ſoundation of violence, and they enlarged their lands with ſpoile: they flew to honour vpon wings of a proud and ambitious heart, and rode poſte, as vpon ſome <hi>Pegaſus,</hi> or winged horſe, to promotion: and in them the Prouerbe proued true; <hi>ſoone ripe, ſoone rotten:</hi> for the poore, <hi>they grinded their faoes;</hi> that is, they vſed them as cruelly as if they had taken a poore mans face, and ground it vpon a
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150376:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>grindle-ſtone: and for the rich, they fed vpon him, as beaſts in a fat paſture, till all was bitten bare alſo; as if they had learned of <hi>Neuiſſan</hi> a better Lawyer then honeſt man, that he that will not venture his body, ſhall neuer be valiant; nor he that will not venture his ſoule, be rich: they made ſpare of neither, for wicked greatneſſe and execrable wealth. They ſought outward things, but ſought not the Lord in them, which made them to thinke no way ſo neare and ready, as by the ſteps of wickedneſſe to aſcend vnto them: and ſo, as by euill they grew to be great, ſo by great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (the childe of euill) they grew to be worſe.</p>
            <p>Not content to be ſtrong, they muſt <hi>ſpread like a greene Bay:</hi> or (as ſome render it) like a tree that groweth of it ſelfe, hauing forgotten that root of princely grace out of which they firſt came. How can ſuch looke for any other end, then ſome ſudden cutting off? though they be as ſtrong as the ſtrong Oakes of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> and as tall and ſpreading as the Cedars of <hi>Libanus;</hi> how can it be but the Lord muſt needes deſtroy their fruit from aboue, and their root from beneath, and leaue them worth nothing, as hee tooke them with nothing when hee firſt aduanced them?</p>
            <p>Among theſe, there are ſome ambitious Church-men, who continually and altogether ſtudie a riſing by Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall dignities, either ſhamefully begged, or Simoniacal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bought: but when they are with Sathan vpon the pina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Temple, they tarrie not there long, but downe they come, not orderly by the ſtaires, but ſuddenly ſome other way, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.5, 6. And ſo in their higheſt pitch of worldly increaſe; <hi>Tolluntur in altum, vt lapſu grauiore ruant:</hi> they are lifted vp for a while, but to their greater fall: while that ſweet morſell of greatneſſe is in their mouthes, the <hi>wrath of the Lord is kindled againſt them, Pſal.</hi> 78.30, 31. as it is againſt all, who by ſuch ſtaires of pride, will needes climbe to promotion.</p>
            <p>Into the heart of this conſideration if wee would (indeede) enter, and (impartially) compare the vanitie of theſe things with the which they ſo ſwell, with the ſudden
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150376:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>and vnlooked for loſſe and departure of them, when they take them to their wings, we would be ſo farre from enuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that we would rather pitie their proſperitie; ſeeing that for the ſame abuſes, God will runne vpon them as with more furie, becauſe they haue couered their face with fatneſſe, and haue collops in their flankes, <hi>Iob</hi> 15.26, 27. That which we read in the Booke of <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> that <hi>the mightie ſhall be mightily tormented, Wiſd.</hi> 6.6. can giue them but poore and ſmall comfort; if they dye without confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in their mouth, and repentance in their hearts, though they dye neuer ſo great and mightie. And that we may not doubt of their fickle eſtate in theſe outward vncertaine things, the Prophet (therefore) addeth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>VERS. 36.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Yet he paſſed away, and loe, hee was gone, I ſought him but he could not be found.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>VVHere he ſheweth both what his eyes ſaw, and his experience got: namely, how hee found that the man, who truſted to the weake ſtaffe of worldly Pompe and greatneſſe, was ſuddenly gone, and before hee could be knowne; and vtterly, ſo as he ſhould neuer (after) bee remembred. For, howſoeuer that little time, which was lent vnto him to ſloriſh and ſpread in, ſeemed ſo long in the iudgement of worldly men, that they counted it an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the greeneneſſe of the Bay; yet was it ſo ſhort indeede, and in the iudgement of wiſe men ſo quickly gone, that it was liker (I ſaid it before, and I ſay it againe) liker to the greene graſſe, and the greene herbe that is mowen, and ſuddenly withereth, or as the corne that is blaſted before it be growne. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.26. For this cauſe, the wicked are compared, in the Scriptures, with things of ſmalleſt continuance, as to the <hi>ſat of Lambes,</hi> which is (cleane) conſumed, and (ſuddenly) <hi>as ſmoake, Pſal.</hi> 37.20. to <hi>waxe before the fire, Pſal.</hi> 68.2. to <hi>a dreame when one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waketh,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150376:49"/>Pſal.</hi> 73.20. and in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 41.11. <hi>to nothing. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing of the wicked</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob) is ſhort, and the ioy of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites is but for a moment. Iob</hi> 20. Hee ſaith it is <hi>ſhort,</hi> and (after) telles how <hi>ſhort:</hi> and further, hee ſaith; <hi>though his excellency mount vp to Heauen, and his head reach the Clouds, yet ſhall hee periſh like his dung, verſe</hi> 7. which is leſt for euer, as a loathſome thing; yea, he ſhall ſo bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, that <hi>they, who haue ſeene him, ſhall ſay, where is he? verſe</hi> 8. that is, what is become of him now? whither is the ſtate he held, the cappes and knees he had, gone? his honours in Court, <hi>as duſt before the winde,</hi> how are <hi>they ſcattered? Pſal.</hi> 1.4. and the ſtubble or chaffe of his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, how and whither is it carried, and how hath the ſtorm of God taken it? <hi>Iob</hi> 21.18. And what maruel, ſeeing hee put all his truſt in that which was nothing worth, and woue thoſe webbes which will make no garment, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed his labour, vpon that which will not couer him? <hi>Eſa.</hi> 59.5, 6.</p>
               <p>All this may teach vs, that the wicked (which are great) can leaue neither floriſhing rootes, nor laſting name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde them. For beſides that their ſtrokes ſhall bee at once, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.7. and God will ſuddenly viſit them, as in a raine of ſnares, fire and brimſtone, and ſtormy tempeſt, that will make a quicke hand and riddance where it falls, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.6. Their very name after their death ſhall feele a greater ſtroke of God vpon it, in that wound of reproch that it ſhall beare, and diſhonour that ſhall not bee done away: then they that ſee it ſhall ſay; <hi>How are the things of Eſau ſought out, how are his hidden things</hi> (or as ſome reade) <hi>treaſures ſearched?</hi> Obad. 6. Their <hi>name ſhall be put out,</hi> ſaith one, Pſal. 9.5. <hi>It ſhall be written in the duſt,</hi> ſaith ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Ier. 17.13. My text ſaith, <hi>they paſſe away and cannot be found:</hi> or there are but certaine rootes of houſes, where goodly houſes ſtood: What was the memoriall of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leck?</hi> Exod. 17.14. What but a fearefull ouerthrow and thing forgotten? ſuch a reward from God ſhall the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of the wicked haue, where the <hi>remembrance of Ioſiah</hi> (a vertuous Ruler) <hi>ſhall bee ſweete as hony in all mouthes,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150376:49"/>and as muſicke at a banket of wine;</hi> Eccleſ. 49.1. <hi>The name of the wicked ſhall rot,</hi> Prou. 10.7. And where the Lord ſaid to <hi>Moſes, I know thee by name, Exod.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.12. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith of the wicked, <hi>I will make no mention of their name with my lips, Pſal.</hi> 16.4.</p>
               <p>And thus their glory is turned to their ſhame, and their name aboue ground hath no better ſmell, then their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſſe in graue: and what maruell, ſeeing they are in no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with God, the onely thing that purchaſeth true credit with men? for God will diſhonour them that would not honour him; and <hi>they that deſpiſe him, ſhall be deſpiſed,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30, Beſides, it is iuſt that men ſhould haue their eſtimation according to their deeds: for, ſpeake well and heare well, doe well and haue well, and earne a good name and take it: but hee that ſinneth muſt needes take ſhame, he ſhall not continue in honour; and when hee dieth, his name ſhall periſh with him: or, hee ſhall goe hence, as a candle ill put out, that leaueth a ſtinke behinde it: for ſo <hi>ſhall his beautie conſume, when he ſhall goe from his houſe to graue, Pſal.</hi> 49.14.</p>
               <p>Let great men conſider this, and ye that call your Lands after your owne name, forget it not. They that would haue a good name when they are gone, muſt deſerue it here: for ſuch ſhall be well ſpoken of, or they haue wrong if they be not: but what wrong hath a godleſſe Atheiſt, a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous varlet, and impious ſinner to be buried in the duſt of his own ſhame? And what lye is it, not to ſpeak well of him or her that neuer did well? wee haue an ill prouerbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, ſpoken in ieſt, but practiſed in earneſt; which is, that <hi>Plaine dealing is a Iewell, but he ſhall dye a beggar and poore that vſeth it.</hi> And (therefore) as we read of <hi>Diony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> that becauſe he neuer ſailed more proſperouſly then when he had robbed the Church of <hi>Diana,</hi> he concluded, that the way to haue the fauor of the gods, was <hi>to rob their Churches:</hi> ſo by a falſe interpretation of Gods ſecret waies, ſome perſwade themſelues, that becauſe the wicked here floriſh for a while, wickedneſſe is the way to floriſh with them; and therefore putting their Maſters comming
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150376:50"/>farre off, they ſmite, <hi>to wit,</hi> with the fiſt of wickedneſſe, and of many wrongs, their innocent fellow ſeruants. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.48, 49. Some (againe) thinke to get a name, and to be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, if it be but for miſchiefe, that is, ſuch a name, and ſuch glory as <hi>Erostratus</hi> gate by burning <hi>Diana's</hi> Temple. But neither that Tyrant, nor this Incendiarie, liue in any other name now then ſuch as the Diuell himſelfe may be aſhamed of.</p>
               <p>And for thoſe who were much applauded in their times for wiſe, and valiant, and ouer-topping men (being (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes) vicious and ſinfull) what did after times, and what do ours ſay of them? We read what the time once thought of <hi>Haman,</hi> and how freſh his root was before his Soueraign. <hi>Heſter</hi> 3.1, 2. But becauſe it was ſet in euill Workes, how ſhort a time had it? And who doeth not (now) honour godly <hi>Mordecai,</hi> who was once ſo poore and baſe, not regarding, but (greatly) contemning that other proud Courtier, whoſe name ſo ſhon, for a while, couered with the robes of the Kings fauour? Who had ſuch an opinion for goodneſſe and holineſſe, as the Phariſes once had? And now, who can patiently endure the name of Phariſe, that knowes what a Phariſe was? And did not wicked <hi>Herod,</hi> who (aliue) was reputed a God; dying giue vp his name with his life to the wormes? <hi>Acts</hi> 12.23. So <hi>Achitophels</hi> politicke head after it had bin in a halter, what name did it leaue? 2 <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 17.23. how glorious was <hi>Wolſey</hi> and <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner</hi> once? and how did <hi>Boner,</hi> the Popes ſlaughterman, once ruffle, when he ſent ſo many Innocents (ſo cruelly) by fire, to martyrdome? and (yet) what are their execrable names now, to the bleſſed names of thoſe whoſe <hi>life they thought to be madneſſe, and their end without honour, Wiſd.</hi> 5.4. and who (now) had not rather be a <hi>Hooper,</hi> a <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> a <hi>Latimer, Bradford,</hi> and <hi>Ridley,</hi> then the greateſt of theſe? alſo, <hi>Naboths</hi> name, is it not now farre better then <hi>Ahabs</hi> that was <hi>ſold to ſinne,</hi> and <hi>Iezebels</hi> that was <hi>giuen to Dogges?</hi> and they that ſtoned him, doe (I doubt not) now wiſh that they had bin ſtoned for him.</p>
               <p>May it not be ſaid of all theſe, and of all like theſe, that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150376:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>they are paſt and gone; their houſes, their Empires, their names and all, leauing their poſteritie, the heires of their diſhonour? haue they not all in their names of diſcredit, made their iuſt account for all the pleaſures and vniuſt peace of their life paſt? and what is left vnto them of all their former glory and vnruly greatneſſe, but that which they are the righteſt owners of; reproach and inſamie throughout all ages? But let vs paſſe to that other part of this Scripture, the moſt certaine and conſtant happineſſe of the righteous, leauing the wicked in their ſhame, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall blacke night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>VERS. 37.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Marke the vpright man, and behold the iuſt: for the end of that man is peace.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THeſe are worthy the marking and ſeeing, and the end they come vnto, is worth the hauing: for they are <hi>vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and iuſt men,</hi> and their <hi>end is peace.</hi> By the <hi>vpright and iuſt man,</hi> wee may vnderſtand the man that is godly, both in habit of minde and behauiour; or good, both in heart and conuerſation: and by <hi>peace,</hi> the Prophet meaneth tranquilitie here, and eternall reſt from our labours in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; this tranquilitie is of minde, and in Chriſt: for in the world we ſhall haue affliction, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.33. The effect of all is: the proſperitie of the wicked doth quickly come, and ſuddenly paſſe: but the peace of the righteous comes in their latter end, and continues world without end. Where the Prophets meaning is, that the godly muſt firſt meete with troubles, and then haue peace: (firſt) <hi>ſowe in teares,</hi> and then <hi>reape in ioy, Pſal.</hi> 126.5. and (firſt) be racked, and then deliuered, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. ſo much he giues vs to learne in this verſe: for the tenure that Chriſtians hold by, is the Croſſe; and this Croſſe of Chriſtians triumpheth not here: here, <hi>all that will liue godly, muſt ſuffer perſecution,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. and from afflictions, not from our beds of caſe, we are taken to heauen: for through many afflictions, as
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:150376:51"/>through the ſtraight gate, we muſt paſſe thither, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22. and great reaſon, we ſhould climbe with ſome difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie this mountaine of bliſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.1. for why ſhould not we (the members, of Chriſt) be like our head as well in his crowne of thornes as in his crowne of glory, and as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly in his cup, as in his precious ſaluation? or, how can we thinke that God ſhould wipe away our teares in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life, when wee haue ſhed none in this? <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.4. and how can we be taken out of miſerie, when (here) wee know no woe? Affliction (then) being both our begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and middle, as peace is our end, if wee be right Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; our way to heauen is marked out vnto vs, and the markes of our direct way thither, are perſecutions in this world, before wee can obtaine <hi>eternall life in the world to come, Mar.</hi> 10.30. But doe wee ſwimme in delights, that ſhould ſwim through a Sea of burning glaſſe? <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.2. Is our beginning peace? are our mid-dayes all in peace? that is, haue we perpetuall peace and quietneſſe in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and ſoules, goods and good name: when peace in all theſe is promiſed at our end, not before and after our war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare accompliſhed, not while we are in the field? then wee goe not as we are directed by our markes, to ſaluation. It is a narrow way of little eaſe, and wee are in a broad way of pleaſures, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13.14. it is vp-hill thither, and wee goe downe-hill, that is, not toward it, but from it: and it is a way of many troubles, but we liue at eaſe in Sion.</p>
               <p>By all this we may well know that we are out of that one right &amp; plaine way to life. Where on the other ſide, if in our names we ſuffer, for our zeale in the Law: if we mourne (in our ſoules) for the ſinnes we behold in the world, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not maſter in our ſelues: if we will looſe our goods, rather then a good conſcience in any commandement: and put not vp the ſword of the ſpirituall battaile till corruption be done away, which will neuer be whiles we be here, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. wee know by this our way to happineſſe ſo painfull and troubleſome, that <hi>we are not far from the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</hi> And ſo we may conclude that they are fooles, and not wiſe, who thinke thoſe beſt that are at beſt eaſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:150376:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>here, &amp; thoſe freeſt from miſery, that are furtheſt from trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. But what Oxe is likeſt to come, firſt to the Butchers axe? That which is fed in the beſt paſtures, or which is kept in the bareſt grounds? Surely the fat Oxe is neerer the ſlaughter, then that which is kept low for ſtore, or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. So Chriſtians, fatted with eaſe, and pampered with the pleaſures of life, are in greater danger of the Butcher of Hell, then they that are kept low with troubles, and haue the World for their enemie, and not at their will, as Satans ſtalled men haue. And here let all that are oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of thoſe fat kine of Baſhan, that feede in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Samaria: <hi>Am.</hi> 4.1. all that are thruſt at by the fat and ſtrong ſheepe of theſe Worldly paſtures. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 34.21. All that are troden downe by the mighty and proud, that ſo ſpreade among vs, neuer faint in their troubles; or, when they ſuffer for righteouſnes, in ſo direct away to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, goe backe with feare and diſcouragement, becauſe of theſe beginnings: For, peace will come, at leaſt when their end comes; for, their end is peace. Hetherto ſerues that comfortable, and moſt ſweet exhortation of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt to the Chriſtians of his time, and (in them) to vs at this day: <hi>Feare yee not them which kill the body, and are not able to kill the ſoule, but feare him who is able to deſtroy both ſoule and body in Hell. Math.</hi> 10.28. Becauſe the heart of man will euer feare ſome thing, Chriſt telleth vs whom wee ſhould feare, and what, that wee may not feare, where there is no cauſe, nor, where there is cauſe, hee ſenſeleſſe. At any hand, hee will not haue vs to feare man too much; for, that is a note of them that feare him too little. And if we neede not to feare mortall man, liuing in the true feare of the immortall God, what cauſe is there that wee ſhould bee ſhaken with their wrongs, as leaues ſhaken with the winde, when they are ſo mooued againſt vs? For, when they haue done their worſt, peace ſhall come, the more they force vs, the ſooner they ſend vs, out of our houſes of clay, to our houſe aboue; and what harme is it to die once, that wee may liue euer? Yet, they that are ſo cruelly bent to harme vs, haue but a borrowed power ouer vs, and wee
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:150376:52"/>no more Maſters of our liues, then the leaſt Spider is of theirs, which by permiſſion can kill them, aſſoone, and deadly, as by power giuen them, they can kill vs. Which being well and rightly conſidered, how weake is our faith, and how little worth, that will bee ſo much diſmaide with the ſilly blaſts of ſimple men, whoſe power is mortall, and bounded by a higher power? Some, in a little thunder from the Court, turne as drinke in a veſſell, not keeping their righteouſneſſe, longer then they can quietly hold it with the good liking of greatneſſe: and ſome, if they bee but threatned by theſe men of might, fall downe, as if they were killed by them. But hee that lookes for peace from him that can giue it, and vp to him from whom onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth his helpe, will not be amazed for any thing that man can doe. For hee knowes that, if hee keepe in with God, mans euill will ſhall either be reconciled, or ſhall doe him no hurt. And hee that knowes ſo much, will neuer turne from man a ſmoake, to turne vpon God a conſuming fire, or make man his friend with Gods enmitie. <hi>Ioſeph, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Daniels</hi> three fellowes, had great knowledge this way: therefore <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> when hee was tempted to wickedneſſe, would (in no caſe) yeeld; <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.10. God was his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and hee could not take pleaſure in that which God abhorreth; neither would he ſet God againſt him, to make his Miſtris his friend. <hi>Daniel</hi> feared the King (as was fit) but feared the Lord more then all Kings; and therefore when the King commanded that which was diſhonourable to God, the higheſt King, hee rather yeelded his body to the Lions, then his obedience in ſuch a matter. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10.16 Alſo <hi>Daniels</hi> three fellowes muſt either bow to an Idole, or burne in a fierie furnace, ſeuen times heated: <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.15.19. but what of that? Not doubting but the God whom they ſerued wold deliuer them, as they knew he was able; they denied to ſerue any but him, that is Lord of all: and yet (if hee ſhould not deliuer them) they would neuer bee drawne to doe the Kings commandement againſt his. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.17.18. Thus they reſolued, and no threatnings of Tyrants, nor iniuries of men could alter them. The reaſon
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:150376:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>was, they tooke his word for their peace, who promiſeth to deliuer his; and therefore they fainted not, in any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. They knew that it cannot but bee well with them that feare the Lord, and doe reuerence before him; that is, well at the laſt: <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.12. Though not ſo with the ſinner whom God ſpareth long, though hee doe euill an hundred times; that is, ſinne without end or meaſure, for it ſhall not be well to him, neither ſhall he prolong his dayes. <hi>ver.</hi> 13. But to proceede further with you, in ſome further benefit of this Scripture: here it is apparent what an intereſt they haue in God, and to his gracious prouidence, that are vpright and iuſt men. Their end is peace, that is, they cannot miſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and they ſhall bee ſure to ſpeede well at the laſt, that make him their confidence. And that Gods children (iuſt and vpright men) in whoſe heart his Word is, ſhall not want ſafety and comfort long, <hi>Dauid</hi> in another Pſalme teacheth vs, for ſpeaking of ſuch, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.9. hee ſaith that nothing ſhall be wanting to them, that is, nothing that for them ſhall appeare to be (abſolutely and neceſſarily) good. For the Angel of the Lord ſhall keepe them, <hi>verſe</hi> 7. and they can take no hurt, and the Lord himſelfe will deliuer them, <hi>ver.</hi> 18.19. and how can they periſh, <hi>ver.</hi> 22. his eyes are vpon them, <hi>verſe</hi> 15. hee ſeeth their troubles, and eares open to them, he heareth when they crie. Doth he ſee and heare, and will hee not regard? Nay, but he redeemeth the ſoules of his ſeruants, and they ſhall not bee deſolate, but they that hate them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall. <hi>ver.</hi> 21. And though <hi>Dauid</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was in many perils, at home by <hi>Saul,</hi> abroad by other enemies; yet neither <hi>Saul</hi> nor they could take his pillow from him at night, but he did lie downe in peace, and ſleep, hauing his dwelling in ſafety. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.8. And this, becauſe hee had the promiſe of God for a wall about him. <hi>Daniel</hi> among the hungry Lyons, came out ſafely: <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.23. and <hi>Daniels</hi> three fellowes in a very hote furnace walked ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely, and without hurt. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.25. So <hi>Pauls</hi> deliuerances were as many as his troubles, afflicted on euery ſide, yet not in diſtreſſe; in pouertie, but not ouercome of pouerty, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, but not forſaken, caſt downe, but he periſhed not.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:150376:53"/>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8, 9. For hee ſhooke off theſe vipers with ſafety, <hi>Act.</hi> 28.5. and they had no power againſt him, to hurt him. Thus the iuſt haue beene, are, and ſhall be deliuered, and it cannot bee other wiſe; for the Lord being their ſhield, they that ſtrike at them, muſt ſtrike through him, before they can be touched; they are thoſe faithfull ſeruants, and loyall ſubiects, whom a good Maſter, and gracious Prince will countenance. And where they that are obedient ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to a good Maſter, are in fauour, and grow in wealth: ſhall wee thinke that vpright, and iuſt men (the good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God) can long liue in miſery, and die vnrewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? Hath godlineſſe, the promiſe of this life, and of that to come? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. And ſhal the godly miſſe of their peace, here and hereafter, now and continually? Surely, if the Couenant that God hath made betweene the day and night can be broken, <hi>Ier.</hi> 33.20. this may be: or, if it can faile to bee day and night in their ſeaſon, the vpright mans peace may faile, when his end is come. <hi>Dauid</hi> knew this, and therefore in another Pſalme, ſtood vpon it, with <hi>a verely,</hi> there is fruit for the righteous, as ſurely, as there is a God that iudgeth in the earth. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.11. Here is a plaiſter of much vertue, and of as much good vſe, for the ſores of thoſe broken conſciences, which Sathan hath wounded for well-doing. With the ſtorme in their faces they cannot ſee how it ſhould bee peace, where there are ſo many skirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes in the houſe, and without doores; ſo many alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and breakings, and ſo much a doe, to obtaine a dayes truce with the enemie of their peace. But marke the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man, and behold the iuſt; that is, looke vpon them with a Spirituall eye, and as when men marke a thing that they ſtill keepe their eye vpon; and yee ſhall finde nothing but peace in all their wayes. Their falles make them wary and circumſpect, how, and where they walke: their buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings humble them, that they may bee raiſed; their bitter draughts, are compounds of the Lords owne making to purge them: their complaints of the want of faith, are the beſt kinde of faith; and leſt they ſhould decay in zeale, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are the bellowes to blow the fire. Alſo we know
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:150376:53"/>that all things worke together for the beſt, vnto them that loue God, and are called of his purpoſe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. And if all things, then afflictions, then Satans rage, and the Worlds vniuſt malice for good deedes. For what are theſe, other then certaine bitter remedies to correctour corruptions, or exerciſes of Gods graces in vs, to trie how much we wil ſuffer for his ſake? And who can denie the name and worke of peace, to theſe temptations that are ſent not to conſume vs like droſſe, but to refine vs like gold? Or, is this end of them, any other then peace? But (ſpecially) this concerneth the troubles that are inflicted vpon the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, by the Worlds ſpite, and by Tyrants that ſeeke their life. And it aſſureth them, whatſoeuer their troubles are, and of what malice or greatneſſe ſo euer they be that trouble them, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance (which is their peace) ſhall come. Many are the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of the righteous, yea, great, and many; yet the Lord deliuereth him out of them all. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.19. And the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaking of the afflictions which came vnto him at Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochia, at Iconium, and at Liſtri, ſaith, but from them al the Lord deliuered me. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.11. The Church ſtories afford vs a large reading in this argument, and the booke of God is plentifull in this matter; alſo, I haue ſpoken ſufficiently hereof (already) for comfort. But now, if wee will haue our parts with iuſt and vpright men in theſe deliuerances, and in their peace; we muſt walke vprightly, and by ſteps of righteouſneſſe come to receiue our parts in them, with the people whom God will ſaue. The Lord that promiſed his Angels to vs in our wayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.11. hath made vs no promiſe of ſafetie by them in other wayes. In the good way of a Chriſtian life, we are ſure to be kept: but it is the Diuell that tels vs, wee ſhall be ſo in any way. <hi>Math.</hi> 4.6. The vpright and iuſt men ſhall haue peace, ſhall it therefore be well to the wicked? Wee haue heard God, by <hi>Salomon,</hi> to ſay no: and <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith there is no peace to the wicked, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57.21. that is, none either with, or for them. Had <hi>Zimri</hi> peace who ſlew his Maſter? 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.31. <hi>Iezebel</hi> (that painted dogges<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meate) could tell he had nor. And indeed, what peace (as <hi>Iehu</hi> ſaid to <hi>Iehoram</hi>) where <hi>Iezebel</hi> and her fornications, the wicked, and their wicked deedes are? 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.22. <hi>Doe men gather grapes of thornes? Math.</hi> 7.16. That is, will the grape of peace,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150376:54"/>grow vpon the thorne of wickedneſſe. Let there be no roote among you (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>that bringeth foorth gall and worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood. Deut.</hi> 29.18. And why no ſuch roote of bitternes among them? He (after) giues the reaſon, becauſe there is no bleſſing in it: it is that roote of ſinne, whoſe doome is the curſe, and whoſe end is to be burned. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8. For he (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) when he heares the words of the curſe, bleſſeth himſelfe in his heart, ſaying, I ſhall haue peace, though he walke in the ſtubbornes of his heart, and adde drunkenneſſe to thirſt. But ſhall it bee ſo? Shall he haue peace that walketh in his ſinnes ſtubbornely? No ſaith that man of God; the Lord will not be mercifull to him; but the wrath of the Lord, and his ielouſie ſhall ſmoake againſt him, and euery curſe that is written in the booke of the law ſhall light him, till it haue put out his name from vnder heauen. <hi>Deu.</hi> 29.19.20. Therefore it is but the poiſon of flattery (a poiſon which ſtriketh to the heart) that perſwadeth the ſinner that he may liue in ſin, and die in peace. For God, by <hi>Ezechiel</hi> telles vs, that, ſeeing he hath ſo done, <hi>he ſhall die the death, and his blood ſhall bee vpon him. Ezech.</hi> 18.13. And how can wee thinke, that hauing had (all our life time) warre with God in our ſinnes, we ſhould eaſily bee reconciled to him on our death bead? Yet fooles and vnwiſe ſo thinke; or, what is their hope when they lie a dying? Surely, their hope is as the dead hope of a Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor in priſon, who puts of the getting of his pardon, till the Iudge be come to condemne him. But we are called to a better hope; let vs therefore walke as the vpright man, and not put off, as ſinners: ſo ſhall our end be peace, when theirs ſhall bee in deſtruction. In this mind and courſe, though the world ſhall count vs vnhappie, yet we muſt thinke our ſelues, and the wiſe will iudge vs the moſt happie men. And I pray you, who was more happie, <hi>Lazarus</hi> going from his ſores, and pouerty to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: or the rich man, that went fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his purple, and delicate fare to Hell? <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.22, 23. We ſay that the end makes all; &amp; Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy ſaith, that no man is either happie, or miſerable, that is, truely ſo, before his end. If we cannot bee ſo wiſe as Chriſtians ſhould, yet it is ſhame, to be more fooliſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heathen were And what reaſon (then) to iudge of men by their preſent ſtates, when it is not the preſent, but future, nor this temporal, but that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150376:54"/>other eternall condition of bliſſe, or vnhappines that muſt giue vs our iuſt ſtandard, or meaſure in theſe matters? And therefore it is ſaid to good purpoſe, by the Prophet further in this verſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marke and behold, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe two words are added as a bridle, to keepe vs in, that we runne not into raſh judgement, when wee heare of the many troubles of the godly, and of the few of thoſe that offend, euen with purpoſe of heart to doe wickedly. For great fooliſhneſſe is bound vp to our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſo farre foorth as wee conſiſt of fleſh, and ſee as naturall men: our reaſon is exceeding weake: and for our naturall light, what is it but darkeneſſe and errour? And therefore great need we haue of this bridle or bit, from haſtie opinion. Great need I ſay, leſt wee binde a falſe note (not onely) to mans courſes which we vnderſtand not, (but euen) to Gods moſt wiſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, which no man can know, For this cauſe, the Prophet bids vs to marke and behold, as it were, to looke with both eyes, diligently to conſider, and faithfully to lay vp the experience that we gather in ſuch high matters: not to take things as they appeare preſently, but as the end leaues them. When a man runnes very faſt and ſwiftly, his eyes will dazle at things; ſo will they not when hee goes faire and ſoftly, or with a deliberate pace. In like manner, let vs goe deliberately, and wiſely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in our iudgements, and they will not dazell at the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie of the wicked that are ſuddenly ſet vp; and where o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers make more haſte then good ſpeede to ſalute them, as happie, wee will take leaſure and time to our opinion of them, and ſay, their end is not yet. From hence wee learne not to iudge any man, by his preſent outward eſtate, to be happie, or miſerable. For whatſoeuer we ſee in men to day, may be much altered to morrow, and the laſt may be firſt. <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.16.</p>
               <p>And this true iudgement in things and of perſons, if it were rightly conſidered, and if wee would wiſely iudge of them by their ends, and not as they ſeeme; would ſtay vs from being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended to a fretting at the wicked for their ſudden proſperitie: or to a condemning of the iuſt for their preſent diſtreſſe. The contrary muſt needes make vs ſtumble in iudgement, and to be offended with our troubles when they continue long. I ſay ſtumble in iudgement; for what man, if hee ſhould iudge of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150376:55"/>
                  <hi>Iobs</hi> election by that which he ſometimes ſpake, and of <hi>Dauids</hi> by that which he once did; the one when hee ſpake ſo vnadui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly againſt God, <hi>Iob</hi> 3.6.10.13. chapters: the other when he lay in ſo foule ſheetes hauing defiled his bed with adultery, and the murther of his deareſt ſeruant <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.4 5.15.17. or if he ſhould weigh <hi>Ieremie</hi> at the rate of that which he ſpake in his diſtemper: and Chriſt himſelfe at that, which (as man) in the hoteſt fornace of his paſſion he complained of his to his father, namely that he had <hi>forſaken him, Ier.</hi> 12.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.14.15, 16, 17, 18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.40. What man (I ſay) if hee ſhould thus iudge, ſhould not condemne (euen) the generation of Gods children, and the ſonne himſelfe? who would thinke that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> two old men (the one foureſcore, the other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue) <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.7. could, going to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> with a little rod in their hand, bring the children of Iſrael out of Egypt in deſpight of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the King thereof? <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.26. yet they refuſed not the ſeruice at Gods commandement, being old men, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with ſimple meanes: where if they had reſted on no more then that which they ſaw or was preſent, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue beleeued they could haue forced a great King in his owne Kingdome to let his priſoners goe; but they ſaw him, and in him (that was inuiſible) great ſaluation, and greater power then either <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or all the <hi>Pharaohs</hi> of the earth could reſiſt; and therefore ſuſpended all iudgement of fleſh to the contrary. Whoſe hart would not faile him (if he ſhould truſt his eyes) to ſee the ſucceſſe of a battaile to hang vpon a youth, fighting (hand to hand) with a great armed Gyant, and man of war; &amp; not with ſpeare or ſhield, but with a <hi>ſling in his hand, and fiue ſmooth ſtones?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.33.40. <hi>Saul</hi> doubted how it could be, but <hi>Dauid</hi> doubted not, <hi>ver.</hi> 33. <hi>Saul</hi> could beleeue no more then he ſaw; <hi>Dauid</hi> beleeued God, and had ſeene his power before, <hi>ver.</hi> 35.36. which hee alſo (then) ſaw in a ſort, waiting for the end: and this end was it, that his eyes were vpon by faith, by which he receiued it before it came. <hi>Gideons</hi> men that were left, were but 300. but his enemies lay in the valley like Graſhoppers, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7.6.12. and what muſt theſe three hundred haue in their hands? nothing but Trumpets in one hand, and emptie pitchers with lamps in another: and what
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:150376:55"/>muſt they doe? blow their Trumpets and breake their pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: and what ſhall enſue when this is done? <hi>The Lord will ſet variance in the hoste, and ſetting euery mans ſword vpon his neighbor, cauſe them to ſlie, ver.</hi> 16, 20, 22. And now, who mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring theſe things with the eye, can thinke that ſo few ſhould be able to driue ſo many with ſo weake purſuers? But <hi>Gideon</hi> looked to the end, and ſtaied not in the meanes, and ſo marked and beheld till the end came. So <hi>Ioſhua</hi> before him, muſt <hi>breake downe the wals of Ierico:</hi> but with what warlike engine, with what rain of iron muſt he doe it? <hi>with blowing ſeuen Trumpets of rams hornes (ſeuen times) with a ſhout,</hi> and with no other power, <hi>Ioſh</hi> 6.13, 15, 16. God ſpake it, <hi>Ioſhua</hi> beleeued it; and the <hi>wals of the Citie,</hi> at the appointed time, <hi>fell downe, ver.</hi> 20. To heape vp more examples would be too long and needeleſſe in ſo plaine a matter.</p>
               <p>The conſideration of this that hath bin ſpoken, as it is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of all haſty and raſh iudging of matters and perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time: ſo it cannot but miniſter great conſolation to the godly, where there is little in the meanes and time to giue them hope; for though preſently they can ſee nothing that is for their helpe, and though in troubleſome difficulties, all things (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingly) make againſt them; yet <hi>comfort and deliuerance will come from one place or another, Heſt.</hi> 4.14. And ſo wee haue heard how we may faile in iudgement, if wee iudge things or perſons raſhly, or before the time. Now as wee may erre in iudgement, ſo we may be offended at the things that come, if we wait not for the end; that is, offer not our obedience in wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for it: which would be conſidered of thoſe, who if the Lord ſuſpend his anſwer and helping of them after ſome time that they haue praied for a hearing, doe through an impatient ſpirit, forſake all, both attendance, and hopes. And (here) ſome, who can bee violent at firſt and for ſome time, are euen cut to the heart when they are put to a longer day: but to be vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a while, and not importunate long for the good things that we aske according to the good minde of God in his word, is (beſides the loſſe of our labour) a deſerued falling from the fruit of our requeſts, which (by the meanes of ſuch faintings) muſt needes faile vs. To remedie all this, we muſt wait (conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually)
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:150376:56"/>by the word for our enlargement in troubles when they tarry long. But beſides this ſinne of impatience in matters that concerne our ſelues: wee may ſinne againſt God by fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt others, namely, the wicked that are lift vp, if wee fondly meaſure them by their preſent eſtate, and not wiſely by their end. <hi>Dauid,</hi> becauſe hee (once) meaſured them with the wrong meaſure of that that was preſent, confeſſeth that hee was fooliſh and ignorant this way, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.22. And how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny beſides him (otherwaies no ill men) hath this falſe interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of happineſſe, in her ſhort and quicke blaze (ſuch as ſhe maketh in wicked men) put into intollerable fits of choller a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God? How much haue they bin offended, and how ill haue they taken it that the wicked ſhould fare ſo well, and the godly no better? It appeareth by the firſt verſe of this <hi>Pſalme,</hi> that in <hi>Dauids</hi> time, many were ouercome of this temptation, who in other things could ſtand ſure: and (all) becauſe they forgat the wicked mans miſerable end, and the happy end of the righteous. But this I touched ſufficiently in the beginning, becauſe it is the maine ſcope of this whole <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I leaue it (and all that hath bin ſpoken beſides) to God, and to the <hi>worke of his grace, who is able to build you further, and to giue you an inheritance among all them that are ſanctified, Acts</hi> 20.32. <hi>The God of peace, that brought againe from the dead our Lord Ieſus the great ſhepheard of the ſheepe through the bloud of the euerlasting couenant, make you perfect in all good workes to doe his will; working in you that which is pleaſant in his ſight through Ieſus Chriſt; to whom be praiſe for euer and euer.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
